What I want to do today
is continue our discussion of Na.ve Bayes,
which is the learning algorithm that
I started to discuss in the previous lecture
and talk about a couple of
different event models in Na.ve Bayes,
and then I'll take a brief digression
to talk about neural networks,
which is something that
I actually won't spend a lot of time on,
and then I want to start to talk about
support vector machines,
and support vector machines
is the learning algorithms,
the supervised learning algorithm that
many people consider the most effective,
off-the-shelf supervised learning algorithm.
That point of view is debatable,
but there are many people that
hold that point of view,
and we'll start discussing that today,
and this will actually take us
a few lectures to complete.
So let's talk about Na.ve Bayes.
To recap from the previous lecture,
I started off describing spam classification
as the most [inaudible] example for Na.ve Bayes
in which we would create feature vectors like these,
right, that correspond to words in a dictionary.
And so, you know, based on
what words appear in a piece of email
were represented as a feature vector with
ones and zeros in the corresponding places,
and Na.ve Bayes was a generative learning algorithm,
and by that I mean it's an algorithm
in which we model PFX given Y,
and for Na.ve Bayes, specifically,
we modeled it as product from I equals one to N,
PFXI given Y,
and also we model PFY,
and then we use Bayes Rule, right,
to combine these two together,
and so our predictions,
when you give it a new piece of email
you want to tell if it's spam or not spam,
you predict RFX over Y, PFY given X,
which by Bayes Rule is RFX over Y,
PFX given Y, times BY, okay?
So this is Na.ve Bayes,
and just to draw attention to two things,
one is that in this model,
each of our features were zero, one,
so indicating whether different words appear,
and the length or the feature vector was, sort of,
the length N of the feature vector
was the number of words in the dictionary.
So it might be on this version
on the order of 50,000 words, say.
What I want to do now
is describe two variations on this algorithm.
The first one is the simpler one,
which it's just a generalization to
if XI takes on more values. So, you know,
one thing that's commonly done
is to apply Na.ve Bayes to problems
where some of these features, XI,
takes on K values rather than just two values,
and in that case, you actually build, sort of,
a very similar model where PFX given Y
is really the same thing, right,
where now these are going to
be multinomial probabilities rather than Bernoulli's
because the XI's can, maybe,
take on up to K values.
It turns out, the situation where
one situation where this arises very commonly is
if you have a feature
that's actually continuous valued,
and you choose to dispertise it,
and you choose to
take a continuous value feature and dispertise it
into a finite set of K values,
and so it's a perfect example
if you remember our very first supervised learning
problem of predicting the price of houses.
If you have the classification
problem on these houses,
so based on features of a house,
and you want to predict whether or not
the house will be sold in the next six months, say.
That's a classification problem,
and once you use Na.ve Bayes,
then given a continuous value feature
like the living area, you know,
one pretty common thing to do
would be take the continuous value living area
and just dispertise it into a few
discreet buckets, and so depending on whether
the living area of the house
is less than 500 square feet
or between 1,000 and 1500 square feet, and so on,
or whether it's greater than 2,000 square feet,
you choose the value of the corresponding feature,
XI, to be one, two, three, or four, okay?
So that was the first variation or generalization
of Na.ve Bayes I wanted to talk about.
I should just check;
are there questions about this? Okay. Cool.
And so it turns out that in practice,
it's fairly common to use about ten buckets
to dispertise a continuous value feature.
I drew four here only to save on writing.
The second and, sort of, final variation that
I want to talk about for Na.ve Bayes
is a variation that's specific
to classifying text documents, or,
more generally, for classifying sequences.
So the text document, like a piece of email,
you can think of as a sequence of words
and you can apply this, sort of,
model I'm about to describe
to classifying other sequences as well,
but let me just focus on text,
and here's the idea.
So the Na.ve Bayes algorithm
as I've described it so far, right,
given a piece of email, we were representing it
using this binary vector value representation,
and one of the things that this loses,
for instance, is the number of times that
different words appear, all right?
So, for example, if some word appears a lot of times,
and you see the word, you know,
"buy" a lot of times.
You see the word "Viagra";
it seems to be a common email example.
You see the word Viagra a ton of times in the email,
it is more likely to be spam than it appears,
I guess, only once
because even once,
I guess, is enough.
So let me just try a different,
what's called an event model for Na.ve Bayes
that will take into account the number of times
a word appears in the email,
and to give this previous model a name
as well this particular model
for text classification is called
the Multivariate Bernoulli Event Model.
It's not a great name.
Don't worry about what the name means.
It refers to the fact that
there are multiple Bernoulli random variables,
but it's really
don't worry about what the name means.
In contrast, what I want to do now
is describe a different representation
for email in terms of the feature vector,
and this is called the Multinomial Event Model, and,
again, there is a rationale behind the name,
but it's slightly cryptic,
so don't worry about why it's called
the Multinomial Event Model;
it's just called that.
And here's what we're gonna do,
given a piece of email,
I'm going to represent my email
as a feature vector,
and so my ith training example,
XI will be a feature vector, XI sub group one,
XI sub group two, XI subscript NI where NI is equal to
the number of words in this email, right?
So if one of my training examples
is an email with 300 words in it,
then I represent this email via a feature vector
with 300 elements,
and each of these elements of the feature vector
lets see. Let me just write this as X subscript J.
These will be an index into my dictionary, okay?
And so if my dictionary has 50,000 words,
then each position in my feature vector will be
a variable that takes on one of 50,000 possible values
corresponding to what word appeared
in the J position of my email, okay?
So, in other words, I'm gonna take
all the words in my email
and you have a feature vector that
just says which word in my dictionary
was each word in the email, okay?
So a different definition for NI now,
NI now varies and is different for
every training example,
and this XJ is now indexed into the dictionary.
You know, the components of the feature vector
are no longer binary random variables;
they're these indices in the dictionary that
take on a much larger set of values.
And so our generative model for this will be that
the joint distribution over X and Y will be that,
where again N is now the length of the email,
all right? So the way to think about
this formula is you imagine that
there was some probably distribution over emails.
There's some random distribution that
generates the emails,
and that process proceeds as follows:
First, Y is chosen, first the class label.
Is someone gonna send you spam email or
not spam emails is chosen for us.
So first Y, the random variable Y,
the class label of spam
or not spam is generated,
and then having decided whether
they sent you spam or not spam,
someone iterates over all 300 positions of the email,
or 300 words that are going to
compose them as email,
and would generate words from some distribution
that depends on whether they chose
to send you spam or not spam.
So if they sent you spam,
they'll send you words
they'll tend to generate words like,
you know, buy, and Viagra,
and whatever at discounts, sale, whatever.
And if somebody chose to send you not spam,
then they'll send you, sort of,
the more normal words you get in an email, okay?
So, sort of, just careful, right?
XI here has a very different definition
from the previous event model,
and N has a very different definition from
the previous event model.
And so the parameters of this model are
let's see. Phi subscript K given Y equals one,
which is the probability that, you know,
conditioned on someone deciding
to spend you spam,
what's the probability that
the next word they choose
to email you in the spam email
is going to be word K, and similarly, you know,
sort of, same thing
well, I'll just write it out, I guess
and Phi Y and just same as before, okay?
So these are the parameters of the model,
and given a training set,
you can work out the
maximum likelihood estimates of the parameters.
So the maximum likelihood estimate of
the parameters will be equal to
and now I'm gonna write one of these,
you know, big indicator function things again.
It'll be a sum over your training sets indicator
whether that was spam times the sum
over all the words in that email
where N subscript I is the number of words
in email I in your training set,
times indicator XIJ, SK times that I, okay?
So the numerator says sum over all your emails
and take into account all the emails that
had class label one,
take into account only of the emails that
were spam because if Y equals zero,
then this is zero, and this would go away,
and then times sum over all the words
in your spam email,
and it counts up the number of times
you observed the word K in your spam emails.
So, in other words, the numerator is look at
all the spam emails in your training set
and count up the total number of times
the word K appeared in this email.
The denominator then
is sum over I into our training set of whenever
one of your examples is spam, you know,
sum up the length of that spam email,
and so the denominator is the total length of
all of the spam emails in your training set.
And so the ratio is just out of all your spam emails,
what is the fraction of words in all
your spam emails that were word K,
and that's your estimate for the probability of
the next piece of spam mail generating
the word K in any
given position, okay?
At the end of the previous lecture,
I talked about LaPlace smoothing,
and so when you do that as well,
you add one to the numerator and K
to the denominator,
and this is the LaPlace
smoothed estimate of this parameter, okay?
And similarly, you do the same thing for
and you can work out the estimates
for the other parameters yourself, okay?
So it's very similar. Yeah?
Student:I'm sorry. On the right on the top,
I was just wondering what the X of I is,
and what the N of
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Right.
So in this second event model, the definition for XI
and the definition for N are different, right?
So here well, this is for one example XY. So here,
N is the number of words in a given email, right?
And if it's the I email subscripting
then this N subscript I,
and so N will be different for
different training examples,
and here XI will be, you know,
these values from 1 to 50,000,
and XI is essentially the identity of
the Ith word in a given piece of email, okay?
So that's why this is grouping,
or this is a
product over all the different words of
your email of their probability the Ith word
in your email, conditioned on Y. Yeah?
Student:[Off mic].
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, no, actually,
you know what, I apologize.
I just realized that overload the notation, right,
and I shouldn't have used K here.
Let me use a different alphabet
and see if that makes sense;
does that make sense?
Oh, you know what, I'm sorry.
You're absolutely right.
Thank you. All right.
So in LaPlace smoothing, that shouldn't be K.
This should be, you know, 50,000,
if you have 50,000 words in your dictionary.
Yeah, thanks. Great.
I stole notation from the previous lecture
and didn't translate it properly.
So LaPlace smoothing, right,
this is the number of possible values that
the random variable XI can take on. Cool.
Raise your hand if this makes sense?
Okay. Some of you,
are there more questions about this? Yeah.
Student:On LaPlace smoothing,
the denominator and the plus A
is the number of values that Y could take?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, let's see.
So LaPlace smoothing is a method to give you,
sort of, hopefully, better estimates of
their probability distribution over a multinomial,
and so was I using X to Y in the previous lecture?
So in trying to estimate the probability
over a multinomial
I think X and Y are different.
I think was it X or Y?
I think it was X, actually. Well
oh, I see, right, right.
I think I was using a different definition for
the random variable Y because suppose you have
a multinomial random variable,
X which takes on
let's use a different alphabet.
Suppose you have a multinomial random
variable X which takes on L different values,
then the maximum likelihood estimate for
the probability of X, PFX equals K,
will be equal to, right,
the number of observations.
The maximum likelihood estimate for
the probability of X being equal to K
will be the number of observations of X
equals K divided by the total number
of observations of X, okay?
So that's the maximum likelihood estimate.
And to add LaPlace smoothing to this,
you, sort of, add one to the numerator,
and you add L to the denominator
where L was the number of possible values that
X can take on. So, in this case,
this is a probability that X equals K,
and X can take on 50,000 values if 50,000
is the length of your dictionary;
it may be something else,
but that's why I add 50,000 to the denominator.
Are there other questions? Yeah.
Student:Is there a specific definition
for a maximum likelihood estimation of a parameter?
We've talked about it a couple times,
and all the examples make sense,
but I don't know what the, like,
general formula for it is.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):I see. Yeah, right.
So the definition of maximum likelihood
so the question is what's the definition for
maximum likelihood estimate?
So actually in today's lecture and the previous lecture
when I talk about Gaussian Discriminant Analysis
I was, sort of, throwing out the maximum likelihood
estimates on the board without proving them.
The way to actually work this out
is to actually write down the likelihood.
So the way to figure out all of
these maximum likelihood estimates is to
write down the likelihood of the parameters,
phi K given Y being zero, phi Y, right?
And so given a training set, the likelihood,
I guess, I should be writing log likelihood
will be the log of the product of I equals one to N,
PFXI, YI, you know,
parameterized by these things, okay?
Where PFXI, YI, right,
is given by NI, PFX, YJ given YI.
They are parameterized by
well, I'll just drop the parameters
to write this more simply oh, I just put it in
times PFYI, okay?
So this is my log likelihood,
and so the way you get the maximum likelihood
estimate of the parameters is you
so if given a fixed training set,
given a set of fixed IYI's,
you maximize this in terms of these parameters,
and then you get the maximum likelihood estimates
that I've been writing out.
So in a previous section of today's lecture
I wrote out some maximum likelihood estimates
for the Gaussian Discriminant Analysis model,
and for Na.ve Bayes, and then this
I didn't prove them, but you get to, sort of,
play with that yourself in the homework problem
as well and for one of these models,
and you'll be able to verify that
when you maximize the likelihood
and maximize the log likelihood that
hopefully you do get the same formulas
as what I was drawing up on the board,
but a way is to find the way these are derived
is by maximizing this, okay? Cool. All right.
So that wraps up what I wanted to say about
oh, so that, more or less,
wraps up what I wanted to say about Na.ve Bayes,
and it turns out that for text classification,
the Na.ve Bayes algorithm
with this second event model,
the last Na.ve Bayes model I presented with
the multinomial event model,
it turns out that almost always does better
than the first Na.ve Bayes model I talked about
when you're applying it to the specific case
to the specific of text classification,
and one of the reasons is hypothesized for this
is that this second model,
the multinomial event model,
takes into account the number of
times a word appears in a document,
whereas the former model doesn't.
I should say that in truth that actually turns out
not to be completely understood
why the latter model does better than
the former one for text classification, and, sort of,
researchers are still debating about it a little bit,
but if you ever have a text classification problem,
you know, Na.ve Bayes Classify is probably not,
by far, the best learning algorithm out there,
but it is relatively straightforward to implement,
and it's a very good algorithm to try
if you have a text
classification problem, okay?
Still a question? Yeah.
Student:So the second model
is still positioning a variant, right?
It doesn't actually care where the words are.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, all right.
Student:And, I mean, X variable,
if my model like you had exclamation in,
does that usually do better if you have enough data?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, so the question is,
sort of, the second model, right?
The second model, the multinomial event model
actually doesn't care about the ordering of the words.
You can shuffle all the words in the email,
and it does exactly the same thing.
So in natural language processing,
there's actually another name;
it's called a Unigram Model
in natural language processing,
and there's some other models like, sort of, say,
higher order markup models that
take into account some of the ordering of the words.
It turns out that for text classification,
the models like the bigram models or trigram models,
I believe they do only very
slightly better, if at all,
but that's when you're
applying them to
text classification, okay?
All right. So the next thing I want to talk about
is to start again to discussion of non-linear classifiers.
So it turns out
well, and so the very first classification algorithm
we talked about was logistic regression,
which had the forming form for hypothesis,
and you can think of this as predicting one
when this estimator probability is greater
or equal to 0.5 and predicting zero, right,
when this is less than 0.5,
and given a training set, right?
Logistic regression will maybe do grade
and descends or something or use Newton's method
to find a straight line that reasonably separates
the positive and negative classes.
But sometimes a data set just can't
be separated by a straight line,
so is there an algorithm that
will let you start to learn these sorts of
non-linear division boundaries?
And so how do you go about
getting a non-linear classifier?
And, by the way, one cool result is that
remember when I said
when we talked about generative learning algorithms,
I said that if you assume Y given X
is exponential family, right, with parameter A,
and if you build a generative learning algorithm
using this, right, plus one, if this is A to one.
This is exponential family
with natural parameter A to zero, right.
I think when we talked about
Gaussian Discriminant Analysis,
I said that if this holds true,
then you end up with a logistic posterior.
It actually turns out that a Na.ve Bayes
model actually falls into this as well.
So the Na.ve Bayes model actually falls into
this exponential family as well, and, therefore,
under the Na.ve Bayes model,
you're actually
using this other linear classifier as well, okay?
So the question is how can you start to
get non-linear classifiers?
And I'm going to talk about one method today
which is and we started to talk about it very briefly
which is taking a simpler algorithm
like logistic regression and using it to build up
to more complex non-linear classifiers, okay?
So to motivate this discussion,
I'm going to use the little picture let's see.
So suppose you have features X1, X2, and X3,
and so by convention,
I'm gonna follow our earlier convention that
X0 is set to one, and so I'm gonna use a little diagram
like this to denote our logistic regression unit, okay?
So think of a little picture like that, you know,
this little circle as denoting a computation note that
takes this input, you know, several features and then
it outputs another number
that's X subscript theta of X,
given by a sigmoid function,
and so this little computational unit
well, will have parameters theta. Now,
in order to get non-linear division boundaries,
all we need to do well, at least one thing to do
is just come up with a way
to represent hypotheses that
can output non-linear division boundaries,
right, and so this is
when you put a bunch of those little pictures that
I drew on the previous board,
you can then get what's called
a Neural Network in which you think of
having my features here and then
I would feed them to say a few of
these little sigmoidal units,
and these together will feed into yet
another sigmoidal unit, say,
which will output my final output H
subscript theta of X, okay?
And just to give these things names,
let me call the values output by
these three intermediate sigmoidal units;
let me call them A1, A2, A3.
And let me just be completely concrete about
what this formula represents, right?
So each of these units in the middle will
have their own associated set of parameters,
and so the value A1 will be
computed as G of X transpose,
and then some set of parameters,
which I'll write as theta one, and similarly,
A2 will be computed as G of X transpose theta two,
and A3 will be G of X transpose, theta three,
where G is the sigmoid function, all right?
So G of Z, and then, finally, our hypothesis will
output G of A transpose theta four, right?
Where, you know,
this A vector is a vector of A1, A2, A3.
We can append another one to it at first
if you want, okay?
Let me just draw up here this
I'm sorry about the cluttered board.
And so H subscript theta of X,
this is a function of all the parameters theta
one through theta four,
and so one way to learn parameters for this model
is to write down the cost function, say,
J of theta equals one-half sum
from Y equals one to M,
YI minus H subscript theta of XI squared, say.
Okay, so that's our familiar quadratic cost function,
and so one way to learn the parameters of
an algorithm like this is to just use
gradient interscent to minimize J of theta
as a function of theta, okay?
See, in the phi gradient descent
to minimize this square area,
which stated differently means you use
gradient descent to make the predictions of
your neural network as close as possible to
what you observed as the labels
in your training set, okay?
So it turns out green descent
on this neural network is a specific name,
the algorithm that implements grand descent
is called back propagation,
and so if you ever hear that all that means is
it just means gradient interscent
on a cost function like this or a variation of this
on the neural network that looks like that,
and well, this algorithm actually has
some advantages and disadvantages,
but let me actually show you. So, let's see.
One of the interesting things about
the neural network is that you can look at
what these intermediate notes are computing, right?
So this neural network has what's called
a hidden layer before you then have the output layer,
and, more generally, you can actually
have inputs feed into these computation units,
feed into more layers of computation units,
to even more layers, to more layers,
and then finally you have an output layer at the end
And one cool thing you can do is look at
all of these intermediate units,
look at these units and what's called
a hidden layer of the neural network.
Don't worry about why it's called that.
Look at computations of the hidden unit
and ask what is the hidden unit
computing the neural network? So to, maybe,
get a better sense of neural networks
might be doing, let me show you a video
I'm gonna switch to the laptop
this is made by a friend,
Yann LeCun who's currently a professor
at New York University.
Can I show a video on the laptop?
So let me show you a video from Yann LeCun
on a neural network that he developed for
Hammerton Digit Recognition.
There was one other thing he did in this neural network
that I'm not gonna talk about called
a Convolutional Neural Network that
well, his system is called LeNet, and let's see.
Would you put on the laptop display?
Hum, actually maybe if
or you can just put on the screen on the side;
that would work too if the big screen isn't working.
Let's see. I'm just trying to think, okay,
how do I keep you guys entertained
while we're waiting for the video to come on?
Well, let me say a few more things
about neural network.
So it turns out that when you write
a quadratic cost function like I wrote down
on the chalkboard just now,
it turns out that unlike logistic regression,
that will almost always
respond to non-convex optimization problem,
and so whereas for logistic regression
if you run gradient descent or Newton's method
or whatever, you converse the global optimer.
This is not true for neural networks.
In general, there are lots of local optimer and,
sort of, much harder optimization problem.
So neural networks, if you're, sort of,
familiar with them, and you're good at making
design choices like what learning rate to use,
and how many hidden units to use, and so on,
you can, sort of, get them to be fairly effective,
and there's, sort of, often ongoing debates about,
you know, is this learning algorithm better,
or is that learning algorithm better?
The vast majority of
machine learning researchers today
seem to perceive support vector machines,
which is what I'll talk about later,
to be a much more effective off-theshelf
learning algorithm than neural networks.
This point of view is contested a bit,
but so neural networks are not something that
I personally use a lot right now
because there's a hard optimization problem
and you should do so often verge,
and it actually, sort of works.
It, sort of,
works reasonably well.
It's just because this is fairly complicated,
there's not an algorithm that
I use commonly or that my friends use all time.
Oh, cool. So but let me just go
and show you an example of neural network,
which was for many years, you know,
the most effective learning algorithm
before support vector machines were invented.
So here's Yann LeCun's video, and
well, there's actually audio on this too, the soundboard.
So I'll just tell you what's happening.
What you're seeing is a trained neural network,
and this display where my mouse pointer
is pointing, right,
this big three there is the input to the neural network.
So you're showing the neural network this image,
and it's trying to recognize what is this.
The final answer output by the neural network
is this number up here,
right below where it says LeNet-5,
and the neural network correctly recognizes
this image as a three,
and if you look to the left of this image,
what's interesting about this is the display
on the left portion of this is actually showing
the intermediate computations of the neural network.
In other words, it's showing you what are
the hidden layers of the neural network computing.
And so, for example, if you look at this one,
the third image down from the top,
this seems to be computing, you know,
certain edges into digits, right?
We're just computing digits on the right-hand side
of the bottom or something of
the input display of the input image, okay?
So let me just play this video,
and you can see some of the inputs and
outputs of the neural network,
and those are very different fonts.
There's this robustness to noise. All right.
Multiple digits, that's, kind of, cool. All right.
So, just for fun,
let me show you one more video, which was
let's see. This is another video from the various CV's,
the machine that changed the world,
which was produced by WGBH Television in corporation
with British Foreclass Incorporation,
and it was aired on PBS a few years ago, I think.
I want to show you a video describing
the NETtalk Neural Network,
which was developed by Terry Sejnowski;
he's a researcher.
And so NETtalk was actually one of the major
milestones in the history of neural network,
and this specific application
is getting the neural network to read text.
So, in other words, can you show a piece of
English to a computer and have the computer read,
sort of, verbally produce sounds that could
respond to the reading of the text.
And it turns out that in the history of AI
and the history of machine learning,
this video created a lot of excitement about
neural networks and about machine learning.
Part of the reason was that Terry Sejnowski had
the foresight to choose to use, in his video,
a child-like voice talking about visiting
your grandmother's house and so on.
You'll see it in a second,
and so this really created the perception of
created the impression of the neural network
being like a young child learning how to speak,
and talking about going to your grandmothers,
and so on. So this actually helped generate
a lot of excitement within academia
and outside academia on neural networks, sort of,
early in the history of neural networks.
I'm just gonna show you the video.
[Begin Video] You're going to hear first
what the network sounds like
at the very beginning of the training,
and it won't sound like words,
but it'll sound like attempts that
will get better and better with time.
[Computer's voice] The network takes the letters,
say the phrase, "grandmother's house,"
and makes a random attempt at pronouncing it.
[Computer's voice] Grandmother's house.
The phonetic difference between the guess
and the right pronunciation is sent back
through the network. [Computer's voice]
Grandmother's house.
By adjusting the connection strengths
after each attempt, the net slowly improves.
And, finally, after letting it train overnight,
the next morning it sounds like this:
Grandmother's house,
I'd like to go to my grandmother's house.
Well, because she gives us candy. Well, and we
NETtalk understands nothing about the language.
It is simply associating letters with sounds.
[End Video] All right.
So at the time this was done, I mean,
this is an amazing piece of work.
I should say today there are other text
to speech systems that work better than
what you just saw,
and you'll also appreciate getting candy from
your grandmother's house is a little bit less
impressive than talking about the Dow Jones
falling 15 points, and profit taking, whatever.
So but I wanted to show that just
because that was another cool,
major landmark in the history of neural networks.
Okay. So let's switch back to the chalkboard,
and what I want to do next is tell you about
Support Vector Machines, okay? That, sort of,
wraps up our discussion on neural networks.
So I started off talking about neural networks
by motivating it as a way to get us
to output non-linear classifiers, right?
I don't really approve of it.
It turns out that you'd be able to come up with
non-linear division boundaries using a neural network
like what I drew on the chalkboard earlier.
Support Vector Machines will be
another learning algorithm that
will give us a way
to come up with non-linear classifiers.
There's a very effective,
off-the-shelf learning algorithm,
but it turns out that in the discussion
I'm gonna in the progression and
development I'm gonna pursue,
I'm actually going to start off by describing yet
another class of linear classifiers with linear
division boundaries, and only be later, sort of,
in probably the next lecture or the one after that,
that we'll then take the support
vector machine idea and, sort of,
do some clever things to it to make it work very well
to generate non-linear division boundaries
as well, okay?
But we'll actually start by talking
about linear classifiers a little bit more.
And to do that, I want to convey
two intuitions about classification.
One is you think about logistic regression;
we have this logistic function that was
outputting the probability that Y equals one,
and it crosses this line at zero.
So when you run logistic regression,
I want you to think of it as an algorithm that
computes theta transpose X, and then
it predicts one, right, if and only if,
theta transpose X is greater than zero, right?
IFF stands for if and only if.
It means the same thing as a double implication,
and it predicts zero, if and only if,
theta transpose X is less than zero, okay?
So if it's the case that theta transpose X
is much greater than zero,
the double greater than sign means these
are much greater than, all right.
So if theta transpose X is much greater than zero,
then, you know, think of that
as a very confident prediction that
Y is equal to one, right?
If theta transpose X is much greater than zero,
then we're gonna predict one
then moreover we're very confident it's one,
and the picture for that
is if theta transpose X is way out here,
then we're estimating that the probability of
Y being equal to one on the sigmoid function,
it will be very close to one.
And, in the same way, if theta transpose X
is much less than zero,
then we're very confident that Y is equal to zero.
So wouldn't it be nice
so when we fit logistic regression of some of
the classifiers is your training set,
then so wouldn't it be nice if, right,
for all I such that Y is equal to one.
We have theta transpose XI
is much greater than zero,
and for all I such that Y is equal to zero,
we have theta transpose XI is much less than zero,
okay? So wouldn't it be nice
if this is true?
That, essentially, if our training set,
we can find parameters theta so that
our learning algorithm not only makes
correct classifications on all the examples
in a training set, but further it's, sort of,
is very confident about
all of those correct classifications.
This is the first intuition that I want you to have,
and we'll come back to this first intuition in a second
when we talk about functional margins, okay?
We'll define this later.
The second intuition that I want to convey,
and it turns out for the rest of today's lecture
I'm going to assume that a training set
is linearly separable, okay?
So by that I mean for the rest of today's lecture,
I'm going to assume that
there is indeed a straight line that can
separate your training set,
and we'll remove this assumption later,
but just to develop the algorithm,
let's take away the linearly separable trainingset.
And so there's a sense that
out of all the straight lines that
separate the training set, you know,
maybe that straight
line isn't such a good one,
and that one actually isn't such a great one either,
but maybe that line in the middle is a much better
linear separator than the others, right?
And one reason that when you and I look at it
this one seems best is because this line is
just further from the data, all right?
That is separates the data with a greater distance
between your positive and your negative
examples and division boundary, okay?
And this second intuition,
we'll come back to this shortly,
about this final line that I drew being, maybe,
the best line this notion of distance from
the training examples.
This is the second intuition I want to convey,
and we'll formalize it later when we talk about
geometric margins of our classifiers, okay?
So in order to describe support vector machine,
unfortunately, I'm gonna have to
pull a notation change, and, sort of,
unfortunately, it, sort of,
was impossible to do logistic regression,
and support vector machines,
and all the other algorithms
using one completely consistent notation,
and so I'm actually gonna change notations
slightly for linear classifiers,
and that will actually make it much easier for us
that'll make it much easier later today
and in next week's lectures
to actually talk about support vector machine.
But the notation that I'm gonna use
for the rest of today and for most of next week
will be that my B equals Y,
and instead of be zero, one,
they'll be minus one and plus one,
and a development of a support vector machine
we will have H, have a hypothesis output values
to the either plus one or minus one,
and so we'll let G of Z be equal to one if Z
is greater or equal to zero,
and minus one otherwise, right?
So just rather than zero and one,
we change everything to plus one and minus one.
And, finally, whereas previously I wrote G
subscript theta of X equals G of theta
transpose X and we had the convention that
X zero is equal to one, right?
And so X is an RN plus one.
I'm gonna drop this convention of letting X zero
equals a one, and letting X be an RN plus one,
and instead I'm going to parameterize my linear
classifier as H subscript W,
B of X equals G of W transpose X plus B, okay?
And so B just now plays the role of theta zero,
and W now plays the role of
the rest of the parameters,
theta one through theta N, okay?
So just by separating out the interceptor B
rather than lumping it together,
it'll make it easier for us
to develop support vector machines. So yes.
Student:[Off mic].
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, yes. Right, yes.
So W is right. So W is a vector in RN,
and X is now a vector in RN rather than N plus one,
and a lowercase b is a real number. Okay.
Now, let's formalize the notion of
functional margin and germesh margin.
Let me make a definition.
I'm going to say that the functional margin
of the hyper plane WB with respect
to a specific training example, XIYI is
WRT stands for with respect to
the function margin of a hyper plane WB
with respect to a certain training example,
XIYI has been defined as Gamma Hat I equals
YI times W transpose XI plus B, okay?
And so a set of parameters,
W, B defines a classifier
it, sort of, defines a linear separating boundary,
and so when I say hyper plane,
I just mean the decision boundary
that's defined by the parameters W, B.
You know what, if you're confused
by the hyper plane term, just ignore it.
The hyper plane of a classifier with parameters W, B
with respect to a training example
is given by this formula, okay?
And interpretation of this is that if YI is equal to one,
then for each to have a large functional margin,
you want W transpose XI plus B to be large, right?
And if YI is equal minus one,
then in order for the functional margin to be large
we, sort of, want the functional margins to large,
but in order for the function margins to be large,
if YI is equal to minus one,
then the only way for this to be big is
if W transpose XI plus B is much less than zero, okay?
So this captures the intuition that
we had earlier about functional margins
the intuition we had earlier that if YI is equal to one,
we want this to be big,
and if YI is equal to minus one,
we want this to be small, and this, sort of,
practice of two cases into one statement that
we'd like the functional margin to be large.
And notice this is also that so long as
YI times W transpose XY plus B,
so long as this is greater than zero,
that means we classified it correctly, okay?
And one more definition,
I'm going to say that the functional margin
of a hyper plane with respect to
an entire training set is going to define gamma hat
to be equal to min over
all your training examples of gamma hat, I, right?
So if you have a training set,
if you have just more than one training example,
I'm going to define the functional margin
with respect to the entire training set
as the worst case of all of
your functional margins of the entire training set.
And so for now we should think of
the first function like an intuition of saying that
we would like the function margin to be large,
and for our purposes, for now,
let's just say we would like the worst-case
functional margin to be large, okay?
And we'll change this a little bit later as well.
Now, it turns out that there's one little problem
with this intuition that will, sort of, edge us later,
which it actually turns out to be very easy
to make the functional margin large, all right?
So, for example,
so as I have a classifiable parameters W and B.
If I take W and multiply it by two
and take B and multiply it by two,
then if you refer to the definition
of the functional margin, I guess that was what?
Gamma I, gamma hat I equals
YI times W times transpose B.
If I double W and B,
then I can easily double my functional margin.
So this goal of making the functional margin large,
in and of itself, isn't so useful
because it's easy to make the functional margin
arbitrarily large just by scaling other parameters.
And so maybe one thing we need to do later
is add a normalization condition.
For example, maybe we want to
add a normalization condition that de-norm,
the alter-norm of the parameter W is equal to one,
and we'll come back to this in a second. All right.
And then so Okay. Now, let's talk about
see how much time we have, 15 minutes.
Well, see, I'm trying to decide how much
to try to do in the last 15 minutes. Okay.
So let's talk about the geometric margin, and so
the geometric margin of a training example [inaudible],
right? So the division boundary of my classifier
is going to be given by the plane W
transpose X plus B is equal to zero, okay?
Right, and these are the X1, X2 axis, say,
and we're going to draw relatively
few training examples here.
Let's say I'm drawing deliberately
few training examples so that
I can add things to this, okay?
And so assuming we classified an example correctly,
I'm going to define the geometric margin
as just a geometric distance between
a point between the training example
yeah,
between the training example XI, YI
and the distance given by this separating line,
given by this separating hyper plane, okay?
That's what I'm going to
define the geometric margin to be.
And so I'm gonna do some algebra fairly quickly.
In case it doesn't make sense, and read through
the lecture notes more carefully for details.
Sort of, by standard geometry, the normal,
or in other words, the vector that's 90 degrees
to the separating hyper plane is going to
be given by W divided by the norm of W;
that's just how planes and high dimensions work.
If this stuff some of this you have to use,
take a look t the lecture notes on the website.
And so let's say this distance is gamma I, okay?
And so I'm going to use the convention that
I'll put a hat on top
where I'm referring to functional margins,
and no hat on top for geometric margins.
So let's say geometric margin,
as this example, is gamma I.
That means that this point here, right, is going to
be XI minus gamma I times W over normal W, okay?
Because W over normal W is the unit vector,
is the length one vector that is normal
to the separating hyper plane,
and so when we subtract gamma I times the unit
vector from this point, XI,
or at this point here is XI.
So XI minus, you know,
this little vector here is going to be this point that
I've drawn as a heavy circle, okay?
So this heavy point here is XI minus this vector,
and this vector is gamma I time W
over norm of W, okay?
And so because this heavy point
is on the separating hyper plane, right,
this point must satisfy W transpose times that
point equals zero, right?
Because all points X on the separating
hyper plane satisfy the equation W transpose X
plus B equals zero, and so this point is
on the separating hyper plane, therefore,
it must satisfy W transpose this point
oh, excuse me. Plus B is equal to zero, okay?
Raise your hand if this makes sense so far?
Oh, okay. Cool, most of you, but, again,
I'm, sort of, being slightly fast in this geometry.
So if you're not quite sure
why this is a normal vector,
or how I subtracted this,
or whatever,
take a look at the details in the lecture notes.
And so what I'm going to do
is I'll just take this equation,
and I'll solve for gamma, right?
So this equation I just wrote down,
solve this equation for gamma or gamma I,
and you find that
you saw that previous equation from gamma I
well, why don't I just do it?
You have W transpose XI plus B equals
gamma I times W transpose W over norm of W;
that's just equal to gamma times the norm of W
because W transpose W is the norm of W squared,
and, therefore, gamma is just
well, transpose X equals, okay?
And, in other words,
this little calculation just showed us that
if you have a training example XI,
then the distance between XI
and the separating hyper plane defined
by the parameters W and B
can be computed by this formula, okay?
So the last thing I want to do
is actually take into account the sign of the –
the correct classification of the training example.
So I've been assuming that
we've been classifying an example correctly.
So, more generally, to find the geometric margin
of a training example to be gamma I equals
YI times that thing on top, okay?
And so this is very similar
to the functional margin,
except for the normalization by the norm of W,
and so as before, you know,
this says that so long as
we would like the geometric margin to be large,
and all that means is that so long as
we're classifying the example correctly,
we would ideally hope of the example to be
as far as possible from the separating hyper plane,
so long as it's on the right side of
the separating hyper plane,
and that's what YI multiplied into this does.
And so a couple of easy facts,
one is if the norm of W is equal to one,
then the functional margin
is equal to the geometric margin,
and you see that quite easily, and,
more generally, the geometric margin
is just equal to the functional margin divided
by the norm of W, okay? Let's see, okay.
And so one final definition is so far I've defined
the geometric margin with respect to
a single training example, and so as before,
I'll define the geometric margin with respect to
an entire training set as gamma equals
min over I of gamma I,
all right?
And so the maximum margin classifier,
which is a precursor to the support vector machine,
is the learning algorithm that
chooses the parameters W and B so as to
maximize the geometric margin,
and so I just write that down.
The maximum margin classified poses
the following optimization problem.
It says choose gamma, W, and B so as to
maximize the geometric margin,
subject to that YI times
well, this is just one way to write it, subject to
actually, do I write it like that? Yeah, fine.
There are several ways to write this, and one of the things
we'll do next time is actually
I'm trying to figure out
if I can do this in five minutes.
I'm guessing this could be difficult.
Well, so this maximizing your classifier
is the maximization problem
over parameter gamma W and B, and for now,
it turns out that the geometric margin doesn't change
depending on the norm of W, right?
Because in the definition of the geometric margin,
notice that we're dividing by the norm of W anyway.
So you can actually set the norm of
W to be anything you want,
and you can multiply W and B by any constant;
it doesn't change the geometric margin.
This will actually be important,
and we'll come back to this later.
Notice that you can take the parameters WB,
and you can impose
any normalization constant to it,
or you can change W and B by
any scaling factor and replace them
by ten W and ten B whatever,
and it does not change the geometric margin, okay?
And so in this first formulation,
I'm just gonna impose a constraint
and say that the norm of W was one,
and so the function of the geometric margins
will be the same,
and then we'll say maximize
the geometric margins subject to
you maximize gamma subject to that
every training example must
have geometric margin at least gamma,
and this is a geometric margin because
when the norm of W is equal to one,
then the functional of
the geometric margin are identical, okay?
So this is the maximum margin classifier,
and it turns out that if you do this, it'll run,
you know, maybe about as well as a
maybe slight
maybe comparable to logistic regression,
but it turns out that
as we develop this algorithm further,
there will be a clever way to allow us
to change this algorithm to let it work
in infinite dimensional feature spaces
and come up with
very efficient non-linear classifiers.
So there's a ways to go before we turn this into
a support vector machine, but this is the first step.
So are there questions about this? Yeah.
Student:[Off mic].
Instructor (Andrew Ng):For now,
let's just say you're given a fixed training set,
and you can't yeah, for now,
and the scaling of the training set is not
something you get to play with, right?
So everything I've said is for a fixed training set,
so that you can't change the X's,
and you can't change the Y's.
Are there other questions?
Okay. So all right. Next week we will take this,
and we'll talk about authorization algorithms,
and work our way towards turning this into
one of the most effective
off-theshelf learning algorithms,
and just a final reminder again,
this next discussion session
will be on Matlab and Octaves.
So show up for that
if you want to see a tutorial. Okay.
See you guys in the next class.