So welcome back
and what I want to do to is talk about
is wrap up our discussion on factor analysis
and in particular
what I want to do is step through
parts of the derivations for
EM for factor analysis
because again there are a few steps
in the EM derivation
that are particularly tricky
and there are specific mistakes
that people often make
on deriving EM algorithms for
algorithms like factor analysis.
So I wanted to show you
how to do those steps right
so you can apply the same ideas
to other problems as well.
And then in the second half or so of this lecture
I'll talk about principal component analysis
which is a very powerful algorithm
for dimensionality reduction.
We'll see later what that means.
So just a recap
in a previous lecture
I described a few properties
of Gaussian distributions.
One was that if you have a random
variable a random value vector X that
can be partitioned into two portions
X1 and X2
and if X is Gaussian with mu [inaudible]
and covariance sigma
where mu is itself a partition vector
and sigma is sort of a partition
matrix that can be written like that.
So I'm just writing sigma in terms of
the four sub-blocks.
Then you can look at the distribution
of X and ask what is the marginal
distribution of say X1.
And the answer we said last time
was that X1 the marginal
distribution of X1 is Gaussian would mean mu
and covariance sigma one one
whereas sigma one one is the upper
left block of that covariance matrix sigma.
So this one is no surprise.
And I also wrote down the formula
for computing conditional distributions
such as what is P of X1 given X2
and last time I wrote down
that the distribution of X1 given X2
would also be Gaussian
with parameters that I wrote as mu of
one given two and sigma of one given two
where mu of one given two is
– let's see [inaudible] this formula. Okay?
So with these formulas will be able to
locate a pair of
joint Gaussian random variables
X1 and X here are both vectors
and compute the marginal
and conditional distributions
so P of X1 or P of X1 given X2.
So when I come back and derive the
actually   I'll come back and
E set –
use the marginal formula in a second
and then when I come back and
derive from the E step in the EM algorithm
for factor analysis
I'll actually be using these
two formulas again.
And again   just to continue summarizing
what we did last time
This is an unsupervised learning problem
and so we're given an unlabeled training set
we said that in factor analysis our model –
where each SI is a vector in RN
as usual.
We want to model the density of X
and our model for X
would be that we imagine there's
a latent random variable Z
that's generating this [inaudible] zero
mean in identity covariance.
And Z will be some
low dimensional thing [inaudible]
and we [inaudible].
And we imagine that
X is generated as mu plus lambda Z
plus epsilon where epsilon is a Gaussian
random variable with mean zero
and a covariance matrix psi.
And so the parameters of this model are
mu which N-dimensional vector
lambda   which is an N by
D-dimensional vector
matrix   and psi which is
N by N and is diagonal.
N is a diagonal matrix.
So the cartoon I drew last time
for factor analysis was
I said that maybe that's the typical example
of data point ZI
if and in this example I had D equals one
N equals two.
So Z in this example is one-dimensional.
D equals one.
And so you take this data   map it to say
[inaudible] mu plus lambda Z and
that may give you some set of points there.
And lastly   this model was envisioning
that you'd place a little Gaussian bump
around each of these say and sample
that would be a typical
sample of the Xs under this model.
So how  the parameters of this model?
– and the Xs are then maybe
Well   the joint distribution of Z and X
is actually Gaussian where parameters given
by some vector [inaudible] mu XZ
and sum covariance matrix sigma.
And [inaudible] what those two things are
this vector [inaudible] is a vector of zeroes
appended to the vector mu.
And the matrix sigma is this partitioned matrix.
We also worked this out last time.
So you can ask what is the distribution of X
under this model
and the answer is under this model X
is Gaussian with mean mu and covariance
lambda lambda [inaudible] plus psi.
So let's just take the
second block of the mean vector
and take that lower right hand corner
block for the covariance matrix
and so this is really my formula for computing
the marginal distribution of a Gaussian
except that I'm computing
the marginal distribution of the second half
of the vector rather than the first half.
So this is the marginal distribution of X
under my model.
And so if you want to learn
Student:[Inaudible] initial distribution
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
Oh   yes.
Yes   so in this one
I'm breaking down the this is really
I'm specifying the conditional distribution
of X given Z.
So the conditional distribution of
would mean mu plus lambda Z and
covariance psi. This is what that [inaudible].
So since this is the
marginal distribution of X
X given Z this is Gaussian –
given my training set of M
unlabeled examples
I can actually write down the log likelihood
of my training set.
So the log likelihood of my training set
actually   no.
Let's just write down the likelihood.
So the likelihood of my parameters given
my training set is the product from
I equals one to M of P of XI
given the parameters.
I can actually write down what that is
because XI is Gaussian with parameter
mu and variance lambda lambda
transpose times psi
so you can actually write this down as one
over two pi to the N over two determined of
and then times E to the minus one half X
of so that's my formula for the density
of a Gaussian that has mean mu and
covariance lambda lambda transpose plus psi.
So this is my likelihood of the parameters
given a training set.
And one thing you could do is actually
take this likelihood and try to maximize it
in terms of the parameters
try to find the [inaudible] the parameters.
if you sort of try take [inaudible] to get the
law of likelihood   take derivatives
set derivatives equal to zero
you find that you'll be unable to
solve for the maximum of this analytically.
But if you do that you find that –
You won't be able to solve this [inaudible]
likelihood estimation problem.
If you take the derivative of this
with respect to the parameters
set the derivatives equal to zero
and try to solve for the value of the parameters
lambda   mu   and psi [inaudible]
so you won't be able to do that [inaudible].
So what we'll use instead to estimate the
parameters in a factor analysis model
will be the EM algorithm.
Student:Why is the law of likelihood
P of X and not P of X [inaudible] X and Z
or something?
Instructor (Andrew Ng) So the question is why
is the likelihood P of X and
not P of X given Z
or P of X and Z.
so by analogy to the mixture of
Gaussian distributions models
we're given a training set that just
comprises a set of unlabeled training examples
that for convenience for whatever reason
it's easier for me to write down a model
The answer is let's see we're in the –
that defines the
joint distribution on P of X comma Z.
But what I would like to do is really maximize
as a function of my parameters
I'm using theta as a shorthand to denote
all the parameters of the model
I want to maximize the probability of
the data I actually observe.
And this would be actually [inaudible] theta
from I equals one to M
and this is really integrating out Z.
So I only ever get to observe the Xs
and the Zs are latent random
variables or hidden random variables.
And so what I'd like to do is do
this maximization in which I've
implicitly integrated out Z.
Does that make sense?
Actually   are there other questions
about the factor analysis models?
Okay. So here's the EM algorithm.
In the E step
we compute the conditional distribution of
ZI given XI in our current
setting of the parameters.
And in the M step
we perform this maximization.
And if this looks a little bit different from
the previous versions of EM that you've seen
the only difference is that
now I'm integrating over ZI
because ZI is now a Gaussian random variable
is now this continuous value thing
so rather than summing over ZI
I now integrate over ZI.
And if you replace [inaudible] of a sum
you [inaudible] ZI then this is
exactly the M step you
saw when we worked it out
from the mixture of Gaussian [inaudible].
So it turns out that
in order to implement
the E step and the M step
there are just two little things
there are actually sort of three key things
that are different from the models
that you saw previously
so I wanna talk about them.
The first one is that the first of the
which is that in the E step
Z is now a continuous value random variable
so you now need a way
to represent these continuous value densities
probably density
functions to represent QI of Z.
So fortunately in this probably
it's not difficult to do
and in particular the conditional distribution of
ZI given XI and
our parameters which
I'm gonna omit from this equation is
going to be Gaussian with mean
so I write like that
where this is going to be equal to the vector
zero minus
if you match this to the formula
I had previously for computing conditional
distributions of Gaussians
this corresponded to the terms mu one minus
sigma one two sigma two two inverse times
two minus mu. So those are the terms
corresponding to the form I had previously for
And the way I got this formula was –
computing themarginal distributions
of a Gaussian. And that is going to be given
by that   and again those are the terms
corresponding to the formulas I had for
the very first thing I did   the formulas for
computing conditional distributions
of Gaussians.
And so this is E step.
You need to compute the Q distribution.
You need to compute QI of ZI
and to do that what you actually do
is you compute this vector mu of
ZI given XI and sigma of ZI given XI
and together these represent the mean
and covariance of the distribution Q where
Q is going to be Gaussian
so that's the E step.
Now here's the M step then.
I'll just mention there are sort of two ways
to derive M steps for especially
Gaussian models like these.
Here's the key trick I guess which is that
when you compute the M step
you often need to compute integrals that
look like these.
And then there'll be some function of ZI.
Let me just write ZI there   for instance.
So there are two ways to compute integrals
like these.
One is if you write out
this is a commonly made mistake in
well   not mistake
commonly made unnecessary complication
One way to try to compute this integral
is you can write this out as
integral over ZI.
And while we know what QI is
right? QI is a Gaussian so two pi
so D over two the covariance of QI
is this sigma given XI
which you've computed
And so writing those out is the unnecessarily
complicated way to do it
that's the times   multiplication
if you actually want to evaluate this integral
it just looks horribly complicated.
I'm not quite sure how to evaluate this.
By far   the simpler to evaluate this integral
is to recognize that this is just the expectation
with respect to ZI drawn
from the distribution QI
if you want to actually integrate –
of the random variable ZI.
And once you've actually got this way
you notice that this is just the
expected value of ZI under the distribution QI
but QI is a Gaussian distribution with
mean given by that mu vector and
covariance given by that sigma vector
and so the expected value of ZI under
this distribution is jus
t mu of ZI given XI.
Does that make sense?
So by making those observations
That this is just an
expected value
there's a much easier way to compute that
integral. [Inaudible].
So we'll apply the same idea to the M step.
So the M step
we want to maximize this.
There's also sum over I there's
a summation over I outside
but this is essentially the term
inside the arg max of the M step
where taking the integral of a ZI and just
I guess just form some expectation respect
to the random variable ZI of this thing inside.
And so this simplifies to the following.
And it turns out actually all I did here
was use the fact that
P of X given Z times P of Z
equals P over X comma Z.
Right? That's just combining this term
and that term gives you the numerator
observe that that's actually –
in the original.
And so in turns out that
for factor analysis
in these two terms
this is the only one
that depends on the parameters.
The distribution P of ZI has no
Parameters
because ZI was just drawn from a Gaussian
with zero mean and identity covariance.
QI of Z was this fixed Gaussian.
It doesn't depend on the parameters theta
and so in the M step
we really just need to maximize this one term
with respect to all parameters
mu   lambda   and psi.
So let's see. There's sort of one more key step
I want to show but to get there
I have to write down an unfortunately large
amount of math
and let's go into it. Okay.
So in the M step
we want to maximize and
all expectations with respect to ZI
drawn from the distributions QI
and sometimes I'll be sloppy and just omit this.
And now this distribution P of XI given ZI
that is a Gaussian density
this is Gaussian with mean
given by mu plus lambda Z and
covariance psi.
And so in this step of the derivation
I will actually go ahead and substitute in
the formula for Gaussian density.
So I will go ahead and take those and plug it
into here
one over two pi to the N over two
psi inverse E to the dot   dot   dot. So I will go
because XI given ZI –
ahead and plug in the Gaussian density.
And when you do that
to not make the derivation too complicated
I'm actually just going to maximize this
with respect to the parameters lambda.
you want to maximize this
with respect to lambda
psi   and mu
but just to keep the amount of math I'm gonna
do in class sane
I'm just going to show how to maximize this
with respect to the matrix lambda
and I'll pretend that psi and mu are fixed.
you find that you get expectation –
And so if you substitute
excuse me. I forgot to say to maintain –
in the Gaussian density
you get some expected value of the constant.
The constant may depend on psi
but not on lambda.
Then mine is this thing.
And this quadratic term essentially came from
the exponent in your Gaussian density.
When I take log of exponent
then you end up with this quadratic term.
And so if you take the derivatives
of the expression above
with respect to the matrix lambda
and you set that to zero
we want to maximize this expression
with respect to the parameters lambda
so you take the derivative of this
ith respect to lambda
excuse me.
That's a minus sign
and set the derivate of this expression to zero
because you set derivatives to zero
to maximize things   right?
When you do that
and simplify
you end up with the following.
And so that's the in the M step
this is the value you should get that
you use to update your parameters lambda.
And again   the expectations are with respect
to ZI drawn from the distributions QI.
So the very last step of this derivation
is we need to work out
what these two expectations are.
And so the very first term EZI transpose
I guess is just mu of ZI give XI transpose
because the QI distribution has mean given by
To work out the other term
let me just remind you
that if you have a random variable Z that's
Gaussian with mean
mu and covariance sigma
then the covariance sigma is EZZ transpose
minus EZ EZ transpose.
That's one of the definitions of the covariance
and so this implies that EZZ transpose
equals sigma plus EZ EZ transpose.
And so this second term here becomes sigma Z
I to the mu I plus given XI.
Okay?
And so that's how you
Compute E of ZI transpose
and E of ZI ZI transpose
and substitute them back into this formula.
And you would then have your M step update
to the parameter matrix lambda.
And the last thing I want to point out
in this derivation is that it turns out
the name EM algorithm
expectation maximization
one common mistake for the EM algorithm
is in the E step
some want to take the expectation of the
random variable Z
and then in the M step they just plug in the
expected value everywhere you see it.
So in particular
one common mistake in deriving EM
for factor analysis is
to look at this and say
"Oh   look. I see ZZ transpose.
–	it's probably because of
Let's just plug in the expected value under the
Q distribution."
And so plug in that mu of ZI given
into that expectation
and that would be an incorrect derivation
of EM because it's missing this other term
sigma of ZI given XI.
So one common misconception for EM
is that in the E step
you just compute the expected value of the
hidden random variable
and the M step
you plug in the expected value.
It turns outin some algorithms that
turns out to be the right thing to do.
In the mixture of Gaussians and the mixture of
[inaudible] models
XI times mu of ZI given XI transpose –
that would actually give you the right answer
but in general
the EM algorithm is more complicated
than just taking the expected values
of the random variables
and then pretending that they were sort of
observed at the expected values.
So I wanna go through this just to illustrate that
step as well.
So just to summarize the three key things to
keep in that came up in this variation were
1.) That for the E step
we had a continuous
Gaussian random variable
and so to compute the E step
we actually compute the mean and covariance
of the distribution QI.
The second thing that came up was
in the M step when you see these integrals
sometimes if you interpret that as expectation
then the rest of the math becomes much easier.
And the final thing was
again in the M step
the EM algorithm is derived by a certain
maximization problem that we solve.
It is not necessarily just plugging the expected
value of ZI everywhere.
Let's see.
I feel like I just did a ton of math
and wrote down way too many equations.
And even doing this
I was skipping many steps.
So you can go to the lecture notes to see
all the derivations of the steps I skipped
like how you actually take derivatives
with respect to the matrix lambda
and how to compute the updates for the other
parameters as well
for mu and for psi
because this is only for lambda.
And so that's the factor analysis algorithm.
Justin?
Student:I was just wondering in the step
in the lower right board
you said that the second term doesn't have any
parameters that we're interested in.
The first term has all the parameters
so we'll [inaudible]   but it seems to me that QI
has a lot of parameters
Instructor (Andrew Ng):I see. Right.
Let's see.
So the question was doesn't the term QI
have parameters?
it actually turns out in the EM algorithm
sometimes P of ZI may have parameters
but QI of ZI may never have any parameters.
In the specific case of factor analysis
P of ZI doesn't have parameters.
In other examples
the mixture of Gaussian models say
ZI was a multinomial random variable
and so in that example PI of ZI has parameters
but it turns out that Q of ZI will
never have any parameters.
is Gaussian with mean given by mu of ZI
given XI and covariance sigma ZI given XI.
And so it's true that mu and sigma may
themselves have depended on
So in the EM algorithm QI is –
the values of the parameters
I had in the previous iteration of EM
but the way to think about Q
is I'm going to take the parameters from the
previous iteration of the algorithm
and use that to compute what QI of ZI is.
And that's the E second EM algorithm.
then this is a fixed distribution.
for mu and sigma   and just keep
these two values fixed as I run the M step.
of the parameters.
When I wrote down QI of ZI
And in particular   QI of ZI is going to be –
that was a function of so yeah the
is this Gaussian distribution –
parameters from the previous iteration.
And I want to compute the new
set of parameters.
Okay. More questions?
So this is probably the most math I'll ever do
in a lecture in this entire course.
Let's now talk about a different algorithm.
Actually   which board was I on?
So what I want to do now is talk about
an algorithm called
principal components analysis
which is often abbreviated PCA.
And then once I’ve computed what QI of Z is
Here's the idea.
PCA has a very similar idea as factor analysis
I’m gonna use these fixed values
but it sort of maybe gets to the problem
a little more directly than just factor analysis.
so we're still doing unsupervised learning
Student:So that’s – I guess I was confused
so given a training set of M examples
because in the second point over there’s
where each XI is an N-dimensional vector
a lot of – it looks like they’re parameters
as usual
but I guess they’re old iterations
what I like to do is reduce it to
a lower dimensional data set where
K is strictly less than N
and quite often will be much smaller than N.
So I'll give a couple examples
of why we want to do this.
Imagine that you're given a data set
that contains measurements and
unknown to you measurements of
and unknown to you
whoever collected this data actually
included the height of the person in
centimeters as well as
the height of the person in inches.
So because of rounding off to the
nearest centimeter or rounding off to
the nearest inch the values won't exactly
match up
but along two dimensions of this data anyway
it'll lie extremely close to a straight line
So the question is given –
but it won't lie exactly on a straight line
because of rounding off to the nearest
centimeter or inch   but lie very close to
the straight line.
And so we have a data set like this.
It seems that what you really care about
is that axis
and this axis is really the variable of interest.
That's maybe the closest thing you have
to the true height of a person.
And this other axis is just noise.
So if you can reduce the dimension of this data
from two-dimensional to one-dimensional
then maybe you can get rid of some
I don't know   people or something –
of the noise in this data.
Quite often
you won't know that this was cm and
this was inches.
You may have a data set
with a hundred attributes
but you just didn't happen to notice one
was cm and one was inches.
Another example that I sometimes
think about is some of you know that
my students and I work
with helicopters a lot.
So we imagined that
you take surveys of quizzes
measurements of radio control helicopter pilots.
Maybe one axis you have measurements
of your pilot's skill
how skillful your helicopter pilot is
and on another axis maybe you measure
how much they actually enjoy flying.
And maybe this is really maybe
this is actually roughly one-dimensional data
and there's some variable of interest
which I'll call maybe pilot attitude
that somehow determines their skill
and how much they enjoy flying.
And so again   if you can reduce this data
from two dimensions to one-dimensional
maybe you'd have a slightly better of measure
of what I'm calling
loosely pilot attitude
which may be what you really wanted to
So let's talk about an algorithm to do this
and I should come back and talk about
more applications of PCA later.
So here's the algorithm.
Before running PCA normally
you will preprocess the data as follows.
I'll just write this out
I guess. I know some of you are writing.
So this is maybe just an unnecessary
amount of writing
to say that compute a mean of my training sets
and subtract out the means
so now I've zeroed out the mean of my
training sets.
And the other step is
I'll compute the variance of each of features
after zeroing out the mean
and then I'll divide each feature
by the standard deviation
so that each of my features now has
equal variance.
So these are some standard preprocessing steps
we'll often do for PCA.
I'll just mention that sometimes the second step
is usually done only when your different
features are on different scales.
So if you're taking measurements of people
one feature may be the height
and another may be the weight
and another may be the strength
and another may be how they age or whatever
all of these quantities are on very
different scales
so you'd normally normalize the variance.
Sometimes
so for example if you're working with
images and the XIJs are the pixels
that they're are on the same scale
because they're all pixel intensity
values ranging from zero to 255
then you may omit this step.
So after preprocessing
let's talk about
how we would find the main axes along
which the data varies.
How would you find a principal axes
of variations ?
let me just go through one specific example
and then we'll formalize the algorithm.
Here's my training set
comprising five examples.
It has roughly zero mean.
And the variance under X1 and X2 axes
are the same.
There's X1
there's X2 axes.
And so the principal axes and variation of
this data is roughly the
positive 45-degree axis
so what I'd like to do is have my algorithm
conclude that this direction
if all the XIs are the same type of thing –
that I've drawn with this arrow U
is the best direction onto which to
project the data   so the axis by which my data
really varies.
So let's think about how we formalize.
One thing we want to look at is suppose
this is really the axis onto which
I want to project
that I want to use to capture
most of the variation of my data.
And then when I take my training set
and project it onto this line
then I get that set of points.
And so you notice that those dots
the projections of my training sets
onto this axis
has very large variance.
In contrast
let's say this is really  the worst
direction onto which to project my data.
If I project all my data onto this axis
then I find that the projects of
my data onto the purple line
onto this other line has
much smaller variance
that my points are clustered together
much more tightly.
So one way to formalize this notion of finding
the main axis of variations of data is
I would like to find the vector U
I would like to find the direction U so that
when I project my data onto that direction
the projected points vary as much as possible.
I take that axis –
So in other words
I'm gonna find a direction so that
when I project my data onto it
the projections are largely widely spaced out.
There's large variance.
So let's see.
So I want to find the direction U.
Just as a reminder
if I have a vector U of norm one
then the vector XI projected onto
U has length XI transpose U.
To project a vector onto to project X
onto unit vector
if I were to choose a different direction –
the length of the projection's just
XI transpose U.
And so to formalize my PCA problem
so I choose U and this is subject to the
constraint that the norm of U
but I'm going to maximize
the length of the projection of the
vectors X onto U. In particular   I want the sum
of square distances of the projections
to be far from the origin.
I want the projections of X onto U to
have large variance.
And just to simplify some of the math later
let me put a one over M in front.
And so that quantity on the right
is equal to one over M.
Let's see. U transpose XI times XI transpose U
and so can simplify and I get
this is U transpose times U.
So I want to maximize U transpose times
some matrix times U subject to the constraint
that the length of U must be equal to one.
And so some of you will recognize that
this means U must be the principal
eigenvector of this matrix in the middle.
then the length of our vector XI projected –
So let me just write that down and
say a few more words about it.
So this implies that U is the principal
eigenvector of the matrix
and I'll just call this matrix sigma.
It actually turns out to be a covariance matrix
equals one to M transpose.
Actually   let's check.
I'm going to choose a vector U to maximize –
How many of you are familiar with
eigenvectors?
Oh   cool. Lots of you
that the length of U is one –
almost all of you.
Great.
let's see   sum from I equals one to M –
What I'm about to
say is very extremely familiar
but it's worth saying anyway.
So if you have a matrix A
and a vector U
and they satisfy AU equals lambda U
then this is what it means for U
to be an eigenvector of the matrix A.
And the value lambda here is
called an eigenvalue.
And so the principal eigenvector is
just the eigenvector that
corresponds to the largest eigenvalue.
One thing that some of you may have seen
but I'm not sure that you have
and I just wanna relate this to stuff
that you already know as well
is that optimization problem is really
maximize U transpose U subject to
let me write that constraint as that
U transpose U equals one.
And so to solve this constrained
optimization problem
you write down the Lagrangian lambda
where that's the Lagrange multiplier
because there's a constraint optimization.
And so to actually solve this optimization
you take the derivative of L with respect to U
and that gives you sigma U minus lambda U.
You set the derivative equal to zero
and this shows that sigma U equals lambda U
and therefore the value of U that
solves this constraint optimization problem
that we care about must be
an eigenvector of sigma.
And in particular it turns out
to be the principal eigenvector.
So just to summarize
what have we done?
We've shown that given a training set
if you want to find the principal axis
of a variation of data
you want to find the 1-D axis on
which the data really varies the most
what we do is we construct
the covariance matrix sigma
the matrix sigma that I wrote down just now
and then you would find the principal
eigenvector of the matrix sigma.
And this gives you
the best 1-D subspace onto which to
project the data.
the norm of U is equal to one and –
And more generally
you would choose
if you wanna K-dimensional subspace onto
which project your date
you would then choose U1 through UK
to be the top K eigenvectors of sigma.
And by top K eigenvectors
I just mean the eigenvectors corresponding
to the K highest eigenvalues.
I guess I showed this only for
the case of a 1D subspace
but this holds more generally.
And now
the eigenvectors U1 through UK represent
give you a new basis with which
to represent your data.
Student:[Inaudible] diagonal?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
So by convention
the PCA will choose orthogonal axes.
So I think this is what I'm saying.
Here's one more example.
Imagine that you're a three-dimensional set
and imagine that your
it's very hard to draw in 3-D on the board
so just let me try this.
Imagine that here my
X1 and X2 axes lie on the plane of the board
and the X3 axis points directly
out of the board.
Imagine that you have a data set
where most of the data lies on
the plane of the board
but there's just a little bit of fuzz.
So imagine that
the X3 axis points orthogonally
out of the board
and all the data lies roughly
in the plane of the board
but there's just a tiny little bit of fuzz so
that some of the data lies
just a couple of millimeters
off the board.
So you run a PCA on this data.
You find that U1 and U2
will be some pair of bases that
essentially lie in the plane of the board
and U3 will be an orthogonal axis
at points roughly
out of the plane of the board.
So if I reduce
this data to two dimensions
then the bases U1 and U2 now
give me a new basis with which
to construct my lower dimensional
representation of the data.
Just to be complete about what that means
previously we have say fairly high
three-dimensional data set –
dimensional input data XI and RN
and now if I want to represent my data
in this new basis
given by U1 up to UK
instead I would take each of my original
training examples XI and I would now
represent it or replace it with a different vector
which I call YI
and that would be computed
as U1 transpose XI U2 transpose XI.
And so the YIs are going to be K-dimensional
your choice of K will be less than N
so this represents a lower dimensional
representation of your data
and serves as an approximate representation
of your original data
where you're using only K numbers
to represent each training example
rather than N numbers. Let's see.
Is it possible not to have eigenvectors but
have trivial eigenvectors?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
What do you mean by trivial eigenvectors?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh   okay.
Yes   so I see.
Let me see if I can get this right.
that don't have a full set of eigenvectors.
Sorry
deficient I think is what it's called.
Is that right
Ziko? Yeah.
So some matrices are deficient and
actually don't have a full set of eigenvectors
like an N by N matrix that
does not have N distinct eigenvectors
but that turns out not to be possible
in this case because the covariance matrix
sigma is symmetric
and symmetric matrices are never deficient
so the matrix sigma will always have
a full set of eigenvectors.
It's possible that if you there's one other issue
which is repeated eigenvalues.
So for example
it turns out that in this example
if my covariance matrix looks like this
where K will be less –
it turns out that the identity of the first two
eigenvectors is ambiguous.
And by that I mean you can choose this
to be U1 and this to be U2
or I can just as well rotate these eigenvectors
and choose that to be U1 and that to be U2
or even choose that to be U1 and
that to be U2
and so on.
And so when you apply PCA
one thing to keep in mind is
sometimes eigenvectors can
rotate freely within their subspaces
when you have repeated eigenvalues
or close to repeated eigenvalues.
And so the way to think about the vectors U
So there are some matrices that are –
I think the term is degenerate –
is think of as a basis with which to
represent your data
but the basis vectors can sometimes
rotate freely
and so it's not always useful to
look at the eigenvectors one at a time
and say this is my first
eigenvector capturing whatever
the height of a person
or this is my second eigenvector
and it captures their skill at or whatever.
That's a very dangerous thing to do
when you do PCA.
What is meaningful is the subspace
spanned by the eigenvectors
but looking at the eigenvectors one at a time
is sometimes a dangerous thing to do
because they can often freely.
Tiny numerical changes can cause eigenvectors
to change a lot
but the subspace spanned by the top K
eigenvectors will usually be about the same.
It actually turns out there are multiple
possible interpretations of PCA.
I'll just give one more
without proof
given a training set like this
and let me just choose a direction.
This is not the principal components.
I choose some direction and
project my data onto it
This is clearly not the
direction PCA would choose
but what you can think of
PCA as doing is
choose a subspace onto
which to project your data so as to
minimize the sum of squares differences
between the projections and the  points.
So in other words
another way to think of PCA
is trying to minimize the sum of
squares of these distances between the dots
the points X and the dots onto
which I'm projecting the data.
It turns out they're actually I don't know.
There's sort of nine or ten different
interpretations of PCA.
This is another one.
There are a bunch of ways to derive PCA.
You get play with some PCA ideas
more in the next problem set.
What I want to do next is talk about
a few applications of PCA.
Here are some ways that PCA is used.
One is visualization.
Very often you have high dimensional data sets.
Someone gives you a 50-dimensional
data set
and it's very hard for you to look at a data
set that's 50-dimensional and understand
what's going on because you can't plot
something in 50 dimensions.
So common practice
which is that  whatever –
if you want to visualize
a very high dimensional data set
another view of PCA is –
is to take your data and project it
into say a 2-D plot
or project it into a 3-D plot
so you can render like a 3-D display
on a computer so you can better
visualize the data and look for structure.
One particular example that I learned about
of doing this recently was in Krishna Shenoy's
lab here in Stanford in which he had
readings from 50 different parts
of a monkey brain.
I actually don't know it was the number 50.
It was tens of different parts of
the monkey brain
and so you'd have these
50-dimensional readings
50-dimensional vectors correspond to
different amounts of electrical activity
in different parts of the monkey brain.
It was actually 50 neurons
but tens of neurons   but it was tens of neurons
in the monkey brain
and so you have a 50dimensional time series
and it's very hard to
visualize very high dimensional data.
But what he understood is that was use PCA
to project this 50-dimensional data down
to three dimensions
and then you can visualize this data
in three dimensions just using 3D plot
so you could visualize
what the monkey is thinking over time.
Another common application of PCA
is compression
so if you have high dimensional data
and you want to store it with numbers
clearly PCA is a great way to do this.
It turns out also that
sometimes in machine learning
sometimes you're just given extremely
high dimensional input data
and for computational reasons
you don't want to deal with such
high dimensional data.
one common use of PCA
is taking very high dimensional data
and represent it with low dimensional subspace
it's that YI is the representation
I wrote down just now
so that you can work with
much lower dimensional data.
And it turns out to be
it's this sort of just seems to
make a fact of life that when you're
given extremely high dimensional data
of all the high dimensional data sets
I've ever seen   very high dimensional data
sets often have all their points
lying on much lower dimensional subspaces
so very often you can dramatically reduce
the dimension of your data
and really be throwing too much of
the information away.
So let's see.
If you're learning algorithms
it takes a long time to run
very high dimensional data.
You can often use PCA to compress
the data to lower dimensions
so that your learning algorithm
runs much faster.
And you can often do this with sacrificing
almost no performance
in your learning algorithm.
There's one other use of PCA for learning
you remember when we
talked about learning theory
we said that
the more features you have
the more complex your hypothesis class
if say you're doing linear classification.
If you have more features
you have lots of features
then you may be more prone to overfitting.
And so fairly –
One other thing you could do with PCA
is just use that to reduce the dimension
of your data
so that you have fewer features
and you may be slightly less
prone to overfitting.
This particular application of PCA to learning
I should say   it sometimes works.
It often works.
I'll actually later show a couple of examples
where sort of do this and it works.
But this particular application of PCA
almost all the time just in practice –
I find looking in the industry
it also seems to be a little bit overused
and in particular actually
let me say more about that later.
We'll come back to that later.
There's a couple of other applications
to talk about.
One is outlier detection or anomaly detection.
The idea is
suppose I give you a data set.
You may then run PCA to
find roughly the subspace on
which your data lies.
And then if you want to find anomalies
in future examples
you then just look at your future examples
and see if the lie very far from your subspace.
This isn't a fantastic
anomaly detection algorithm.
the idea is if I give you a data set
you may find a little dimensional subspace
which is –
on which it lies
and then if you ever find a point that's far
from your subspace
you can factor
it as an anomaly.
So this really isn't the best
anomaly detection algorithm
but sometimes this is done.
And the last application that I want to go
into a little bit more in detail is
matching or to find better
distance calculations.
So let me say what I mean by this.
I'll go into much more detail on this last one.
So here's the idea.
Let's say you want to do face recognition
So let's say you want to do face recognition
and you have 100 of 100 images.
So a picture of a face is like
whatever
some array of pixels
and the pixels have different grayscale values
and dependent on
the different grayscale values
you get different pictures of people's faces.
And so you have 100 of 100 pixel images
and you think of each face
as a 10  000-dimensional vector
which is very high dimensional.
cartoon to keep in mind
and you think of here's
my plot of my 100-dimensional space
and if you look at a lot of
different pictures of faces
each face will be along what will be
some point in this 100  000-dimensional space.
And in this cartoon
I mean most of this data lies on a relatively
low dimensional subspace
because in this
10  000-dimensional space
It's not a very good –
really not all points correspond to
valid images of faces.
The vast majority of values
the vast majority of 10  000-dimensional images
just correspond to random noise
like looking things and don't correspond to
a valid image of a face. But instead the space
of possible face of images probably spans
a much lowerdimensional subspace.
And so what we'll do is
we'll use a low dimensional subspace
on which the data lies
and in practice a PCA dimension of
50 would be fairly typical.
there's some axes that really measure
the shape or the appearance of the face
and there are some other axes
that we're not interested in
that are maybe just random noise.
So what we'll do is for face recognition
I might give you a picture of a face
and ask you what face looks
the most similar to this.
I'll give you a picture of someone
and ask you can you find
other pictures of the same person.
And so the key step to do that is to look at
two faces and to compare
how similar these two faces are.
So here's how we'll use PCA.
Given a face there and a different face there
the way I'll measure the difference between
these two faces is
I won't just measure
the Euclidian distance similarity.
Instead   I'll take the space and project it
take this and project it onto
my 50-dimensional subspace and
measure the similarity
between those two points on the subspace.
I want you to think of it as –
And so when I do that
I may end up with a face here
and a face here that look very far
upon the original space
but when I project them onto the subspace
they may end up looking much more similar.
So what I want to show you
a second on the laptop
is given each of these training
examples is a 10  000-dimensional vector
I can plot that as a grayscale image
and I'd get like a picture
of some person's face.
What I'll also show you on the laptop
will be plots of my eigenvectors.
And so the eigenvectors also
live in a 10  000-dimensional subspace.
And I plot that. You get some image that's
and these images are called eigenfaces.
So when you think of –
And what PCA is doing is essentially
using linear combinations of these eigenface
images to approximate these XIs
and it's the eigenfaces that span
so that these
bases U1   U2 and so on that
span hopefully the subspace along
which my faces live.
So here's a training set
comprising aligned images like these
a much larger set
than is shown here
and so when you run PCA
these are some of the plots of the UIs.
Remember when I said plot the eigenvectors
UI in the same way that it's
plotting the training examples
and so you end up with the
eigenvectors being grayscale images like these
and what approximate images of faces
with linear combinations of these.
So I said it's dangerous
to look at individual eigenvectors
onto my 50-dimensional subspace –
and you really shouldn't do that
but let me just do that a little bit anyway.
So if you look at the first eigenvector
this corresponds roughly to
whether the face is illuminated
from the left or the right.
So depending on how heavy the weight is
on this image
that roughly captures variation in illumination.
The second image is hard to tell.
It seems to be capturing variation
in overall brightness of the face.
The third eigenvector
capturing roughly how much of a shadow
or maybe a beard or something a person
has and so forth.
It's dangerous to look at
individual eigenvectors
but it sort of slightly informs the look of it.
Here's an example
of a specific application of eigenfaces.
This is from
Sandy Pentland Alex Pentland's lab at MIT.
In this display
this upper leftmost image is the input
to the eigenface's algorithm.
The algorithm is then asked to go through
a database and find the most similar faces.
This second image here is
what it thinks is the most similar face
of the input.
The next one over is the second most similar.
The next one over is the third most similar
and so on.
And so using eigenfaces   and by measuring
differences between faces
in that lower dimensional subspace
it is able to do a reasonable job
identifying pictures of the same person
even with faces of the person removed.
And the next row shows the
next most similar faces and so on
so this one is the fourth most similar face
and so on.
This is a usual application of eigenfaces.
The last thing I wanna say is
just when people tell me
about machine learning problems
I do often recommend they try PCA
for different things
so PCA is a useful thing to know
to use for compression
visualization   and so on.
But in industry
I just tend to see PCA used slightly more often.
There are also some times
where you see people using PCA when
they really shouldn't.
So just one final piece of advice
for use of PCA is before you use it
also think about whether you could just do it
with the original training data XI
without compressing it
since I've also definitely
seen people compress the data when
they really didn't need to.
But having said that
I also often advise people to use PCA for
various problems and it often works.
Okay.
Sorry about running late.
So let's wrap up for today.