So welcome back,
and what I want to do  today
is continue our discussions
of the EM Algorithm,
and in particular,
I want to talk  about the EM formulation
that we derived in the previous lecture
and apply it to the  mixture
of Gaussians model,
apply it to a different model
and a mixture of naive Bayes  model,
and then the launch part
of today's lecture will be
on the factor analysis  algorithm,
which will also use the EM.
And as part of that,
we'll actually take a brief  digression
to talk a little bit about sort of useful
properties of Gaussian distributions.
So just to recap where we are.
In the previous lecture,
I started to talk about
unsupervised  learning,
which was machine-learning problems,
where you're given
an unlabeled  training
set comprising m examples here, right?
And then
so the fact that there are no  labels;
that's what makes this
unsupervised or anything.
So one problem that
I talked  about last time was
what if you're given a data set
that looks like this and
you want to  model the density PFX from
which you think the data had been drawn,
and so with a data  set like this,
maybe you think
was a mixture of two Gaussians
and start to talk about an  algorithm
for fitting a mixture of Gaussians model,
all right?
And so we said that
we  would model
the density of XP of X
as sum over Z PFX
given Z times P of Z where
this  later random variable meaning
this hidden random variable Z
indicates which of the two  Gaussian
distributions each
of your data points came from
and so we have, you know,
Z  was not a nomial with parameter
phi and X conditions on a coming from
the JAFE  Gaussian was given by Gaussian
of mean mu J and covariant sigma J,
all right?
So, like I said at the beginning
of the previous lecture,
I just talked about
a very specific  algorithm
that I sort of pulled out of the air
for fitting the parameters of this model
for  finian, Francis, phi, mu and sigma,
but then in the second half of the previous lecture
I  talked about
what's called the EM Algorithm
in which our goal is that
it's a  estimation of parameters.
So we want to maximize
in terms of theta,
you know, the, sort  of,
usual right matter of log likelihood
well, parameterized by theta.
And because we  have
a later random variable Z
this is really maximizing
Okay?
So using Jensen's inequality last  time
we worked out the EM Algorithm
in which in the E step we would
chose these  probability distributions QI
to the l posterior on Z given X and
parameterized by theta
and in the M step
we would set theta to be the value
that maximizes this.
Okay?
So these  are the ones
we worked out last time and
the cartoon that I drew was that
you have this  long likelihood function
L of theta
that's often hard to maximize
and what the E step does
is choose these probability
distribution production QI's.
And in the cartoon,
I drew what  that corresponded to
was finding a lower bounds
for the log likelihood.
And then  horizontal access data
and then the M step you maximize
the lower boundary,
right?
So  maybe you were here previously
and so you jumped to the new point,
the new maximum  of this lower bound.
Okay? And so this little curve here,
right? This lower bound function  here
that's really the right-hand side
of that augments.
Okay?
So this whole thing in the  augments.
If you view this thing
as a function of theta,
this function of theta is
a lower bounds for the log likelihood
of theta and so
the M step we maximize this lower bound
and that corresponds to jumping to
this new maximum to lower bound.
So it turns out that in the EM Algorithm
so why do you evolve with
the EM algorithm?
It turns out that very often,
and this will be true
for all the examples we see today,
it turns  out that very often
in the EM Algorithm
maximizing the M Step,
so performing the  maximization the M
Step, will be tractable and can often
be done analytically in the  closed form.
Whereas if you were trying to maximize
this objective
we try to take this  formula on the right
and this maximum likely object,
everyone, is to take this all
on the  right and set its derivatives
to zero and try to solve
and you'll find that
you're unable to obtain a solution
to this in closed form this maximization.
Okay?  And so to give you an example
of that is that you remember
our discussion
on  exponential family marbles, right?
It turns out that if X and Z is jointly,
I guess, a line in  exponential
families.
So if P of X, Z prioritized by theta
there's an explanation family
distribution,
which it turns out to be true for the
mixture of Gaussians distribution.
Then  turns out that
the M step here will be tractable
and the E step will also be tractable
and so  you can do
each of these steps very easily.
Whereas performing
trying to perform this
original maximum likelihood
estimation problem on this one, right?
Will be  computationally very difficult.
You're going to set
the derivatives to zero
and try to solve  for that.
Analytically you won't be able to find
an analytic solution to this.
Okay?
So what I want to do in a second
is actually take this view
of the EM Algorithm and  apply it
to the mixture of Gaussians models.
I want to take these
E steps and M Steps and  work them out
for the mixture of Gaussians model,
but before I do that,
I just want to say  one more thing about
this other view of the EM Algorithm.
It turns out there's one other  way
of thinking about the EM Algorithm,
which is the following:
I can define an  optimization objective
J of theta, Q are defined it to be this.
This is just a thing in the  augments
in the M step.
Okay?
And so what we proved
using Jensen's inequality is that
the log likelihood of theta
is greater and equal to J of theta Q.
So in other words,
we  proved last time that
for any value of theta and Q
the log likelihood upper bounds
J of  theta and Q.
And so just to relate this back to,
sort of, yet more things
that you all ready  know,
you can also think of covariant cause
in a sense, right?
However, our discussion  awhile back
on the coordinate ascent optimization
algorithm. So we can show,
and I  won't actually show this view
so just take our word for it
and look for that at home if you  want,
that EM is just coordinate
in a set on the function J.
So in the E step
you maximize  with respect to Q
and then the M step
you maximize with respect to theta.
Okay?
So this  is another view
of the EM Algorithm
that shows why it has to converge,
for example. If  you can –
I've used in a sense of J of theta, Q
having to monotonically increase
on every  iteration.
Okay?
So what I want to do next
is actually take
this general EM machinery
that we worked up  and apply it to
a mixture Gaussians model.
Before I do that,
let me just check
if there are  questions about
the EM Algorithm as a whole?
Okay, cool.
So let's go ahead and work on
the mixture of Gaussian's EM, all right?
MOG, and that's  my abbreviation
for Mixture of Gaussian's.
So the E step
were called those Q  distributions,
right?
In particular,
I want to work out
so Q is the probability distribution
over the late and random variable Z
and so the E step I'm gonna figure out
what is these  compute –
what is Q of ZI equals J.
And you can think of this
as my writing P of ZI  equals J,
right? Under the Q distribution.
That's what this notation means.
And so the EM  Algorithm tells us that,
let's see,
Q of J is the likelihood probability
of Z being the value J  and given XI
and all your parameters. And so, well,
the way you compute this
is by  Dave's rule,right?
So that is going to be equal to
divided by right?
That's all the by Dave's rule.
And so this you know
because XI  given ZI equals J.
This was a Gaussian with mean mu J and
covariant sigma J.
And so to  compute this first term
you plug in the formula
for the Gaussian density there
with  parameters mu J and sigma J
and this you'd know
because Z was not a nomial, right?
Where parameters given by phi and so
the problem of ZI being with J is just
phi J
and so  you can substitute
these terms in.
Similarly do the same thing
for the denominator and
that's how you work out what Q is.
Okay?
And so in the previous lecture
this value the  probability that
ZI equals J under the Q distribution
that was why I denoted that as WIJ.
So that would be the E step
and then in the M step
we maximize with respect
to all of our  parameters.
This, well I seem to be writing
the same formula down a lot today.
All right.
And just so we're completely
concrete about how you do that,
right? So if you do that
you end up with
so plugging in the quantities
that you know that becomes this,
let's see.  Right.
And so that we're completely
concrete about what the M step is doing.
So in the M  step that was,
I guess,
QI over Z, I being over J.
Just in the summation,
sum over J is the  sum over
all the possible values of ZI
and then
this thing here is my Gaussian density.
Sorry, guys, this thing –
well, this first term here, right?
Is my P of XI given ZI
and that's  P of ZI.
Okay?
And so to maximize this with respect to
say you want to maximize this
with respect to all of your parameters
phi, mu and sigma.
So to maximize with respect to  the
parameter mu,
say, you would take the derivative
for respect to mu
and set that to  zero
and you would and if you actually do
that computation you would get,
for  instance, that that becomes your
update to mu J.
Okay?
Just so I want to
the equation is  unimportant.
All of these equations are written down
in the lecture notes.
I'm writing  these down
just to be completely concrete about
what the M step means.
And so write  down that formula,
plug in the densities you know,
take the derivative set to zero,
solve  for mu J
and in the same way
you set the derivatives equal to zero
and solve for your  updates
for your other parameters phi
and sigma as well.
Okay?
Well,
just point out just one little
tricky bit for this
that you haven't seen before
that most  of you
probably all ready now,
but I'll just mention is that
since phi here is
a multinomial  distribution
when you take this formula
and you maximize it with respect to phi
you  actually have
an additional constraint, right?
That the sum of I let's see,
sum over J, phi  J must be equal to one.
All right?
So, again,in the M step
I want to take this thing
and  maximize it with respect
to all the parameters
and when you maximize this respect
to the  parameters phi J
you need to respect the constraint
that sum of J phi J must be
equal to  one.
And so, well, you all ready know
how to do constraint maximization,
right?
So I'll  throw out the method
of the granjay multipliers
and generalize the granjay when you
talk  about the support of X machines.
And so to actually perform the
maximization in terms of phi J
you construct to the granjay, which is –
all right?
So that's the equation from  above
and we'll denote in the dot dot dot
plus theta times that,
where this is sort of
the  granjay multiplier
and this is your optimization objective.
And so to actually solve
the  parameters phi J
you set the parameters of this
so that the granjay is zero and solve.
Okay?
And if you then work through the math
you get the appropriate value
to update the  phi J's too
which I won't do,
but I'll be all the full directions
are in the lecture notes.
I  won't do that here.
Okay.
And so if you actually perform
all these computations
you can also verify that.
So I  just wrote down
a bunch of formulas for the EM Algorithm.
At the beginning of the last  lecture
I said for
the mixture of Gaussian's model –
I said for the EM here's the formula
for computing the WIJ's
and here's a formula for
computing the mud's
and so on,
and  this variation is where
all of those formulas actually come from.
Okay? Questions about  this?
Yeah?
Student:
Instructor (Andrew Ng):[Inaudible]
Oh, I see. So it turns out that, yes,
there's also constrained to
the phi J this must be greater than zero.
It turns out that if you want
you could actually  write down
then generalize the granjayn
incorporating all of these constraints
as well
and  you can solve to [inaudible]
these constraints.
It turns out that
in this particular derivation
actually it turns out that very often
we find maximum likely estimate for
multinomial  distributions probabilities.
It turns out that
if you ignore these constraints
and you just  maximize the formula
luckily you end up with values that
actually are greater than
or  equal to zero
and so if even ignoring those constraint
you end up with parameters
that are  greater than or equal to zero
that shows that that must be
the correct solution
because  adding that constraint
won't change anything.
So this constraint it is then caused –
it turns  out that if you ignore this
and just do what I've wrote down
you actually get the right  answer.
Okay? Great.
So let me just very quickly talk about
one more example of a mixture model.
And the  perfect example for this
is imagine you want to do
text clustering, right?
So someone  gives you a large set of
documents and you want to cluster them
together into cohesive  topics.
I think I mentioned
the news website news.google.com.
That's one application
of  text clustering where you might
want to look at all of the news
stories about today,
all the  news stories
written by everyone,
written by all the online news websites
about whatever  happened yesterday
and there will be
many, many different stories
on the same thing,
right?
And by running a text-clustering
algorithm you can
group related documents  together.
Okay?
So how do you apply the EM Algorithm
to text clustering?
I want to do this to illustrate
an example in which
you run the EM Algorithm
on discreet valued inputs
where the input
where the training examples XI
are discreet values.
So what I want to talk about
specifically is
the mixture of na.ve Bayes model
and depending on how much you  remember
about na.ve Bayes
I talked about two event models.
One was the
multivariant  vanuvy event model.
One was the multinomial event model.
Today I'm gonna use
the   multivariant vanuvy event model.
If you don't remember
what those terms mean  anymore
don't worry about it.
I think the equation will
still make sense.
But in this  setting
we're given a training set X1 for XM.
So we're given M text documents
where  each XI is zero one to the end.
So each of our training examples
is an indimensional bit  of vector,
right? S this was the representation
where XIJ was it indicates
whether word  J appears in document I,
right? And let's say that
we're going to model ZI the
our latent  random variable
meaning our hidden random variable ZI
will take on two values zero one
so this means I'm just gonna find
two clusters
and you can generalize the clusters
that  you want.
So in the mixture of na.ve Bayes model
we assume that ZI is distributed
and mu E with  some value of phi
so there's some probability of
each document coming from cluster one
or from cluster two.
We assume that
the probability of XI given ZI, right?
Will make the  same na.ve Bayes
assumption as we did before.
Okay?
And more specifically –
well,  excuse me, right. Okay.
And so most of us [inaudible] cycles
one given ZI equals say  zero will be
given by a parameter phi substitute J
given Z equals zero.
So if you take this  chalkboard
and if you take all instances of
the alphabet Z and replace it with Y
then you  end up with exactly
the same equation as I've written down
for na.ve Bayes like a long  time ago.
Okay?
And I'm not actually going to work out
the mechanics deriving the EM Algorithm,
but it  turns out that
if you take this joint distribution
of X and Z and if you work out
what the  equations are
for the EM algorithm for
maximum likelihood estimation
of parameters
you  find that in the E step you compute,
you know, let's say these parameters –
these weights  WI which are going to be
equal to your perceived distribution of Z
being equal one  conditioned on XI
parameterized by your phi's
and given your parameters
and in the M  step.
Okay?
And that's the equation you get
in the M step.
I mean, again, the equations  themselves
aren't too important.
Just sort of convey –
I'll give you a second
to finish  writing, I guess.
And when you're done
or finished writing take a look
at these equations
and see if they make intuitive sense
to you why these three equations,
sort of, sound like  they might be
the right thing to do. Yeah?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Say that again.
Student:Y
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, yes, thank you. Right. Sorry, just,
for everywhere over Y I  meant Z.
Yeah?
Student:[Inaudible] in the first place?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):No.
So what is it? Normally
you initialize phi's
to be  something else, say randomly.
So just like in na.ve Bayes
we saw zero probabilities
as a  bad thing so the same reason
you try to avoid zero probabilities,
yeah. Okay? And so just the intuition
behind these equations is in the E step
WI's is you're gonna take
your best  guess for whether the document
came from cluster one or cluster zero,
all right? This is  very similar
to the intuitions behind the EM Algorithm
that we talked about
in a previous  lecture.
So in the E step
we're going to compute these weights
that tell us
do I think this  document
came from cluster one or cluster zero.
And then in the M step
I'm gonna say  does this numerator
is the sum over all the elements
of my training set of
so then  informally, right?
WI is one there,
but I think the document
came from cluster one and
so  this will essentially sum up
all the times I saw words J
in documents that I think are in
cluster one.
And these are sort of weighted
by the actual probability.
I think it came from  cluster one
and then I'll divide by again,
if all of these were ones and zeros
then I'd be  dividing by the actual
number of documents
I had in cluster one.
So if all the WI's were  either
onesor zeroes
then this would be exactly
the fraction of documents that
I saw in  cluster one in which
I also saw were at J.
Okay?
But in the EM Algorithm
you don't  make a hard
assignment decision about
is this in cluster one or
is this in cluster zero.
You  instead represent your uncertainty
about cluster membership with the
parameters WI.
Okay?
It actually turns out that
when we actually implement
this particular model
it actually  turns out that
by the nature of this computation
all the values of WI's
will be very close to  either one or zero
so they'll be numerically
almost indistinguishable
from one's and  zeroes.
This is a property of na.ve Bayes.
If you actually compute this probability
from  all those documents
you find that WI is either 0.0001
or 0.999.
It'll be amazingly close to
either zero or one
and so the M step
and so this is pretty much guessing
whether each  document is
in cluster one or cluster zero
and then using formulas
they're very similar to  maximum
likely estimation for na.ve Bayes.
Okay? Cool.
Are there and if some of
these equations don't look
that familiar to you anymore,
sort of, go back and
take another  look at what you saw
in na.ve Bayes
and hopefully you can see the links
there as well.
Questions about this before I move on?
Right, okay.
Of course the way I got these equations
was by turning through the machinery
of the EM  Algorithm,
right? I didn't just write these
out of thin air.
The way you do this is
by  writing down the E step
and the M step for this model
and then the M step same  derivatives
equal to zero
and solving from that
so that's how you get the
M step and the E  step.
So the last thing I want to do today
is talk about the factor analysis model
and the reason  I want to do this
is sort of two reasons
because one is factor analysis
is kind of a useful  model.
It's not as widely used as
mixtures of Gaussian's
and mixtures of na.ve Bayes  maybe,
but it's sort of useful.
But the other reason
I want to derive this model is that
there  are a few steps in the math
that are more generally useful.
In particular,
where this is for  factor
analysis this would be an example
in which we'll do EM
where the late and  random variable
where the hidden random variable Z is
going to be continued as  valued.
And so some of the math we'll see
in deriving factor analysis
will be a little bit  different
than what you saw before
and they're just a –
it turns out the full derivation
for  EM for factor analysis
is sort of extremely long and complicated
and so I won't inflect  that
on you in lecture today,
but I will still be writing
more equations than is –
than you'll    see me do
in other lectures because there are,
sort of, just a few steps
in the factor  analysis derivation
so I'll physically illustrate it.
So it's actually [inaudible] the model
and it's really contrast to
the mixture of Gaussians  model,
all right?
So for the mixture of Gaussians model,
which is our first model we had,
that well I actually motivated it
by drawing the data set like this,
right?
That one of you  has a data set
that looks like this,
right? So this was a problem
where n is twodimensional
and you have, I don't know,
maybe 50 or 100 training examples,
whatever,  right?
And I said maybe you want to give
a label training set like this.
Maybe you want to  model this
as a mixture of two Gaussians.
Okay?
And so a mixture of Gaussian models
tend to be applicable
where m is larger, and often much
larger, than n where the number  of
training examples you have
is at least as large as,
and is usually much larger than,
the  dimension of the data.
What I want to do is talk about
a different problem
where I want you to imagine
what  happens if either the dimension
of your data is roughly equal
to the number of examples  you have or
maybe the dimension of your data is maybe
even much larger than the  number of
training examples you have. Okay?
So how do you model such
a very high  dimensional data?
Watch and you will see sometimes, right?
If you run a plant or  something,
you run a factory,
maybe you have a thousand measurements
all through your  plants,
but you only have five
you only have 20 days of data.
So you can have 1,000  dimensional data,
but 20 examples of it all ready.
So given data that has this property
in  the beginning that
we've given a training
set of m examples. Well,
what can you do to try  to model
the density of X?
So one thing you can do
is try to model it just as
a single  Gaussian, right?
So in my mixtures of Gaussian
this is how you try model as
a single  Gaussian and say
X is intuitive with mean mu
and parameter sigma where sigma
is going  to be done n by n matrix
and so if you work out
the maximum likelihood estimate
of the  parameters
you find that
the maximum likelihood estimate
for the mean is just the  empirical
mean of your training set,
right. So that makes sense. And the
maximum  likelihood of
the covariance matrix sigma will be this,
all right? But it turns out that
in  this regime where the data
is much higher dimensional
excuse me, where the data's  dimension
is much larger than the training examples
you have if you compute the  maximum
likely estimate of
the covariance matrix sigma
you find that this matrix is  singular.
Okay? By singular, I mean that it
doesn't have four vanq
or it has zero eigen  value
so it doesn't have
I hope one of those terms makes sense.
And there's another  saying that
the matrix sigma will be non-invertible.
And just in pictures,
one complete  example is if D is
if N equals M equals two
if you have two-dimensional data
and you  have two examples.
So I'd have two training examples
in two-dimen this is X1 and X2.
This is my unlabeled data.
If you fit a Gaussian
to this data set
you find that
well you  remember I used to
draw constables of Gaussians as ellipses,
right? So these are  examples
of different constables of Gaussians.
You find that
the maximum likely  estimate Gaussian
for this responds to Gaussian
where the contours are sort of
infinitely  thin and infinitely long
in that direction.
Okay? So in terms so the contours
will sort of  be infinitely thin, right?
And stretch infinitely long
in that direction.
And another way of  saying it is that
if you actually plug in the formula
for the density of the Gaussian,
which  is this,
you won't actually get a nice answer
because the matrix sigma is
non-invertible
so sigma inverse is not defined
and this is zero.
So you also have one over zero times
E to  the sum inversive
and non-inversive matrix
so not a good model.
So let's do even better,  right?
So given this sort of data
how do you model P of X?
Well, one thing you could do
is constrain sigma to be diagonal.
So you have a covariance  matrix X is
okay? So in other words
you get a constraint sigma
to be this matrix, all  right?
With zeroes on the off diagonals.
I hope this makes sense.
These zeroes I've  written down here
denote that everything after diagonal
of this matrix is a zero.
So the  massive likely estimate
of the parameters will be pretty
much what you'll expect, right?
And in pictures what this means
is that the [inaudible] the distribution
with Gaussians  whose controls
are axis aligned.
So that's one example of a Gaussian
where the  covariance is diagonal.
And here's another example
and so here's a third example.
But  often I've used the examples
of Gaussians where the covariance matrix
is off diagonal.  Okay?
And, I don't know, you could do this
in model P of X,
but this isn't very nice
because you've now thrown away
all the correlations
between the different variables
so  the axis are X1 and X2, right?
So you've thrown away you're
failing to capture any of  the
correlations or the relationships between
any pair of variables in your data.
Yeah?
Student:Is it could you say again
what does that do for the diagonal?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Say again.
Student:The covariance matrix
the diagonal,  what does that again?
I didn't quite  understand  what the examples mean.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Okay.
So these are the contours of
the Gaussian density that  I'm drawing,
right? So let's see so post
covariance issues with diagonal
then you can  ask what is P of X
parameterized by mu and sigma,
right?
If sigma is diagonal and
so this  will be some Gaussian dump,
right? So not in
oh, boy. My drawing's really bad,
but in  two-D the density for Gaussian
is like this bump shaped thing, right?
So this is the  density of the Gaussian
wow, and this is a really bad drawing.
With those, your axis X1  and X2
and the height of this is P of X
and so those figures over there
are the contours of  the density
of the Gaussian. So those are the
contours of this shape.
Student:No, I don't mean the contour.
What's special about these types?
What makes  them different than
instead of general covariance matrix?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, I see. Oh,
okay, sorry.
They're axis aligned so the main
these, let's see. So I'm not drawing
a contour like this, right?
Because the main axes of  these
are not aligned with the X1 and X-axis
so this occurs found to Gaussian
where the  off-diagonals are non-zero,
right?
Cool. Okay.
You could do this, this is sort of work.
It  turns out that
what our best view is two training
examples you can learn
in non-singular  covariance matrix,
but you've thrown away
all of the correlation in the data
so this is not  a great model.
It turns out you can do something –
well, actually,
we'll come back
and use this property  later.
But it turns out you can do something
even more restrictive,
which is you can  constrain sigma
to equal to sigma squared times
the identity matrix.
So in other words,
you can constrain it
to be diagonal matrix and moreover
all the diagonal entries must be
the same and so the cartoon
for that is that you're constraining
the contours of your  Gaussian density
to be circular.
Okay?
This is a sort of even harsher constraint
to place in  your model.
So either of these versions,
diagonal sigma or sigma being the,
sort of,  constant value diagonal
are the all ready strong assumptions,
all right? So if you have  enough data
maybe write a model just a little bit
of a correlation between
your different  variables.
So the factor analysis model
is one way to attempt to do that.
So here's the  idea.
So this is how the factor analysis model
models your data.
We're going to assume  that
there is a latent random variable,
okay?
Which just means random variable Z.
So Z is  distributed Gaussian
with mean zero and covariance
identity where Z will be
a Ddimensional  vector now
and D will be chosen
so that it is lower than the dimension
of  your X's.
Okay?
And now I'm going to assume that
X is given by
well let me write  this.
Each XI is distributed actually,
sorry, I'm just.
We have to assume that
conditions  on the value of Z, X
is given by another Gaussian with mean
given by mu plus lambda Z
and covariance given by matrix si.
So just to say the second line
in an equivalent form,
equivalently I'm going to model X
as mu plus lambda Z plus
a noise term epsilon
where  epsilon is Gaussian with mean zero
and covariant si.
And so the parameters of this model
are going to be a vector mu
with its n-dimensional
and matrix lambda,
which is n by D  and
a covariance matrix si, which is n by n,
and I'm going to impose
an additional  constraint on si.
I'm going to impose a constraint
that si is diagonal. Okay?
So that was a  form of definition
let me actually, sort of,
give a couple of examples
to make this more  complete.
So let's give a kind of example,
suppose Z is one-dimensional
and X is twodimensional
so let's see what this model –
let's see a, sort of,
specific instance of
the  factor analysis model
and how we're modeling the joint –
the distribution over X of
what this gives us in terms of
a model over P of X, all right?
So let's see.
From this model to let me assume that
lambda is 2, 1 and si,
which has to be diagonal matrix,
remember, is this.
Okay? So Z is one-dimensional
so let me just draw a  typical sample
for Z, all right?
So if I draw ZI from a Gaussian
so that's a typical sample  for
what Z might look like
and so I'm gonna at any rate
I'm gonna call this
Z1, Z2, Z3
and so on.
If this really were a typical sample
the order of the Z's
would be jumbled up,
but I'm just ordering them like this
just to make the example easier.
So, yes, typical  sample
of random variable Z from
a Gaussian distribution with
mean of covariance one.
So and with this example
let me just set mu equals zero.
It's to write the just that
it's  easier to talk about.
So lambda times Z, right?
We'll take each of these numbers
and  multiply them by lambda.
And so you find that all of the values
for lambda times Z will  lie on
a straight line, all right?
So, for example,
this one here would be one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, I guess.
So if this was Z7 then this one here
would be lambda times  Z7
and now that's the number in R2,
because lambda's a two by one matrix.
And so what  I've drawn here
is like a typical sample
for lambda times Z and the final step
for this is
what a typical sample for X looks like.
Well X is mu plus lambda Z plus epsilon
where  epsilon is Gaussian with
mean nu and covariance given by si,
right?
And so the last step
to draw a typical sample
for the random variables X
I'm gonna take these non
these are    really same as
mu plus lambda Z because mu is zero
in this example and around this  point
I'm going to place
an axis aligned ellipse.
Or in other words,
I'm going to create
a  Gaussian distribution centered
on this point and this
I've drawn corresponds
to one of the  contours of
my density for epsilon,
right?
And so you can imagine placing
a little  Gaussian bump here.
And so I'll draw an example
from this little Gaussian
and let's say I  get that point going,
I do the same here and so on.
So I draw a bunch of examples
from  these Gaussians and the –
the orange points I drew
whatever they call it –
will comprise a  typical sample
for whether distribution of X
is under this model.
Okay? Yeah?
Student:Would you add, like, mean?
Instructor:   Oh, say that again.
Student:Do you add mean into that?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, yes, you do.
And in this example,
I said you do a zero zero
just to make it easier.
If mu were something else
you'd take the whole picture
and you'd  sort of shift it
to whatever value of mu is. Yeah?
horizontal line right there,
which was Z.What did the X's,
of course,  what does that Y-axis
corresponds to?
so this is Z is one-dimensional
so here I'm plotting the  typical sample
for Z
so this is like zero.
So this is just the Z Axis, right.
So Z is onedimensional  data.
So this line here is like a plot of
a typical sample of values for Z.
Okay? Yeah?
Student:You have by axis, right?
And the axis data pertains samples.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, yes, right.
Student:So sort of projecting them
into that?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's not
talk about projections yet,
but, yeah, right.
So these  beige points –
so that's like X1 and that's X2
and so on, right?
So the beige points are  what I see.
And so in reality all you ever get
to see are the X's,
but just like in the mixture
of Gaussians model I tell a story
about what I would imagine the Gau
—the data came  from two Gaussian's
was is had a random variable Z
that led to the generation of X's
from two Gaussians.
So the same way I'm sort of telling
the story here,
which all the  algorithm actually
sees are the orange points,
but we're gonna tell a story about
how the  data came about and
that story is what comprises
the factor analysis model.
Okay? So one  of the ways to see
the intrusion of this model
is that we're going to think of
the model as  one way just informally,
not formally,
but one way to think about this model
is you can  think of this
factor analysis model as modeling
the data from coming from
a lower  dimensional subspace
more or less so the data X here Y
is approximately on one D line
and then plus a little bit of noise –
plus a little bit of random noise
so the X isn't exactly
on this one D line.
That's one informal way of
thinking about factor analysis.
We're not doing great on time. Well,
let's do this.
So let me just do one more quick
example,
which is, in this example,
let's say Z is in R2
and X is in R3, right?
And so in  this example Z,
your data Z now lies in 2-D
and so let me draw this
on a sheet of paper.  Okay?
So let's say the axis of my paper
are the Z1 and Z2 axis
and so here is a typical  sample
of point Z,
right?
And so we'll then take the sample Z
well, actually let me draw  this here
as well. All right.
So this is a typical sample for Z
going on the Z1 and Z2 axis
and I guess the origin would be here.
So center around zero.
And then we'll take those  and map it
to mu plus lambda Z
and what that means is
if you imagine the free space
of  this classroom is R3.
What that means is
we'll take this sample of Z's
and we'll map it to  position
in free space.
So we'll take this sheet of paper
and move it somewhere
and some  orientation in 3-D space.
And the last step is you have
X equals mu plus lambda Z plus  epsilon
and so you would take
the set of the points which align
in some plane in our 3-D  space
the variable of noise of these
and the noise will, sort of,
come from Gaussians
to  the axis aligned. Okay?
So you end up with a data
set that's sort of like
a fat pancake or a  little bit of fuzz
off your pancake.
So that's a model
let's actually talk about
how to fit  the parameters of the model.
Okay?   In order to describe
how to fit the model
I'm sure we need to re-write
Gaussians and this  is
in a very slightly different way.
So, in particular,
let's say I have a vector X
and I'm  gonna use this notation
to denote partition vectors, right?
X1, X2 where if X1 is
say an rdimensional  vector
then X2 is an estimational vector
and X is an R plus S dimensional  vector.
Okay? So I'm gonna use this notation
to denote just the taking of vector and,
sort  of, partitioning the vector
into two halves.
The first R elements followed
by the last S  elements.
So let's say you have X
coming from a Gaussian distribution
with mean mu
and covariance sigma where mu
is itself a partition vector.
So break mu up into two  pieces mu1
and mu2
and the covariance matrix sigma
is now a partitioned matrix. Okay?
So what this means is that
you take the covariance matrix sigma
and I'm going to break it  up
into four blocks, right?
And so the dimension of this is there
will be R elements here
and there will be S elements here
and there will be R elements here.
So, for example,
sigma 1, 2 will be an R
by S matrix.
It's R elements tall
and S elements wide.
So this Gaussian over to down
is really a joint distribution
of a loss of variables,
right?
So  X is a vector so XY
is a joint distribution over X1
through X of
over XN or over X of R  plus S.
We can then ask what are the marginal
and conditional distributions
of this  Gaussian?
So, for example,
with my Gaussian,
I know what P of X is,
but can I compute  the modular
distribution of X1, right.
And so P of X1 is just equal to,
of course, integrate  our X2,
P of X1 comma X2 DX2.
And if you actually perform
that distribution
that  computation you find that
P of X1, I guess,
is Gaussian with mean given by mu1
and  sigma 1, 1. All right.
So this is sort of no surprise.
The marginal distribution
of a  Gaussian is itself the Gaussian
and you just take out
the relevant sub-blocks
of the  covariance matrix
and the relevant sub-vector
of the mu vector E in vector mu.
You can  also compute conditionals.
You can also what does P of X1
given a specific value for  X2, right?
And so the way you compute that is,
well, the usual way P of X1
comma X2    divided by P of X2, right?
And so you know what
both of these formulas are,
right?
The  numerator well,
this is just a usual Gaussian
that your joint distribution over X1,
X2 is a  Gaussian with mean mu
and covariance sigma
and this by that marginalization
operation  I talked about is that.
So if you actually plug in
the formulas for these two Gaussians
and  if you simplify
the simplification step is actually
fairly non-trivial.
If you haven't seen it  before
this will actually be –
this will actually be somewhat
difficult to do.
But if you  plug this in
for Gaussian
and simplify that expression
you find that conditioned
on the  value of X2, X1 is
the distribution of X1 conditioned
on X2 is itself going to be  Gaussian
and it will have mean mu of 1 given 2
and covariant sigma of 1 given 2
where  well, so about
the simplification and derivation
I'm not gonna show the formula
for mu  given of mu of one given 2
is given by this and I think the sigma
of 1 given 2 is given  by that.
Okay?
So these are just
useful formulas to know for
how to find the conditional
distributions of  the Gaussian
and the marginal distributions
of a Gaussian.
I won't actually show
the  derivation for this.
Student:Could you repeat
the [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Sure.
So this one on the left mu
of 1 given 2 equals mu1
plus  sigma 1,2, sigma 2,
2 inverse times X2 minus mu2
and this is sigma 1 given 2 equals
sigma 1,1 minus sigma 1,2 sigma 2,
2 inverse sigma 2,1. Okay?
These are also in the  lecture notes.
Shoot. Nothing as
where I was hoping to on time. Well,
actually it is.  Okay?
So it turns out I think I'll skip
this in the interest of time.
So it turns out that well, so  let's
go back and use these in the factor
analysis model, right?
It turns out that you can go  back
and oh, do I want to do this?
I kind of need this though.
So let's go back and  figure out
just what the joint
distribution factor analysis
assumes on Z and X's. Okay?
So  under the factor analysis model Z
and X, the random variables Z
and X have some joint  distribution
given by I'll write
this vector as mu ZX
in some covariance matrix sigma.
So let's go back and figure out
what mu ZX is and what sigma is
and I'll do this
so that  we'll get a little bit more
practice with partition vectors
and partition matrixes.
So just to  remind you, right?
You have to have Z as Gaussian
with mean zero
and covariance  identity and X
is mu plus lambda Z plus epsilon
where epsilon is Gaussian with mean
zero covariant si.
So I have the
I'm just writing out
the same equations again.
So let's  first figure out
what this vector mu ZX is.
Well, the expected value of Z
is zero and,  again,
as usual I'll often drop
the square backers around here
And the expected value of  X is
well, the expected value
of mu plus lambda Z plus epsilon.
So these two terms  have zero
expectation
and so the expected value of X
is just mu and so that vector mu
ZX, right, in my parameter
for the Gaussian this is going to be
the expected value of this
partition vector given
by this partition Z and X
and so that would just be zero followed
by  mu. Okay?
And so that's a d-dimensional zero
followed by an indimensional mu.
That's  not gonna work out
what the covariance matrix sigma is.
So the covariance matrix sigma
if you work out definition
of a partition.
So this is into your partition matrix.
Okay?  Will be
so the covariance matrix sigma
will comprise four blocks like that
and so the   upper left most block,
which I write as sigma 1,1
well, that uppermost left block
is just  the covariance matrix of Z,
which we know is the identity.
I was gonna show you briefly
how to derive some of the other blocks,
right, so sigma 1,2 that's the upper
oh, actually,  excuse me.
Sigma 2,1
which is the lower left block
that's E of X minus EX times Z
minus EZ.
So X is equal to mu plus lambda Z
plus epsilon and then minus EX
is minus  mu and then times Z
because the expected value of Z is zero,
right, so that's equal to  zero.
And so if you simplify
or if you expand this out
plus mu minus mu cancel out
and  so you have the expected value
of lambda oh, excuse me.
ZZ transpose minus the  expected
value of epsilon Z is equal to that,
which is just equal to lambda times
the  identity matrix. Okay?
Does that make sense?
Cause this term is equal to zero.
Both  epsilon and Z are independent
and have zero expectation
so the second terms are zero.
Well, so the final block is sigma 2,2
which is equal to the expected value
of mu plus  lambda Z plus epsilon
minus mu times, right?
Is equal to and I won't do this,
but this  simplifies to lambda
lambda transpose plus si. Okay?
So putting all this together this tells
us that the joint distribution of this
vector ZX is going to be Gaussian
with mean vector  given by that,
which we worked out previously.
So this is the new ZX that
we worked out  previously,
and covariance matrix given by that.
let's see, so the  parameters
Okay? So in principle –
of our model are mu, lambda,
and si. And so in order to find
the parameters of  this model
we're given a training
set of m examples
and so we like to do a massive likely
estimation of the parameters.
And so in principle one thing
you could do is you can  actually
write down what P of XI is and,
right, so P of XI XI is actually
the distribution  of X, right?
If, again,
you can marginalize this Gaussian
and so the distribution of X,
which is the lower half of
this partition vector is going to
have mean mu and covariance  given by
lambda lambda transpose plus si.
Right?
So that's the distribution
that we're  using to model P of X.
And so in principle one thing
you could do is actually write down
the log likelihood of  your parameters,
right?
Which is just the product over of
it is the sum over I log P
of XI  where P of XI will be
given by this Gaussian density, right.
And I'm using theta as a  shorthand
to denote all of my parameters.
And so you actually know
what the density for  Gaussian is
and so you can say P of XI is
this Gaussian with E mu in covariance
given by  this
lambda lambda transpose plus si.
So in case you write down
the log likelihood of  your parameters
as follows and you can try
to take derivatives
of your log likelihood with  respect
to your parameters and maximize
the log likelihood, all right.
It turns out that if  you do that
you end up with sort of
an intractable atomization problem
you won't be able to find
the  massive likely estimate of
the parameters inclosed form.
So what I would have liked to  do
so in order to fit parameters
is– well,
to this model
what we'll actually do is use the  EM
Algorithm in with the E step, right?
We'll compute that and this formula
looks the  same except
that one difference is that now Z
is a continuous random variable
and so in  the E step we actually
have to find the density QI of ZI
where it's the, sort of,
E step  actually requires that
we find the posterior distribution
that so the density to the random
variable ZI
and then the M step
will then perform the following
maximization where,again,
because Z is now continuous
we now need to integrate over Z. Okay?
Where in the  M step now
because ZI was continuous we now have
an integral over Z
rather than a  sum.
Okay?
I was hoping to go a little bit further
r in deriving these things,
but I don't have time today
so we'll wrap that up
in the next lecture,
but before I close let's check
if there are  questions about
the whole factor analysis model.
Okay.
So we'll come back
in the next  lecture;
I will wrap up this model and
because I want to go a little bit deeper
into the E  and M steps,
as there's some tricky parts
for the factor analysis model
specifically. Okay.
I'll see you in a couple of days.