Okay. So welcome back.
What I want to do today is start a new chapter
in between now and then.
In particular, I want to talk about learning theory.
So in the previous, I guess eight lectures so far,
You've learned about a lot of learning algorithms,
and yes, you now I hope understand a little about some of
the best and most powerful tools of machine learning in the.
And all of you are now sort of well qualified to go into
industry and though powerful learning algorithms apply,
really the most powerful learning algorithms
we know to all sorts of problems,
and in fact, I hope you start to do
that on your projects right away as well.
You might remember,
I think it was in the very first lecture,
that I made an analogy to
if you're trying to learn to be a carpenter,
so if you imagine
you're going to carpentry school to learn to be a carpenter,
then only a small part of what you need to do
is to acquire a set of tools.
If you learn to be a carpenter
you don't walk in
and pick up a tool box and
so when you need to cut a piece of wood
do you use a rip saw,
or a jig saw, or a keyhole saw whatever,
is this really mastering the tools
there's also an essential part of becoming a good carpenter.
And what I want to do in the next few lectures
is actually give you a sense of the mastery
of the machine learning tools all of you have.
Okay?
And so in particular, in the next few lectures
what I want to is to talk more deeply about
the properties of different machine learning algorithms
so that you can get a sense of
when it's most appropriate to use each one.
And it turns out that
one of the most common scenarios in machine learning
is someday you'll be doing research or a company.
And you'll apply
one of the learning algorithms you learned about,
you may apply logistic regression,
or support vector machines,
or Na.ve Bayes or something,
and for whatever bizarre reason,
it won't work as well as you were hoping
or it won't quite do what you were hoping it to.
To me what really separates the people
from what really separates the people
that really understand and really get machine learning,
compared to people that maybe read the textbook
and so they'll work through the math,
will be what you do next.
Will be in your decisions of
when you apply a support vector machine
and it doesn't quite do what you wanted,
do you really understand enough
about support vector machines to know
what to do nextand how to modify the algorithm?
And to me that's often
what really separates the great people
in machine learning versus the people
that like read the text book and so they'll the math,
and so they'll have just understood that.
Okay?
So what I want to do today
is lecture will mainly be on learning theory
and we'll start to talk about some of the theoretical results
of machine learning.
The next lecture, later this week
will be on algorithms for sort of,
or fixing some of the problems that the learning theory
will point out to us and help us understand.
And then two lectures from now,
that lecture will be almost entirely focused on the practical
advice for how to apply learning algorithms. Okay?
So you have any questions about this before I start?
Okay.
So the very first thing we're gonna talk about is
something that you've probably already seen
on the first homework,
and something that alluded to previously,
which is the bias variance trade-off.
So take ordinary least squares,
the first learning algorithm we learned about,
if you  a straight line through these datas,
this is not a very good model.
Right. And if this happens,
we say it has underfit the data,
or we say that
this is a learning algorithm with a very high bias,
because it is failing
to fit the evident quadratic structure in the data.
And for the prefaces of you can formally think of the bias
of the learning algorithm as representing the fact that
even if you had an infinite amount of training data,
even if you had tons of training data,
this algorithm would still fail to fit the quadratic function
the quadratic structure in the data.
And so we think of
this as a learning algorithm with high bias.
Then
there's the opposite problem,
so that's the same dataset.
If you fit a fourth of the polynomials into this dataset,
then you have
you'll be able to
interpolate the five data points exactly,
but clearly,
this is also not a great model to the structure that you
and I probably see in the data.
And we say that this algorithm has a problem
excuse me, is overfitting the data
or alternatively that this algorithm has high variance.
Okay?
And the intuition behind overfitting a high variance is that
the algorithm is fitting serious patterns in the data,
or is fitting idiosyncratic properties of this specific dataset,
be it the dataset of housing prices
or whatever.
And quite often,
They'll be some happy medium
of fitting a quadratic function
that maybe won't interpolate
your data points perfectly
but also captures multi-structure
in your data than a simple
model which under fits.
I say that you can sort of have the exactly
the same picture of classification problems as well,
so lets say this is my training set, right,
of positive and negative examples,
and so you can fit logistic regression
with a very high order polynomial [inaudible],
or [inaudible] of X equals the sigmoid function of whatever.
Sigmoid function applied to
a tenth of the polynomial.
And you do that,
maybe you get a decision boundary like this. Right.
That does indeed perfectly separate the positive
and negative classes, this is another example of
how overfitting, and in contrast you fit logistic regression
into this model with just the linear features,
with none of the quadratic features,
then maybe you get a decision boundary like that,
which can also underfit. Okay.
So what I want to do now is
understand this problem
of overfitting versus underfitting,
of high bias versus high variance,
more explicitly, I will do that by posing a more formal
model of machine learning and so trying to prove
when these two twin problems
when each of these two problems come up.
And as I'm modeling the example for
our initial foray into learning theory,
I want to talk about learning classification,
in which H of X is equal to G of data transpose X. Okay?
So the learning classifier.
And for this class I'm going to use, Z
excuse me
I'm gonna use G as indicator Z grading with zero.
With apologies
in advance for changing the notation yet again,
for the support vector machine lectures
we use Y equals minus one or plus one.
For learning theory lectures,
turns out it'll be a bit cleaner if I switch back to
Y equals zero-one again,
so I'm gonna switch back to my original notation.
And so you think of this model as a model forum as logistic
regressions, say, and think of this
as being similar to logistic regression,
except that now we're going to
force the logistic regression algorithm,
to opt for labels that are either zero or one.
Okay?
So you can think of this as a classifier
to opt for labels zero or one involved in the probabilities.
And so as usual
Let's say we're given a training set of M examples.
That's just my notation
for writing a set of M examples
ranging from I equals one through M.
And I'm going to assume that
the training example is XIYI.
I've drawn IID,
from sum distribution, scripts D.
Okay? [Inaudible].
Identically and definitively distributed
and if you have you have running
a classification problem on houses,
like features of the house comma,
whether the house will be sold in the next six months,
then this is just the priority distribution over features of
houses and whether or not they'll be sold.
Okay?
So I'm gonna assume that
training examples we've drawn IID
from some probability distributions,
scripts D. Well, same thing for spam,
if you're trying to build a spam classifier then this would be
the distribution of what emails look like comma, whether
they are spam or not. And in particular,
to understand or simplify to understand the phenomena of
bias invariance, I'm actually going to use a simplified
model of machine learning.
And in particular, logistic regression fits this parameters
the model like this for maximizing the law of likelihood.
But in order to understand learning algorithms more deeply,
I'm just going to assume
a simplified model of machine learning,
let me just write that down.
So I'm going to define training error
as so this is a training error of
a hypothesis X subscript  data.
Write this epsilon hat of subscript data.
If I want to make the dependence on
a training set explicit,
I'll write this with a subscript S there where S is a training set.
And I'll define this as,
I hope the notation is clear.
This is a sum of indicator functions
for whether your hypothesis correctly classifies the Y the
IFE example. And so when you divide by M,
this is just in your training set what's the fraction of
training examples your hypothesis classifies
so defined as a training error.
And training error is also called risk.
The simplified model of machine learning I'm gonna talk
about is called empirical risk minimization.
And in particular, I'm going to assume that
the way my learning algorithm works is it will choose
parameters data, that minimize my training error.  Okay?
And it will be this learning algorithm
that we'll prove properties about.
And it turns out that you can think of
this as the most basic learning algorithm,
the algorithm that minimizes your training error.
It turns out that logistic regression and support vector
machines can be formally viewed as approximation cities,
so it turns out that if you actually want to do this,
this is a nonconvex optimization problem.
This is actually it actually [inaudible]
hard to solve this optimization problem.
And logistic regression and support vector machines
can both be viewed as approximations to
this nonconvex optimization problem
by finding the convex approximation to it.
Think of this as similar to what algorithms
like logistic regression are doing.
So let me take that definition of empirical risk minimization
and actually just rewrite it in a different equivalent way.
For the results I want to prove today,
it turns out that it will be useful to think of our learning
algorithm as not choosing a set of parameters,
but as choosing a function.
So let me say what I mean by that.
Let me define the hypothesis class, script h,
as the class of all hypotheses of
in other words
as the class of
all linear classifiers,
that your learning algorithm  is choosing from.
Okay? So H subscript data
is a specific linear classifier,
so H subscript data
in each of these functions each of these is a function
mapping from the input domain X
is the class zero-one.
Each of these is a function,
and as you vary the parameter's data,
you get different functions.
And so let me define the hypothesis class script H
to be the class of all functions
that say logistic regression can choose from.
Okay.
So this is the class of all linear classifiers
and so I'm going to define, or maybe redefine
empirical risk minimization as instead of writing this
choosing a set of parameters, I want to think of it
as choosing a function into hypothesis class of script H
that minimizes my training error.
Okay?
So actually can you raise your hand
if it makes sense to you
why this is equivalent to the previous formulation?
Okay, cool. Thanks.
So for development of the use of think of algorithms
as choosing from function from the class instead,
because in a more general case this set,
script H, can be some other class of functions.
Maybe is a class of all functions represented by viewer
network, or the class of all some other class of functions the
learning algorithm wants to choose from.
And this definition for empirical risk minimization
will still apply.
Okay?
So what we'd like to do is understand whether
empirical risk minimization is a reasonable algorithm.
Alex?
Student: a function that's defined by G of data TX,
or is it now more general?
Instructor (Andrew Ng): I see, right
so lets see I guess this the question is
H data still defined by G of phase transpose X,
is this more general?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Oh, yeah so very, two answers
to that. One is, this framework is general,
so for the purpose of this lecture
it may be useful to you to keep in mind a model
of the example of when H subscript data is the class of all
linear classifiers
such as those used by like a visectron algorithm
or logistic regression. This everything on this board,
however, is actually more general.
H can be any set of functions,
mapping from the INFA domain to the center
of class label zero and one,
and then you can perform
empirical risk minimization over any hypothesis class.
For the purpose of today's lecture,
I am going to restrict myself to talking about
binary classification,
but it turns out everything
I say generalizes to regression in other problem as well.
Does that answer your question?
Student:Yes.
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Cool. All right.
So I wanna understand if empirical risk minimization
is a reasonable algorithm.
In particular, what are the things we can prove about it?
So clearly we don't actually care about training error,
we don't really care about
making accurate predictions on the training set,
or at a least that's not the ultimate goal.
The ultimate goal is
how well it makes generalizationhow well it makes
predictions on examples that we haven't seen before.
How well it predicts prices
or sale or no sale outcomes of
houses you haven't seen before.
So what we really care about
is generalization error,
which I write as epsilon of H.
And this is defined as
the probability that if I sample a new example,
X comma Y, from that distribution scripts D,
my hypothesis mislabels that example.
And in terms of notational convention,
usually
if I use if I place a hat on top of something,
it usually means
not always
but it usually means that
it is an attempt to estimate something about the hat.
So for example, epsilon hat here
this is something that we're trying
think of epsilon hat training error
as an attempt to approximate generalization error.
Okay, so the notation convention is usually the things
with the hats on top are things we're using to estimate other quantities.
So the notion is
Another qauantities estimate
And H hat is a hypothesis output by learning algorithm
to try to estimate what the functions from H to Y, X to Y.
So let's actually prove some things about
when empirical risk minimization will do well in a sense of
giving us low generalization error,
which is what we really care about.
In order to prove our first learning theory result,
I'm going to have to state two lemmas,
the first is the union vowel,
which is the following,
let A1 through AK be K event.
And when I say events,
I mean events in a sense of a probabilistic
event that either happens or not.
And these are not necessarily independent.
So there's some current distribution over the events A one
through AK,
and maybe they're independent
maybe not,
no assumption on that.
Then the probability of A one or A two or dot, dot, dot, up
to AK, this union symbol,
this hat,
this just means this sort of just set notation
for probability just means ?°or.?±
So the probability of at least one of these events occurring,
of A one or A two, or up to AK,
this is S equal to the probability of A one plus probability of
A two plus dot, dot, dot, plus probability of AK. Okay?
So the intuition behind this is just that ¨
I'm not sure if you've seen
Venn diagrams depictions of probability before,
if you haven't,
what I'm about to do may be a little cryptic,
so just ignore that.
Just ignore what I'm about to do
if you haven't seen it before.
But if you have seen it before then
this is really
this is really great the probability of
A one, union A two, union A three,
is less than the P of A one,
plus P of A two, plus P of A three.
Right. So that the total mass in the union of
these three things [inaudible] to the sum of the masses in
the three individual sets, it's not very surprising.
It turns out that depending on
how you define your axioms of probability,
this is actually one of the axioms that probably varies,
so I won't actually try to prove this.
This is usually written as an axiom.
So sigmas of avitivity are probably measured as this
what is sometimes called as well.
But in learning theory
it's commonly called the union balance
I just call it that.
The other lemma I need is called
the Hufting inequality.
And again, I won't actually prove this,
I'll just state it,
which is let's let Z1 up to ZM, BM, IID,
there may be random variables with mean Phi.
So the probability of ZI equals 1 is equal to Phi.
So let's say you observe M IID
for newly random variables
and you want to estimate their mean.
So let me define Phi hat,
and this is again that notation, no convention,
Phi hat means
does not attempt is an estimate or something else.
So when we define Phi hat to be 1 over M,
semper my equals one through MZI.
Okay?
So this is our attempt to
estimate the mean of these Benuve random variables
by sort of taking its average.
And let any gamma be fixed.
Then, the Hufting inequality is that
the probability your estimate of Phi
is more than gamma away from the true value of Phi,
that this is bounded by two E
to the next of two gamma squared.
Okay?
So just in pictures ¨
so this theorem holds his lemma,
the Hufting inequality,
this is just a statement of fact,
this just holds true.
But let me now draw a cartoon to describe
some of the intuition behind this, I guess.
So lets say
this is a real number line
from zero to one.
And so Phi is the mean of your Benuve random variables.
You will remember from you know,
whatever some undergraduate probability or statistics class,
we told you
the central limit theorem that says
that when you average all the things together,
you tend to get a Gaussian distribution.
And so when you toss M coins
with bias Phi,
we observe these M Benuve random variables,
and we average them,
then the probability distribution of Phi hat
will roughly be a Gaussian lets say.
Okay?
It turns out if you haven't seen this up before,
this is actually that
the cumulative distribution function of Phi hat
will converse with that of the Gaussian.
Technically Phi hat can only take on
a discreet set of values
because these are factions one over Ms.
It doesn't really have an entity
but just as a cartoon think of it
as a converse roughly to a
Gaussian. So what the Hufting inequality says is that
if you pick a value of gamma,
let me put S one interval gamma
there's another interval gamma.
Then the saying that the probability mass of the details
the probability that my value of Phi hat is more than
a gamma away from the true value,
that the total mass that the total probability mass
in these tails is at most two E to the negative two gamma
squared M. Okay?
That's what the Hufting inequality
so if you can't read that this just says
this is just
the right hand side of the bound, two E to negative two
gamma squared. So balance the probability that
you make a mistake in estimating the mean of a Benuve
random variable.
And the cool thing about
this bound the interesting thing
behind this bound is that the exponentially in M, so it
says that for a fixed value of gamma,
as you increase the size of your training set,
as you toss a coin more and more,
then the worth of this Gaussian will shrink.
The worth of this Gaussian will actually
shrink like one over root to M.
And that will cause the probability mass left
in the tails to decrease exponentially,
quickly, as a function of that.
And this will be important later.
Yeah?
Student: Does this come from the central limit theorem.
Instructor (Andrew Ng): No it doesn't.
So this is proved by a different
this is proved no so the central limit theorem
there may be a version of the central limit theorem,
but the versions I'm familiar with tend
are sort of asymptotic,
but this works for any finer value of M.
Oh, and for your this bound holds
even if M is equal to two,
or M is [inaudible],
if M is very small,
the central limit theorem approximation is not gonna hold,
but this theorem holds regardless.
Okay?
I'm drawing this just
as a cartoon to help explain the intuition,
but this theorem just holds true,
without reference to central limit theorem.
All right.
So lets start to understand empirical risk minimization,
and what I want to do is begin
with studying empirical risk minimization for a  case
that's a logistic regression, and in particular
I want to start with studying
the case of finite hypothesis classes.
So let's say script H is a class of K hypotheses.
Right. So this is K functions w
ith no each of these is just a function mapping
from inputs to outputs,
there's no parameters in this.
And so what the empirical risk minimization would do is
it would take the training set
and it'll then look at each of these K functions,
and it'll pick whichever of these functions has the lowest
training error. Okay?
So now that the logistic regression
uses an infinitely large a continuous infinitely large class of
hypotheses, script H,
but to prove the first row I actually want to just describe
our first learning theorem is all for the case of
when you have a finite hypothesis class,
then we'll later generalize that into the hypothesis classes.
So empirical risk minimization
takes the hypothesis of the lowest training error,
and what I'd like to do is prove a bound
on the generalization error of H hat.
All right. So in other words
I'm gonna prove that
somehow minimizing training error
allows me to do well on generalization error.
And here's the strategy,
the first step in this prove I'm going to show that
training error is a good approximation to generalization
error, and then I'm going to show that
this implies a bound on the generalization error of
the hypothesis of  empirical risk minimization.
And I just realized, this class I guess
is also maybe slightly notation heavy class round, instead of
just introducing a reasonably large set of new symbols,
so if again, in the course of today's lecture,
you're looking at some symbol
and you don't quite remember what it is,
please raise your hand and ask.
what's that, what was that,
was that a generalization error
or was it something else?
So raise your hand and ask if you don't understand what
the notation I was defining.
Okay. So let me introduce this in two steps.
And the empirical risk strategy is
I'm gonna show training errors that
give approximation generalization error,
and this will imply that minimizing training error
will also do pretty well
in terms of minimizing generalization error.
And this will give us a bound on the generalization error of
the hypothesis output by empirical risk minimization.
Okay?
So here's the idea.
So lets even not consider all the hypotheses at once,
lets pick any hypothesis,
HJ in the class script H,
and so until further notice lets just consider there one fixed
hypothesis. So pick any one hypothesis
and let's talk about that one.
Let me define ZI
to be indicator function for
whether this hypothesis misclassifies the IFE example
excuse me or Z subscript I. Okay?
So ZI would be zero or one depending on whether this one
hypothesis which is the only one I'm gonna even consider
whether this hypothesis was classified as an example.
And so my training set is
drawn randomly from sum distribution scripts d,
and depending on what training examples I've got,
these ZIs would be either zero or one.
So let's figure out what the probability distribution ZI is.
Well, so ZI takes on the value of either zero or one
so clearly is
a Benuve random variable,
it can only take on these values.
Well, what's the probability that ZI is equal to one?
In other words,
what's the probability that from a fixed hypothesis HJ,
when I sample my training set IID from distribution D,
what is the chance that my hypothesis will misclassify it?
Well, by definition,
that's just a generalization error of my hypothesis HJ.
So ZI is a Benuve random variable with mean given by
the generalization error of this hypothesis.
Raise your hand if that made sense. Oh, cool. Great.
And moreover, all the ZIs
have the same probability of being one,
and all my training examples I've drawn are IID,
and so the ZIs are also independent
and therefore the ZIs themselves are IID random variables.
Okay?
Because my training examples
were drawn independently of each other, by assumption.
If you read this as the definition of training error,
the training error of my hypothesis HJ, that's just that.
That's just the average of my ZIs,
which was , well I previously defined it like this.
Okay?
And so epsilon hat of HJ is exactly the average of MIID,
Benuve random variables,
drawn from Benuve distribution
with mean given by the generalization error,
so well this is the average of MIID
Benuve random variables,
each of which has meaning
given by the generalization error of HJ.
And therefore, by the Hufting inequality
we have to add the probability that the difference
between training and generalization error,
the probability that this is greater than gamma is less than
to two, E to the negative two, gamma squared M. Okay?
Exactly by the Hufting inequality.
And what this proves is that,
for my fixed hypothesis HJ,
my training error,
epsilon hat will with high probability,
assuming M is large,
if M is large than
this thing on the right hand side will be small,
because this is two Es
and a negative two gamma squared M.
So this says that if my training set is large enough,
then the probability my training error
is far from generalization error,
meaning that it is more than gamma,
will be small,
will be bounded by this thing on the right hand side. Okay?
Now, here's the tricky part,
what we've done is approve this bound
for one fixed hypothesis,
for HJ.
What I want to prove is that training error
will be a good estimate for generalization error,
not just for this one hypothesis HJ,
but actually for all K hypotheses
in my hypothesis class script H.
So let's do it, well, better do it on a new board.
So in order to show that,
let me define a random event,
let me define AJ to be the event
that to be the event that you know,
the difference between training and generalization error
is more than gamma on a hypothesis HJ.
And so what we put on the previous board was that
the probability of AJ is less equal to
two E to the negative two, gamma squared M,
and this is pretty small.
Now, What I want to bound is the probability that
there exists some hypothesis in my class script H,
such that I make a large error in my estimate of
generalization error. Okay?
Such that this holds true.
So this is really just that the probability that
there exists a hypothesis for which this holds.
This is really the probability
that A one or A two, or up to AK holds.
The chance there exists a hypothesis is just well the priority
that for hypothesis one and make a large error
in estimating the generalization error,
or for hypothesis two and make a large error in estimating
generalization error, and so on.
And so by the union bound,
this is less than equal to that,
which is therefore less than
equal to is equal to that. Okay?
So let me just take one minus both sides of the equation
on the previous board
let me take one minus both sides,
so the probability that there does not exist for hypothesis
such that  . The probability that there does not exist a
hypothesis on which I make a large error in this estimate
while this is equal to
the probability that for all hypotheses,
I make a small error,
or at most gamma, in my estimate of generalization error.
In taking one minus on the right hand side
I get two KE to the negative two gamma squared M.
Okay?
And so
and the sign of the inequality flipped
because I took one minus both sides.
The minus sign flips the sign of the equality.
So what we're shown is that
with probability which abbreviates to
WP with probability
one minus two KE to the negative two gamma squared M.
We have that, epsilon hat of H will be
then gamma of epsilon of H,
simultaneously for all hypotheses in our class script H.
And so just to give this result a name,
this is called, one instance of what's called a uniform
conversions result, and the term uniform conversions this
sort of alludes to the fact that
this shows that as M becomes large,
then these epsilon hats will all simultaneously converge
to epsilon of H.
That training error will become very close to
generalization error simultaneously for all hypotheses H.
That's what the term uniform refers to,
is the fact that this converges for all hypotheses H
and not just for one hypothesis.
And so what we're shown is one example of
a uniform conversions result.
Okay?
So let me clean a couple more boards.
I'll come back
and ask what questions you have about this.
We should take another look at this and make sure it all
makes sense. Yeah, okay.
What questions do you have about this?
Student: How the is the value of gamma computed?
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Right. Yeah. So let's see,
the question is how is the value of gamma computed?
So for these purposes,
gamma is a constant.
Imagine
a gamma is some constant
that we chose in advance  and this is a bound
that holds true for any fixed value of gamma.
Later on as we take this bound
and then sort of develop this result further,
we'll choose specific values of gamma as  of this bound.
For now we'll just imagine that
when we're proved
this holds true for any value of gamma.
Any questions? Yeah?
Student:[Inaudible] hypothesis phase is infinite [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes,
the labs in the hypothesis phase is infinite,
so this simple result won't work in this present form,
but we'll generalize this probably won't get to it today
but we'll generalize this at the beginning
of the next lecture
to infinite hypothesis classes.
Student:How do we use this theory ?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):How do you use theorem factors?
So let me, I might get to a little of that later today,
we'll talk concretely about algorithms,
the consequences of the understanding
of these things in the next lecture as well.
Yeah, okay? Cool.
Can you just raise your hand
if the things I've proved so far make sense?
Okay. Cool. Great. Thanks.
All right. Let me just take this uniform conversions
bound and rewrite it in a couple of other forms.
So this is a sort of a bound on probability,
this is saying suppose
I fix my training set and then fix my training set
And fix my threshold, my error threshold gamma,
what is the probability that uniform conversions holds,
and well, that's my formula that gives the answer.
This is the probability of something happening.
So there are actually three parameters of interest.
One is, ?°What is this probability'±
The other parameter is,
What's the training set size M?
And the third parameter is,
What is the value of this error threshold gamma?
I'm not gonna vary K for these purposes.
So other two other equivalent forms of the bounds,
which  so you can ask,
Given gamma ¨so what we proved was given gamma
and given M,
what is the probability of uniform conversions?
The other equivalent forms are,
so that given gamma and the probability delta of
making a large error,
how large a training set size do you need in order to give a
bound on how large a training set size do you need to give a
uniform conversions bound with parameters gamma
and delta?
And well,
so if you set delta to be
two KE so negative two gamma squared M.
This is that form that I had on the left.
And if you solve for M,
what you find is that there's an equivalent form of this
result that says that so long as your training set assigns M
as greater than this.
And this is the formula that I get by solving for M.
Okay?
So long as M is greater than equal to this,
then with probability,
which I'm abbreviating to WP again,
with probability at least one minus delta
we have for all.
Okay?
So this says how large a training set size that
I need to guarantee that
with probability
at least one minus delta,
we have the training error is
within gamma of generalization error for all my
hypotheses, and this gives an answer.
And just to give this another name,
this is an example of a sample complexity bound.
So from undergrad computer science classes
you may have heard of computational complexity,
which is how much computations
you need to achieve something.
So sample complexity just means
how large a training example
how large a sample of examples do you need
in order to achieve a certain bound and error.
And it turns out that in many of the theorems
we write out you can pose them
in sort of a form of probability bound
or a sample complexity bound or in some other form.
I personally often find
the sample complexity bounds the most easy to interpret
because it says
how large a training set do
you need to give a certain bound on the errors.
And in fact well, we'll see this later,
sample complexity bounds often sort of
help to give guidance for really
if you're trying to achieve something
on a machine learning problem,
this really is trying to give guidance on
how much training data you need to prove something.
The one thing I want to note here is that
M grows like the log of K, right,
so the log of K grows
extremely slowly as a function of K.
The log is one of the slowest growing functions, right.
It's one of well, some of you may have heard this, right?
That for all values of K,
right, I learned this
from a colleague, Andrew Moore, at Carnegie Mellon that
in computer science
for all practical purposes for all values of K,
log K is less, 30 this is almost true.
So log K is, logs is one of the slowest growing functions,
and so the fact that M sample complexity grows
like the log of K,
means that you can increase this number of hypotheses
in your hypothesis class quite a lot
and the number of the training examples you need
won't grow very much. [Inaudible].
This property
will be important later
when we talk about infinite hypothesis classes.
The final form is the
I guess is sometimes called the error bound,
which is when you hold M and delta fixed and
solved for gamma.
And so and what do you do what you get then is that
the probability at least one minus delta, we have that.
For all hypotheses in my hypothesis class,
the difference in the training generalization error
would be less than equal to that.
Okay?
And that's just solving for gamma
and plugging the value I get in there. Okay?
All right.
So the second step of the overall proof
I want to execute is the following.
The result of the training error is
essentially that uniform conversions will hold true with
high probability. What I want to show now is
let's assume that uniform conversions hold.
So let's assume that for all hypotheses H,
we have that epsilon of
H minus epsilon hat of H, is less than of the gamma.
Okay?
What I want to do now is
use this to see what we can prove about the bound of
see what we can prove about the generalization error.
So I want to know
suppose this holds true
I want to know can we prove something about
the generalization error of H hat, where again,
H hat was the hypothesis selected by empirical risk
minimization. Okay?
So in order to show this, let me make one more definition,
let me define H star,
to be the hypothesis in my class script H
that has the smallest generalization error.
So this is if I had an infinite amount of training data
or if I really I could go in
and find the best possible hypothesis
the best possible hypothesis
in the sense of minimizing generalization error
what's the hypothesis I would get? Okay?
So in some sense,
it sort of makes sense to compare the performance
of our learning algorithm to the performance of H star,
because we sort of, we clearly can't hope to do better
than H star.
Another way of saying that is that if your hypothesis class
is a class of all linear decision boundaries,
that the data just can't be separated
by any linear functions.
So if even H star is really bad,
then there's sort of it's unlikely then there's just not
much hope that your learning algorithm could do even
better than H star.
So I actually prove this result in three steps.
So the generalization error of H hat,
the hypothesis I chose,
this is going to be less than equal to that,
actually let me number these equations, right.
This is  because of equation one,
because I see that epsilon of H hat and epsilon hat of H hat
will then gamma of each other. Now because H star,
excuse me, now by the definition
of empirical risk minimization, H hat was chosen to
minimize training error and so there can't be any
hypothesis with lower training error than H hat.
So the training error of H hat must be less than
the equal to the training error of H star.
So this is sort of by two,
or by the definition of H hat,
as the hypothesis that minimizes training error H hat.
And the final step is
I'm going to apply this uniform conversions result again.
We know that
epsilon hat of H star must be
moving gamma of epsilon of H star.
And so this is at most plus gamma.
Then I have my original gamma there. Okay?
And so this is by equation one again
because, oh, excuse me ¨
because I know the training error of H star
must be moving gamma
of the generalization error of H star.
And so well, I'll just write this as plus two gamma.
Okay? Yeah?
Student:[inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Oh, okay. Let me just, well,
let me write that down on this board.
So actuallyactually let me think fit this in here.
So epsilon hat of H is the training error of the hypothesis H.
In other words, given the hypothesisa
hypothesis is just a function
right mapped from X or Y
so epsilon hat of H
is given the hypothesis H,
what's the fraction of training examples it misclassifies?
And generalization error of H,
is given the hypothesis H
if I sample another example from my distribution scripts D,
what's the probability
that H will misclassify that example?
Does that make sense?
Student:[Inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Oh, okay.
And H hat is the hypothesis that's chosen by empirical
risk minimization. So when I talk about empirical risk
minimization, is the algorithm that minimizes training error,
and so epsilon hat of H
is the training error of H,
and so H hat is defined as the hypothesis
that out of all hypotheses in my class script H, t
he one that minimizes training error epsilon hat of H.
Okay? All right. Yeah?
Student:
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Yes it is.
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng): I'll talk about that later.
So let me tie all these things together into a theorem.
Let there be a hypothesis class
Given with a finite set
of K hypotheses
and let any M delta be fixed.
Then  so I fixed M and delta,
so this will be the error bound form of the theorem
right?
Then with probability at least one minus delta.
We have that.
The generalization error of H hat
is less than or equal to the minimum over all hypotheses
in set H epsilon of H, plus two times, plus that. Okay?
So to prove this, well,
this term of course is just epsilon of H star.
And so to prove this
we set gamma to equal to that
this is two times the square root term.
To prove this theorem
we set gamma to equal to that square root term.
Say that again?
Student:[Inaudible].
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Wait. Say that again?
Instructor (Andrew Ng): Oh, yes. Thank you.
That didn't make sense at all.
Thanks. Great.
So set gamma to that square root term,
and so we know equation one, right
from the previous board holds
with probability one minus delta.
Right. Equation one was the uniform conversions result
right, that well, IE.
This is equation one from the previous board, right
so set gamma equal to this we know that
we'll probably use one minus delta
this uniform conversions holds,
and whenever that holds,
that implies
you know,
I guess if we call this equation star
And whenever uniform conversions holds,
we showed again,
on the previous boards
that this result holds,
that generalization error of H hat
is less than two, generalization error of H star  plus two times gamma.
Okay?
And so that proves this theorem.
So this result sort of helps us
to quantify a little bit that bias variance tradeoff
that I talked about at the beginning of actually
near the very start of this lecture.
And in particular let's say
I have some hypothesis class script H,
that I'm using, maybe as a class of all linear functions
and linear regression, and logistic regression with just the
linear features. And let's say I'm considering
switching to some new class H prime
by having more features.
So lets say this is linear
and this is quadratic
so the class of all linear functions
and the subset of the class of all quadratic functions,
and so H is the subset of H prime.
And let's say I'm considering, instead of using my
linear hypothesis class, let's say I'm considering
switching to a quadratic hypothesis class
or switching to a larger hypothesis class.
Then what are the tradeoffs involved?
Well, I proved this only for finite hypothesis classes,
but we'll see that something very similar holds for
infinite hypothesis classes too.
But the tradeoff is
what if I switch from H to H prime,
or I switch from
linear to quadratic functions.
Then epsilon of H star will become better
because the best hypothesis in my hypothesis class will
become better. The best quadratic function
by best I mean in the sense of generalization error  the
hypothesis function
the quadratic function with the lowest generalization error
has to have equal or more likely lower generalization error
than the best linear function.
So by switching to a more complex hypothesis class
you can get this first term as you go down.
But what I pay for then is that K will increase.
By switching to a larger hypothesis class,
the first term will go down,
but the second term will increase
because I now have a larger class of hypotheses
and so the second term K will increase.
And so this is sometimes called the bias
this is usually called the bias variance tradeoff.
Whereby going to larger hypothesis class
maybe I have the hope for finding a better function,
that my risk of sort of not fitting my model so accurately
also increases, and that's because
illustrated by the second term going up
when the size of your hypothesis, when K goes up.
And so speaking very loosely,
we can think of this first term as corresponding maybe to
the bias of the learning algorithm, or the bias of the
hypothesis class. And you canagain speaking very loosely, t
hink of the second term as corresponding to the variance in  your hypothesis,
in other words
how well you can actually fit a hypothesis in the
how well you actually fit this hypothesis class to the data.
And by switching to a more complex hypothesis class,
your variance increases
and your bias decreases.
As a note of warning,
it turns out that if you take like a statistics class
you've seen definitions of bias and variance,
which are often defined in terms of squared error
or something. It turns out that for classification problems,
there actually is no universally accepted formal definition
of bias and variance for classification problems.
For regression problems,
there is this square error definition.
For classification problems
it turns out there've been several competing proposals
for definitions of bias and variance.
So when I say bias and variance here,
think of these as very loose,
informal, intuitive definitions,
and not formal definitions.
Okay. The cartoon associated with intuition
I just said would be as follows:
Let's say and everything about the plot
will be for a fixed value of M,
for a fixed training set size M.
Vertical axis I'll plot ever
and on the horizontal axis I'll plot model complexity.
And by model complexity I mean sort of degree of
polynomial, size of your hypothesis class script H etc.
It actually turns out, you remember the bandwidth
parameter from locally weighted linear regression,
that also has a similar effect in controlling
how complex your model is.
Model complexity [inaudible] polynomial I guess.
So the more complex your model,
the better your training error,
and so your training error will tend to zero
as you increase the complexity of your model
because the more complete your model
the better you can fit your training set.
But because of this bias variance tradeoff,
you find that generalization error will come down
for a while and then it will go back up.
And this regime on the left is
when you're underfitting the data
or when you have high bias. And this regime on the right is
when you have high variance or you're overfitting the data.
Okay?
And this is why
a model of sort of intermediate complexity,
somewhere here if often preferable to if
and minimize generalization error. Okay?
So that's just a cartoon.
In the next lecture we'll actually talk about
the number of algorithms for trying
to automatically select model complexities,
say to get you as close as possible to this minimum
to this area of minimized generalization error.
The last thing I want to do is
actually going back to the theorem I wrote out,
I just want to take that theorem well,
so the theorem I wrote out was
about the error theorem
it says
an error bound theorem this says for fixed M
delta where probability one minus delta,
I get a bound on gamma,
which is what this term is.
So the very last thing I wanna do today is
just come back to this theorem and write out a corollary
where I'm gonna fix gamma,
I'm gonna fix my error bound,
and fix delta and solve for M.
And if you do that,
you get the following corollary:
Let H
be fixed with K hypotheses
and let any delta and gamma be fixed.
Then in order to guarantee that,
let's say I want a guarantee that the generalization error of
the hypothesis I choose with empirical risk minimization,
that this is at most two times gamma worse than the best
possible error I could obtain with this hypothesis class.
Lets say I want this to hold true with probability
at least one minus delta, then it suffices that M is to that.
Okay?
And this is sort of solving for the error bound for M.
One thing we're going to convince yourselves
of the easy part of this is if you set that term gamma
and solve for M you will get this.
One thing I want you to go home and sort of convince
yourselves of is that this result really holds true.
That this really logically follows
from the theorem
we've proved.
In other words,
you can take that formula we wrote and solve for M
because this is the formula you get for M,
that's just that's the easy part.
That once you go back and convince yourselves
that this theorem is a true fact and that it does indeed
logically follow from the other one.
In particular,
make sure that if you solve for that
you really get M grading equals this,
and why is this M grading that
and not M less equal two,
and just make sure, I can write this down a
nd it sounds plausible why don't you just go back
and convince yourself this is really true. Okay?
And it turns out that
when we prove these bounds in learning theory
it turns out that very often the constants are sort of loose.
So it turns out that
when we prove these bounds usually we're interested
usually we're not very interested in the constants,
and so I write this
as big O of one over gamma squared, log K over delta,
and again, the key step in this is that the dependence on
M with the size of the hypothesis class is logarithmic.
And this will be very important later
when we talk about infinite hypothesis classes.
Okay?
Any questions about this? No? Okay, cool.
So next lecture we'll come back,
we'll actually start from this result again.
Remember this.
I'll write this down as the first thing I do in the next
lecture and we'll generalize these to infinite hypothesis
classes and then talk about
practical algorithms for model spectrum.
So I'll see you guys in a couple days.