Instructor (Andrew Ng):Okay. Good morning
and welcome back to the third lecture of this class.
So here's what I want to do today,
and some of the topics I do today
may seem a little bit like I'm jumping,
sort of, from topic to topic,
but here's, sort of, the outline for today
and the illogical flow of ideas.
In the last lecture, we talked about linear regression
and today I want to talk about sort of
an adaptation of that called locally weighted regression.
It's very a popular algorithm
that's actually one of my former mentors
probably favorite machine learning algorithm.
We'll then talk about a probable second interpretation
of linear regression and use that
to move onto our first classification algorithm,
which is logistic regression;
take a brief digression to tell you
about something called the perceptron algorithm,
which is something we'll come back to,
again, later this quarter;
and time allowing I hope
to get to Newton's method,
which is an algorithm
for fitting logistic regression models.
So this is recap
where we're talking about in the previous lecture,
remember the notation I defined was that
I used this X superscript I,
Y superscript I to denote the I training example.
And when we're talking about linear regression
or linear least squares, we use this
to denote the predicted value
of "by my hypothesis H" on the input XI.
And my hypothesis was franchised
by the vector of grams as theta and so
we said that this was equal to some from theta J, si J,
and more theta transpose X.
And we had the convention that
X subscript Z is equal to one so this accounts for
the intercept term in our linear regression model.
And lowercase n here was the notation I was using
for the number of features in my training set. Okay?
So in the example
when trying to predict housing prices,
we had two features,
the size of the house and the number of bedrooms.
We had two features and there was
little n was equal to two.
So just to finish recapping the previous lecture,
we defined this quadratic cos function J
of theta equals one-half,
something I equals one to m,
theta of XI minus YI squared where
this is the sum over our m training examples
and my training set.
So lowercase m was the notation I've been using
to denote the number of training examples I have
and the size of my training set.
And at the end of the last lecture,
we derive the value of theta that
minimizes this enclosed form,
which was X transpose X inverse X transpose Y. Okay?
So as we move on in today's lecture,
I'll continue to use this notation and, again,
I realize this is a fair amount of
notation to all remember,
so if partway through this lecture you forgot
if you're having trouble remembering
what lowercase m is or what lowercase n is
or something please raise your hand and ask.
When we talked about linear regression
last time we used two features.
One of the features was the size
of the houses in square feet,
so the living area of the house,
and the other feature was
the number of bedrooms in the house.
In general, we apply a machine-learning algorithm
to some problem that you care about.
The choice of the features will very much
be up to you, right?
And the way you choose your features
to give the learning algorithm will often have
a large impact on how it actually does.
So just for example, the choice we made
last time was X1 equal this size,
and let's leave this idea of the feature of the number
of bedrooms for now, let's say we don't have data
that tells us how many bedrooms are in these houses.
One thing you could do is actually define
oh, let's draw this out. And so, right?
So say that was the size of the house
and that's the price of the house.
So if you use this as a feature maybe you get
theta zero plus theta 1, X1, this, sort of, linear model.
If you choose
let me just copy the same data set over, right?
You can define the set of features
where X1 is equal to the size of the house
and X2 is the square of the size of the house. Okay?
So X1 is the size of the house in say square footage
and X2 is just take whatever the square footage
of the house is and just square that number,
and this would be another way
to come up with a feature,
and if you do that then the same algorithm will end up
fitting a quadratic function for you.
Theta 2, XM squared. Okay?
Because this is actually X2.
And depending on what the data looks like,
maybe this is a slightly better fit to the data.
You can actually take this even further, right?
Which is let's see.
I have seven training examples here,
so you can actually maybe fit up
to six for the polynomial.
You can actually fill a model theta zero plus theta one,
X1 plus theta two, X squared plus up to theta six.
X to the power of six and theta six
are the polynomial to these seven data points.
And if you do that you find that
you come up with a model
that fits your data exactly.
This is where, I guess, in this example I drew,
we have seven data points,
so if you fit a six model polynomial you can, sort of,
fit a line that passes through
these seven points perfectly.
And you probably find that
the curve you get will look something like that.
And on the one hand,
this is a great model in a sense
that it fits your training data perfectly.
On the other hand, this is probably not
a very good model in the sense that
none of us seriously think that
this is a very good predictor of housing prices
as a function of the size of the house, right?
So we'll actually come back to this later.
It turns out of the models we have here;
I feel like maybe the quadratic model fits the data best.
Whereas the linear model looks like
there's actually a bit of a quadratic component
in this data that the linear function is not capturing.
So we'll actually come back to this a little bit later
and talk about the problems associated with
fitting models that are either too simple,
use two small a set of features,
or on the models that are too complex
and maybe use too large a set of features.
Just to give these a name,
we call this the problem of underfitting and,
very informally, this refers to a setting where
there are obvious patterns that
where there are
patterns in the data that
the algorithm is just failing to fit.
And this problem here we refer to as overfitting
and, again, very informally,
this is when the algorithm is fitting
the idiosyncrasies of
this specific data set, right?
It just so happens that of the seven houses
we sampled in Portland,
or wherever you collect data from,
that house happens to be a bit more expensive,
that house happened on the less expensive,
and by fitting six for the polynomial we're, sort of,
fitting the idiosyncratic properties of this data set,
rather than the true underlying trends of
how housing prices vary
as the function of the size of house. Okay?
So these are two very different problems.
We'll define them more formally me later
and talk about how to address each of these problems,
but for now I hope you appreciate that
there is this issue of selecting features.
So if you want to just teach us the learning problems
there are a few ways to do so.
We'll talk about feature selection algorithms later
this quarter as well.
So automatic algorithms for choosing
what features you use in a regression problem like this.
What I want to do today is talk about a class of algorithms
called non-parametric learning algorithms that
will help to alleviate the need somewhat
for you to choose features very carefully. Okay?
And this leads us into our discussion
of locally weighted regression.
And just to define the term, linear regression,
as we've defined it so far,
is an example of a parametric learning algorithm.
Parametric learning algorithm is one
that's defined as an algorithm that
has a fixed number of parameters that
fit to the data. Okay?
So in linear regression
we have a fix set of parameters theta, right?
That must fit to the data.
In contrast, what I'm gonna talk about now
is our first non-parametric learning algorithm.
The formal definition, which is not very intuitive,
so I've replaced it with a second, say, more intuitive.
The, sort of, formal definition of the non-
parametric learning algorithm is that
it's an algorithm where
the number of parameters goes with M,
with the size of the training set.
And usually it's defined as a number of parameters
grows linearly with the size of the training set.
This is the formal definition.
A slightly less formal definition is that
the amount of stuff that your learning algorithm
needs to keep around will grow linearly
with the training sets or,
in another way of saying it,
is that this is an algorithm that
we'll need to keep around an entire training set,
even after learning. Okay?
So don't worry too much about this definition.
But what I want to do now is describe a specific
non-parametric learning algorithm
called locally weighted regression.
Which also goes by a couple of other names
which also goes by the name of Loess
for self-hysterical reasons.
Loess is usually spelled L-O-E-S-S,
sometimes spelled like that, too.
I just call it locally weighted regression.
So here's the idea.
This will be an algorithm that
allows us to worry a little bit less about
having to choose features very carefully.
So for my motivating example,
let's say that I have a training site
that looks like this, okay? So this is X and that's Y.
If you run linear regression on this
and you fit maybe a linear function to this
and you end up with a more or less flat,
straight line, which is not a very good fit to this data.
You can sit around and stare at this and try to
decide whether the features are used right.
So maybe you want to toss in a quadratic function,
but this isn't really quadratic either.
So maybe you want to model this as a X plus X squared
plus maybe some function of sin of X or something.
You actually sit around and fiddle with features.
And after a while you can probably come up with
a set of features that the model is okay,
but let's talk about an algorithm that
you can use without needing to do that.
So if well, suppose you want to
evaluate your hypothesis H at a certain point
with a certain query point low K is X. Okay?
And let's say you want to know what's
the predicted value of Y at this position of X, right?
So for linear regression, what we were doing
was we would fit theta to minimize sum over I,
YI minus theta, transpose XI squared,
and return theta transpose X. Okay?
So that was linear regression.
In contrast, in locally weighted linear regression
you're going to do things slightly different.
You're going to look at this point X
and then I'm going to look in my data set
and take into account only the data points that are,
sort of, in the little vicinity of X. Okay?
So we'll look at where I want to value my hypothesis.
I'm going to look only in the vicinity of this point
where I want to value my hypothesis,
and then I'm going to take, let's say,
just these few points,
and I will apply linear regression to fit a straight line
just to this sub-set of the data. Okay?
I'm using this sub-term sub-set
well let's come back to that later.
So we take this data set
and I fit a straight line to it
and maybe I get a straight line like that.
And what I'll do is then evaluate
this particular value of straight line
and that will be the value I return for my algorithm.
I think this would be the predicted value for
this would be the value of then my hypothesis outputs
in locally weighted regression. Okay?
So we're gonna fall one up.
Let me go ahead and formalize that.
In locally weighted regression,
we're going to fit theta to minimize sum over I
to minimize that where these terms W
superscript I are called weights.
There are many possible choice for ways,
I'm just gonna write one down.
So this E's and minus, XI minus X squared over two.
So let's look at what these weights really are, right?
So notice that
suppose you have a training example XI.
So that XI is very close to X. So this is small, right?
Then if XI minus X is small,
so if XI minus X is close to zero,
then this is E's to the minus zero
and E to the zero is one. So if XI is close to X,
then WI will be close to one. In other words,
the weight associated with the,
I training example be close to one if XI
and X are close to each other.
Conversely if XI minus X is large then
I don't know, what would WI be?
Student:Zero.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Zero, right. Close to zero.
Right. So if XI is very far from X
then this is E to the minus of some large number
and E to the minus some large number
will be close to zero. Okay?
So the picture is, if I'm quarrying at a certain point X,
shown on the X axis, and if my data set, say,
look like that, then I'm going to give the points
close to this a large weight
and give the points far away a small weight.
So for the points that are far away,
WI will be close to zero.
And so as if for the points that are far away,
they will not contribute much
at all to this summation, right?
So I think this is sum over I
of one times this quadratic term for points by points
plus zero times this quadratic term for faraway points.
And so the effect of using this weighting is that
locally weighted linear regression
fits a set of parameters theta,
paying much more attention
to fitting the points close by accurately.
Whereas ignoring the contribution from faraway points.
Okay? Yeah?
Student:Your Y is exponentially  [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah. Let's see.
So it turns out there are many other
weighting functions you can use.
It turns out that there are definitely different
communities of researchers that tend to
choose different choices by default.
There is somewhat of a literature
on debating what point
exactly what function to use.
This, sort of,
exponential decay function is
this happens to be a reasonably common one that
seems to be a more reasonable choice on many problems,
but you can actually plug in other functions as well.
Did I mention what [inaudible] is it at?
For those of you that are familiar
with the normal distribution,
or the Gaussian distribution, say this
what this formula I've written out here,
it cosmetically looks a bit like a Gaussian distribution.
Okay? But this actually has absolutely nothing
to do with Gaussian distribution.
So this is not that a problem with XI is Gaussian or whatever.
This is no such interpretation.
This is just a convenient function that
happens to be a bell-shaped function,
but don't endow this of any Gaussian semantics.
Okay?
So, in fact well, if you remember
the familiar bell-shaped Gaussian, again,
it's just the ways of associating
with these points is that if you imagine putting this
on a bell-shaped bump, centered around the position
of where you want to value your hypothesis H,
then there's a saying this point here I'll give a weight
that's proportional to the height of the Gaussian
excuse me, to the height of the bell-shaped function
evaluated at this point.
And the way to get to this point will be,
to this training example,
will be proportionate to that height and so on. Okay?
And so training examples that
are really far away get a very small weight.
One last small generalization to this is that
normally there's one other parameter to this algorithm,
which I'll denote as tow.
Again, this looks suspiciously
like the variants of a Gaussian,
but this is not a Gaussian.
This is a convenient form or function.
This parameter tow is called the bandwidth parameter
and informally it controls
how fast the weights fall of with distance. Okay?
So just copy my diagram from the other side, I guess.
So if tow is very small, if that's a query X,
then you end up choosing a fairly narrow Gaussian
excuse me, a fairly narrow bell shape,
so that the weights of the points
are far away fall off rapidly.
Whereas if tow is large
then you'd end up choosing a weighting function
that falls of relatively slowly
with distance from your query. Okay?
So I hope you can, therefore,
see that if you apply locally weighted linear regression
to a data set that looks like this,
then to ask what your hypothesis output
is at a point like this you end up
having a straight line making that prediction.
To ask what kind of class this output
at that value you put a straight line there
and you predict that value.
It turns out that every time
you try to vary your hypothesis,
every time you ask your learning algorithm
to make a prediction for how much
a new house costs or whatever,
you need to run a new fitting procedure
and then evaluate this line that you fit just
at the position of the value of X.
So the position of the query where
you're trying to make a prediction. Okay?
But if you do this for
every point along the X-axis
then you find that locally weighted regression
is able to trace on this, sort of,
very non-linear curve for a data set like this. Okay?
So in the problem set we're actually gonna
let you play around more with this algorithm.
So I won't say too much more about it here.
But to finally move on to the next topic
let me check the questions you have. Yeah?
Student:It seems like you still have
the same problem of overfitting and underfitting,
like when you had a Q's tow.
Like you make it too small in your
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, absolutely. Yes.
So locally weighted regression can run into
locally weighted regression is not a penancier
for the problem of overfitting or underfitting.
You can still run into the same problems
with locally weighted regression.
What you just said about
and so some of these things I'll leave you
to discover for yourself in the homework problem.
You'll actually see what you just mentioned. Yeah?
Student: [inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
Student:I'm just trying to think of  [inaudible]
the original data points.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Right.
So the question is, sort of, this
it's almost as if you're not building a model,
because you need the entire data set.
And the other way of saying that is that
this is a non-parametric learning algorithm.
So this –I don't know.
I won't debate whether, you know,
are we really building a model or not.
But this is a perfectly fine
so if I think when you write a code implementing
locally weighted linear regression on the data set
I think of that code as a whole
as building your model.
So it actually uses
we've actually used this quite successfully to model,
sort of, the dynamics of
this autonomous helicopter this is. Yeah?
Student:I ask if this algorithm that
learn the weights based on the data?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Learn what weights?
Oh, the weights WI.
Student:Instead of using [inaudible].
Instructor (Andrew Ng):I see, yes.
So it turns out there are a few things you can do.
One thing that is quite common is
how to choose this band with parameter tow, right?
As using the data. We'll actually talk about that
a bit later when we talk about model selection.
Yes? One last question.
Student:I used [inaudible] Gaussian sometimes
if you [inaudible] Gaussian and then
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, I guess. Lt's see. Boy.
The weights are not random variables and it's not,
for the purpose of this algorithm,
it is not useful to endow it with probable semantics.
So you could choose to define things as Gaussian,
but it, sort of, doesn't lead anywhere.
In fact, it turns out that I happened to choose this,
sort of, bell-shaped function to define my weights.
It's actually fine to choose a function that
doesn't even integrate to one,
that integrates to infinity, say,
as you're weighting function.
So in that sense, I mean,
you could force in the definition of a Gaussian,
but it's, sort of, not useful.
Especially since you use other functions that
integrate to infinity and don't integrate to one. Okay?
It's the last question and let's move on
Student:Assume that we have a very huge [inaudible],
for example. A very huge set of houses and
want to predict the linear for each house
and so should the end result for each input
I'm seeing this very constantly for
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, you're right.
So because locally weighted regression
is a non-parametric algorithm every time
you make a prediction you need to fit theta to
your entire training set again.
So you're actually right.
If you have a very large training set
then this is a somewhat expensive algorithm to use.
Because every time you want to
make a prediction you need to fit a straight line
to a huge data set again.
Turns out there are algorithms that
turns out there are ways to make this
much more efficient for large data sets as well.
So don't want to talk about that.
If you're interested, look up the work
of Andrew Moore on KD-trees.
He, sort of, figured out ways
to fit these models much more efficiently.
That's not something I want to go into today. Okay?
Let me move one.
Let's take more questions later.
So, okay. So that's locally weighted regression.
Remember the outline I had, I guess,
at the beginning of this lecture.
What I want to do now is talk about a
probabilistic interpretation of linear regression, all right?
And in particular of the
it'll be this probabilistic interpretation that
let's us move on to talk about logistic regression,
which will be our first classification algorithm.
So let's put aside locally weighted regression for now.
We'll just talk about
ordinary unweighted linear regression.
Let's ask the question of
why least squares, right?
Of all the things we could optimize
how do we come up with this criteria
for minimizing the square of the area between
the predictions of the hypotheses
and the values Y predicted.
So why not minimize the absolute value ofthe areas
or the areas to the power of four or something?
What I'm going to do now is present one set of assumptions
that will serve to "justify"
why we're minimizing the sum of square zero. Okay?
It turns out that there are many assumptions
that are sufficient to justify why we do least squares
and this is just one of them.
So just because I present one set of assumptions
under which least squares regression make sense,
but this is not the only set of assumptions.
So even if the assumptions I describe don't hold,
least squares actually still makes sense
in many circumstances.
But this sort of new help, you know,
give one rationalization, like,
one reason for doing least squares regression.
And, in particular, what I'm going to do
is endow the least squares model
with probabilistic semantics.
So let's assume in our example of
predicting housing prices,
that the price of the house it's sold four,
and there's going to be some linear function
of the features, plus some term epsilon I. Okay?
And epsilon I will be our error term.
You can think of the error term
as capturing unmodeled effects, like,
that maybe there's some other features of a house,
like, maybe how many fireplaces it has or whether
there's a garden or whatever,
that there are additional features that
we jut fail to capture
or you can think of epsilon as random noise.
Epsilon is our error term that captures
both these unmodeled effects.
Just things we forgot to model.
Maybe the function isn't quite linear or something.
As well as random noise, like maybe that day the seller
was in a really bad mood and so he sold it,
just refused to go for a reasonable price
or something.
And now I will assume that the errors have a probabilistic
have a probability distribution.
I'll assume that the errors epsilon I are distributed
just till they denote epsilon I is distributive
according to a probability distribution.
That's a Gaussian distribution with mean zero
and variance sigma squared. Okay?
So let me just scripts in here,
n stands for normal, right?
To denote a normal distribution,
also known as the Gaussian distribution,
with mean zero and covariance sigma squared.
Actually, just quickly raise your hand
if you've seen a Gaussian distribution before.
Okay, cool. Most of you. Great.
Almost everyone. So, in other words,
the density for Gaussian is what you've seen before.
The density for epsilon I would
be one over root 2 pi sigma, E to the negative,
epsilon I squared over 2 sigma squared, right?
And the density of our epsilon I will be
this bell-shaped curve with one standard
deviation being a, sort of, sigma. Okay?
This is form for that bell-shaped curve.
So, let's see. I can erase that.
Can I erase the board?
So this implies that the probability distribution
of a price of a house given in si
and the parameters theta, that
this is going to be Gaussian with that density. Okay?
In other words, saying goes as that the price
of a house given the features of the house
and my parameters theta,
this is going to be a random variable
that's distributed Gaussian with mean theta
transpose XI and variance sigma squared. Right?
Because we imagine that the way the housing prices
are generated is that the price of a house is equal to
theta transpose XI and then plus some random
Gaussian noise with variance sigma squared.
So the price of a house is going to have mean
theta transpose XI, again, and sigma squared, right?
Does this make sense?
Raise your hand if this makes sense. Yeah, okay.
Lots of you. In point of notation oh, yes?
Student:Assuming we don't know anything
about the error,
why do you assume here the error is a Gaussian?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Right. So, boy.
Why do I see the error as Gaussian?
Two reasons, right?
One is that it turns out to be mathematically
convenient to do so and the other is, I don't know,
I can also mumble about justifications,
such as things to the central limit theorem.
It turns out that if you, for the vast majority of problems,
if you apply a linear regression model like this
and try to measure the distribution of the errors,
not all the time, but very often you find that
the errors really
are Gaussian.
That this Gaussian model is a good assumption
for the error in regression problems like these.
Some of you may have heard of
the central limit theorem, which says that
the sum of many independent random variables
will tend towards a Gaussian.
So if the error is caused by many effects,
like the mood of the seller, the mood of the buyer,
some other features that we miss,
whether the place has a garden or not,
and if all of these effects are independent,
then by the central limit theorem you might
be inclined to believe that the sum of all these effects
will be approximately Gaussian.
If in practice, I guess, the two real answers are that,
1.) In practice this is actually a
reasonably accurate assumption, and
2.)Is it turns out
to be mathematically convenient to do so.
Okay? Yeah?
Student:It seems like we're saying if we assume that
area around model has zero mean,
then the area is centered around our model.
Which it seems almost like we're trying to
assume what we're trying to prove.
Instructor: That's the [inaudible] but, yes.
You are assuming that the error has zero mean.
Which is, yeah, right. I think later this quarter
we get to some of the other things,
but for now just think of this as a mathematically
it's actually not an unreasonable assumption.
I guess, in machine learning all the assumptions
we make are almost never true in the absence sense, right?
Because, for instance, housing prices are priced to
dollars and cents, so the error will be
errors in prices are not continued
as value random variables,
because houses can only be priced at a certain number
of dollars and a certain number of cents and you never
have fractions of cents in housing prices.
Whereas a Gaussian random variable would.
So in that sense, assumptions we make
are never "absolutely true,"
but for practical purposes this
is a accurate enough assumption that
it'll be useful to make. Okay?
I think in a week or two,
we'll actually come back to selected more about
the assumptions we make and when they help our
learning algorithms and when
they hurt our learning algorithms.
We'll say a bit more about it when
we talk about generative and discriminative
learning algorithms, like, in a week or two. Okay?
So let's point out one bit of notation,
which is that when I wrote this down I actually
wrote P of YI given XI and then semicolon theta
and I'm going to use this notation
when we are not thinking of theta as a random variable.
So in statistics, though,
sometimes it's called the frequentist's point of view,
where you think of there as being some, sort of,
true value of theta that's out there
that's generating the data say,
but we don't know what theta is,
but theta is not a random variable, right?
So it's not like there's some random
value of theta out there. It's that theta is
there's some true value of theta out there.
It's just that we don't know
what the true value of theta is.
So if theta is not a random variable, then
I'm going to avoid writing P of YI given XI comma theta,
because this would mean that probably of YI
conditioned on X and theta and you can
only condition on random variables.
So at this part of the class where
we're taking sort of frequentist's viewpoint
rather than the Bayesian viewpoint,
in this part of class we're thinking of theta
not as a random variable,
but just as something we're trying to estimate
and use the semicolon notation.
So the way to read this is this is the probability
of YI given XI and parameterized by theta. Okay?
So you read the semicolon as parameterized by.
And in the same way here,
I'll say YI given XI parameterized by theta
is distributed Gaussian with that. All right.
So we're gonna make one more assumption.
Let's assume that the error terms are IID, okay?
Which stands for Independently and Identically Distributed.
So it's going to assume that the error terms
are independent of each other, right?
The identically distributed part just means that
I'm assuming the outcome for the same Gaussian
distribution or the same variance,
but the more important part of is this is that
I'm assuming that the epsilon I's
are independent of each other.
Now, let's talk about how to fit a model.
The probability of Y given X parameterized by theta
I'm actually going to give this another name.
I'm going to write this down
and we'll call this the likelihood of theta
as the probability of Y given X parameterized by theta.
And so this is going to be the product
over my training set like that.
Which is, in turn, going to be a product
of those Gaussian densities that
I wrote down just now, right? Okay?
Then in parts of notation, I guess,
I define this term here to be the likelihood of theta.
And the likely of theta is just
the probability of the data Y, right?
Given X and prioritized by theta.
To test the likelihood and probability are often confused.
So the likelihood of theta is the same thing
as the probability of the data you saw.
So likely and probably are,
sort of, the same thing.
Except that when I use the term likelihood
I'm trying to emphasize that I'm taking this thing
and viewing it as a function of theta. Okay?
So likelihood
and for probability,
they're really the same thing except that
when I want to view this thing as a function of
theta holding X and Y fix are then called likelihood.
Okay? So hopefully you hear me say
the likelihood of the parameters
and the probability of the data, right?
Rather than the likelihood of the data
or probability of parameters.
So try to be consistent in that terminology.
So given that the probability
of the data is this
and this is also the likelihood of the parameters,
how do you estimate
the parameters theta?
So given a training set, what parameters theta
do you want to choose for your model?
Well, the principle of maximum likelihood
estimation says that, right?
You can choose the value of theta that
makes the data as probable as possible, right?
So choose theta to maximize the likelihood.
Or in other words choose the parameters that
make the data as probable as possible, right?
So this is massive likely your estimation
from six to six. So it's choose the parameters that
makes it as likely as probable as possible for me
to have seen the data I just did.
So for mathematical convenience,
let me define lower case l of theta.
This is called the log likelihood function
and it's just log of capital L of theta.
So this is log over product over I
to find sigma E to that.
I won't bother to write out
what's in the exponent for now.
It's just saying this from the previous board.
Log and a product is the same
as the sum of over logs, right?
So it's a sum of the logs of
which simplifies to m times one over root
two pi sigma plus and then log of
exponentiation cancel each other, right?
So if log of E of something
is just whatever's inside the exponent.
So, you know what, let me write this on the next board.
Okay. So maximizing the likelihood
or maximizing the log likelihood is the same as
minimizing that term over there.
Well, you get it, right? Because there's a minus sign.
So maximizing this because of the minus sign
is the same as minimizing this as a function of theta.
And this is, of course, just the same
quadratic cos function that we had last time,
J of theta, right?
So what we've just shown is that
the ordinary least squares algorithm,
that we worked on the previous lecture,
is just maximum likelihood assuming
this probabilistic model,
assuming IID Gaussian errors on our data. Okay?
One thing that we'll actually leave is that,
in the next lecture notice that the value of
sigma squared doesn't matter, right?
That somehow no matter
what the value of sigma squared is, I mean,
sigma squared has to be a positive number.
It's a variance of a Gaussian.
So that no matter what sigma squared
is since it's a positive number the value of theta
we end up with will be the same, right?
So because minimizing this you get the same value
of theta no matter what sigma squared is.
So it's as if in this model the value
of sigma squared doesn't really matter.
Just remember that for the next lecture.
We'll come back to this again.
Any questions about this?
Actually, let me clean up another couple of boards
and then I'll see what questions you have.
Okay. Any questions? Yeah?
Student:You are, I think here you try to
measure the likelihood of your nice of theta
by a fraction of error,
but I think it's that you measure because
it depends on the family of theta too, for example.
If you have a lot of parameters
[inaudible] or fitting in?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, yeah. I mean,
you're asking about overfitting,
whether this is a good model. I think let's
the thing's you're mentioning are maybe deeper
questions about learning algorithms that
we'll just come back to later,
so don't really want to get into that right now.
Any more questions? Okay.
So this endows linear regression
with a probabilistic interpretation.
I'm actually going to use this probabil use this,
sort of, probabilistic interpretation in order to
derive our next learning algorithm,
which will be our first classification algorithm. Okay?
So you'll recall that I said that regression problems
are where the variable Y that
you're trying to predict is continuous values.
Now I'm actually gonna talk about
our first classification problem, where the value
Y you're trying to predict will be discreet value.
You can take on only a small number of
discrete values and in this case
I'll talk about binary classification
where Y takes on only two values, right?
So you come up with classification problems
if you're trying to do, say,
a medical diagnosis and try to decide based on
some features that the patient has a disease
or does not have a disease.
Or if in the housing example,
maybe you're trying to decide will
this house sell in the next six months
or not and the answer is either yes or no.
It'll either be sold in the next six months
or it won't be. Other standing examples,
if you want to build a spam filter.
Is this e-mail spam or not?
It's yes or no.
Or if you, you know, some of my colleagues sit in
whether predicting whether
a computer system will crash.
So you have a learning algorithm
to predict will this computing cluster
crash over the next 24 hours?
And, again, it's a yes or no answer.
So there's X, there's Y. And in a classification problem
Y takes on two values, zero and one.
That's it in binding the classification.
So what can you do?
Well, one thing you could do is take linear regression,
as we've described it so far,
and apply it to this problem, right?
So you, you know,
given this data set
you can fit a straight line to it.
Maybe you get that straight line, right?
But this data set I've drawn, right?
This is an amazingly easy classification problem.
It's pretty obvious to all of us that, right?
The relationship between X and Y is
well, you just look at
a value around here and
it's the right is one, it's the left and Y is zero.
So you apply linear regressions to this data set
and you get a reasonable fit and you can
then maybe take your
linear regression hypothesis
to this straight line and threshold it at 0.5.
If you do that you'll certainly get the right answer.
You predict that if X is to the right of, sort of,
the mid-point here then Y is one
and then next to the left of that mid-point then Y is zero.
So some people actually do this.
Apply linear regression to classification problems
and sometimes it'll work okay,
but in general it's actually a pretty bad idea
to apply linear regression to classification problems
like these and here's why.
Let's say I change my training set by
giving you just one more training example
all the way up there, right?
Imagine if given this training set is actually still
entirely obvious what the relationship
between X and Y is, right?
It's just take this value as greater than
Y is one and it's less then Y is zero.
By giving you this additional training example
it really shouldn't change anything.
I mean, I didn't really convey much new information.
There's no surprise that
this corresponds to Y equals one.
But if you now fit
linear regression to this data
set you end up with a line that, I don't know,
maybe looks like that, right?
And now the predictions of your hypothesis
have changed completely
if your threshold
your hypothesis at Y equal both 0.5. Okay?
So Student:In between there might
be an interval where it's zero, right?
For that far off point?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, you mean, like that?
Student: Right.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, yeah, fine.
Yeah, sure. A theta set like that so.
So, I guess, these just yes, you're right,
but this is an example
and this example works.
This–
Student:[Inaudible]
that will change it even more if you gave it all –
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
Then I think this actually would make it even worse.
You would actually get a line that
pulls out even further, right? So this is my example.
I get to make it whatever I want, right?
But the point of this is that
there's not a deep meaning to this.
The point of this is just that
it could be a really bad idea to apply linear regression
to classification algorithm.
Sometimes it work fine,
but usually I wouldn't do it.
So a couple of problems with this. One is that, well –
so what do you want to do for classification?
If you know the value of Y lies between
zero and one then to kind of fix this problem
let's just start by changing the form of
our hypothesis so that my hypothesis always lies
in the unit interval between zero and one. Okay?
So if I know Y is either zero or one
then let's at least not
have my hypothesis predict
values much larger than one and much smaller than zero.
And so I'm going to instead of choosing
a linear function for my hypothesis I'm going to choose
something slightly different.
And, in particular, I'm going to choose this function,
H subscript theta of X is going to equal to G of theta
transpose X where G is going to be this function
and so this becomes more than one plus
theta X of theta transpose X.
And G of Z is called the sigmoid function
and it is often also called the logistic function.
It goes by either of these names.
And what G of Z looks like is the following.
So when you have your horizontal axis
I'm going to plot Z and so G of Z will look like this. Okay?
I didn't draw that very well. Okay.
So G of Z tends towards zero as Z becomes very small
and G of Z will ascend towards one as Z becomes
large and it crosses the vertical axis at 0.5.
So this is what sigmoid function,
also called the logistic function of. Yeah? Question?
Student:What sort of sigmoid in other step five?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Say that again.
Student:Why we cannot chose this
at five for some reason, like, that's better binary.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
Let me come back to that later. So it turns out that Y
where did I get this function from, right?
I just wrote down this function.
It actually turns out that there are two reasons
for using this function that we'll come to.
One is we talked about generalized linear models.
We'll see that this falls out naturally
as part of the broader class of models.
And another reason that we'll talk about next week,
it turns out there are a couple of, I think, very
beautiful reasons for why we choose logistic functions.
We'll see that in a little bit.
But for now let me just define it
and just take my word for it
for now that this is a reasonable choice. Okay?
But notice now that my
the values output by my hypothesis will always
be between zero and one.
Furthermore, just like we did
for linear regression,
I'm going to endow the outputs and my hypothesis
with a probabilistic interpretation, right?
So I'm going to assume that the probability that
Y is equal to one given X and parameterized by theta
that's equal to H subscript theta of X, all right?
So in other words I'm going to imagine that
my hypothesis is outputting all these numbers that
lie between zero and one.
I'm going to think of my hypothesis as trying to
estimate the probability that Y is equal to one. Okay?
And because Y has to be either zero or one
then the probability of Y equals zero is going to be that.
All right? So more simply it turns out actually,
take these two equations and write them more compactly.
Write P of Y given X parameterized by theta.
This is going to be H subscript theta of X to the power
of Y times one minus H of X
to the power of one minus Y. Okay?
So I know this looks somewhat bizarre,
but this actually makes the variation much nicer.
So Y is equal to one then this equation is H of X
to the power of one times
something to the power of zero.
So anything to the power of zero is just one, right?
So Y equals one then this is something to the power
of zero and so this is just one.
So if Y equals one this is just saying P of Y
equals one is equal to H subscript theta of X. Okay?
And in the same way, if Y is equal to zero then
this is P of Y equals zero equals this thing to the power
of zero and so this disappears.
This is just one times this thing power of one. Okay?
So this is a compact way of writing both of
these equations to gather them to one line.
So let's hope our parameter fitting, right?
And, again, you can ask
well, given this model by data,
how do I fit the parameters theta of my model?
So the likelihood of the parameters is, as before,
it's just the probability of data, right?
Which is product over I,
PFYI given XI parameterized by theta.
Which is just plugging those in. Okay?
I dropped this theta subscript just so
you can write a little bit less. Oh, excuse me.
These should be XI's and YI's. Okay?
So, as before, let's say we want to find a maximum
likelihood estimate of the parameters theta.
So we want to find the
setting the parameters theta that
maximizes the likelihood L of theta.
It turns out that very often
just when you work with the derivations,
it turns out that it is often much easier to
maximize the log of the likelihood rather than
maximize the likelihood.
So the log likelihood L of theta is just log of capital L.
This will, therefore, be sum of this. Okay?
And so to fit the parameters theta of our model
we'll find the value of theta that
maximizes this log likelihood. Yeah?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Say that again.
Student:YI is [inaudible].
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, yes. Thanks.
So having maximized this function
well, it turns out we can actually apply
the same gradient descent algorithm that we learned.
That was the first algorithm we used to
minimize the quadratic function.
And you remember,
when we talked about least squares,
the first algorithm we used to minimize
the quadratic error function was great in descent.
So can actually use exactly the same algorithm to
maximize the log likelihood.
And you remember, that algorithm was just
repeatedly take the value of theta and you replace it
with the previous value of theta plus a learning rate
alpha times the gradient of the cos function.
The log likelihood will respect the theta. Okay?
One small change is that
because previously we were trying to
minimize the quadratic error term.
Today we're trying to maximize rather than minimize.
So rather than having a minus sign we have a plus sign.
So this is just great in ascents,
but for the maximization rather than the minimization.
So we actually call this gradient ascent and
it's really the same algorithm.
So to figure out what this gradient
so in order to derive gradient descent,
what you need to do is compute the partial derivatives
of your objective function with respect to each of
your parameters theta I, right?
It turns out that
if you actually compute this partial derivative
so you take this formula, this L of theta, which is
oh, got that wrong too.
If you take this lower case l theta,
if you take the log likelihood of theta,
and if you take it's partial derivative
with respect to theta I you find that this is equal to
And, I don't know,
the derivation isn't terribly complicated,
but in the interest of saving you watching me
write down a couple of
blackboards full of math
I'll just write down the final answer.
But the way you get this is you just take those,
plug in the definition for F subscript theta
as function of XI, and take derivatives,
and work through the algebra it turns out
it'll simplify down to this formula. Okay?
And so what that gives you is that
gradient ascent is the following rule.
Theta J gets updated as theta J plus alpha gives this.
Okay? Does this
look familiar to anyone?
Did you remember seeing
this formula at the last lecture? Right.
So when I worked up Bastrian descent
for least squares regression I, actually,
wrote down exactly the same thing,
or maybe there's a minus sign and this is also fit.
But I, actually, had exactly the same learning rule
last time for least squares regression, right?
Is this the same learning algorithm then?
So what's different?
How come I was making
all that noise earlier about
least squares regression being a bad idea for
classification problems and then I did a bunch of math
and I skipped some steps, but I'm, sort of, claiming
at the end they're really
the same learning algorithm?
Student:[Inaudible] constants?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Say that again.
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, right. Okay, cool.
Student:It's the lowest it
Instructor (Andrew Ng):No, exactly. Right.
So zero to the same, this is not the same, right?
And the reason is, in logistic regression
this is different from before, right?
The definition of this H subscript theta of XI
is not the same as the definition
I was using in the previous lecture.
And in particular this is no longer
theta transpose XI. This is not a linear function anymore.
This is a logistic function
of theta transpose XI. Okay?
So even though this looks cosmetically similar,
even though this is similar on the surface,
to the Bastrian descent rule I derived last time
for least squares regression this is
actually a totally
different learning algorithm. Okay?
And it turns out that there's actually no coincidence
that you ended up with the same learning rule.
We'll actually talk a bit more about this later
when we talk about generalized learning models.
But this is one of the most elegant generalized
learning models that we'll see later.
That even though we're using a different model,
you actually ended up with what looks like the same
learning algorithm and it's actually no coincidence.
Cool.
One last comment as part of a sort of learning process,
over here I said I take the derivatives
and I ended up with this line.
I didn't want to make you sit
through a long algebraic derivation,
but later today or later this week, please,
do go home and look at our lecture notes,
where I wrote out the entirety
of this derivation in full,
and make sure you can follow every single step of
how we take partial derivatives of this log likelihood
to get this formula over here. Okay?
By the way, for those who are interested in
seriously masking machine learning material,
when you go home and look at the lecture notes
it will actually be very easy for most of you
to look through the lecture notes
and read through every line and go yep,
that makes sense, that makes sense,
that makes sense, and, sort of, say cool.
I see how you get this line.
You want to make sure you really understand the material.
My concrete suggestion to you would be to you to go home,
read through the lecture notes, check every line,
and then to cover up the derivation
and see if you can derive this example, right?
So in general, that's usually good advice for studying
technical material
like machine learning.
Which is if you work through a proof
and you think you understood every line,
the way to make sure you really understood it is
to cover it up and see
if you can rederive the entire thing itself.
This is actually a great way
because I did this a lot when I was trying to
study various pieces of
machine learning theory and various proofs.
And this is actually a great way to study
because cover up the derivations
and see if you can do it yourself without
looking at the original derivation. All right.
I probably won't get to Newton's Method today.
I just want to say take one quick digression
to talk about one more algorithm,
which was the discussion sort of alluding to this earlier,
which is the perceptron algorithm, right?
So I'm not gonna say a whole lot
about the perceptron algorithm,
but this is something that we'll come back to later.
Later this quarter we'll talk about learning theory.
So in logistic regression we said that G of Z are, sort of,
my hypothesis output values that
were low numbers between zero and one.
The question is what if you want to force G of Z
to up the value to either zero one?
So the perceptron algorithm defines G of Z to be this.
So the picture is or the cartoon is,
rather than this sigmoid function.
E of Z now looks like this step function that
you were asking about earlier.
In saying this before, we can use H subscript
theta of X equals G of theta transpose X. Okay?
So this is actually
everything is exactly the same as before,
except that G of Z is now the step function.
It turns out there's this learning
called the perceptron learning rule
that's actually even the same as
the classic gradient ascent for logistic regression.
And the learning rule is given by this. Okay?
So it looks just like the classic gradient ascent rule
for logistic regression.
So this is very different flavor of algorithm
than least squares regression and logistic regression,
and, in particular, because it outputs
only values are either zero or one it turns out
it's very difficult to endow this algorithm
with probabilistic semantics.
And this is, again, even though oh, excuse me.
Right there. Okay.
And even though this learning rule looks, again,
looks cosmetically very similar to what
we have in logistics regression
this is actually a very different type of learning rule
than the others that were seen in this class.
So because this is such a simple learning algorithm, right?
It just computes theta transpose X
and then you threshold
and then your output is zero or one. This is right.
So these are a simpler algorithm than
logistic regression, I think.
When we talk about learning theory later in this class,
the simplicity of this algorithm will let us come back
and use it as a building block. Okay?
But that's all I want to say
about this algorithm for now.