MachineLearning-Lecture18
Okay. Welcome back. What I want to do today
is talk about one of my favorite algorithms
for controlling MDPs that I think is one of
the more elegant and efficient
and powerful algorithms that I know of.
So what I'll do is I'll first start by
talking about a couple variations of MDPs that
are slightly different from the MDP
definition you've seen so far.
These are pretty common variations.
One is state action rewards, and the other is
horizon MDPs. Using this semi-modified
definition of an MDP, I'll talk about linear
dynamical systems. I'll spend a little bit of time
talking about models within dynamical
systems, and then talk about LQR, or linear
quadratic regulation control, which will lead us
to some kind of [inaudible] equation,
which is something we will solve in order to do
LQR controls.
So just to recap, and we've seen this definition
many times now. We've been defining an
MDP as [inaudible] states actions, states
transition probabilities, discount factor reward function
where the discount factor's a gamma
number between zero and one. And R, the
reward function, was the function mapping
from the states, the rewards was the
function mapping from the states, the real
numbers.
So we had value iteration, which would do this.
So after a while, the value of the iteration
will cause V to convert to V star. Then having
found the optimal value function, if you
compute the optimal policy by taking
essentially the orgmax of this equation above.
orgmax of A of that thing.
So in value iteration, as you iterate of this
you know, perform this update, the function
V will [inaudible] convert to V star.
So there won't be so without defining
the number of iterations, you get closer
and closer to V star. This actually converge
exponentially quickly to V star.
We will never exactly convert to V star
and define the number of iterations.
So what I want to do now is describe a couple
of common variations of MDPs that we
slightly different definitions of. First the reward
function and then second, we'll do
something slightly different from just counting.
Then remember in the last lecture, I said
that for infinite state of continuously in MDPs,
we couldn't apply the most straightforward
version of value iteration because if you have a
continuous state MDP, we need to use
some approximations of the optimal value function.
The [inaudible] later in this lecture, I'll talk
about a special case of MDPs, where you can
actually represent the value function exactly,
even if you have an infinite-state space or
even if you have a continuous-state space. I'll
actually do that, talk about these special
constants of infinite-state MDPs, using this new
variation of the reward function and the
alternative to just counting, so start to make the
formulation a little easier.
So the first variation I want to talk about is
State-action Rewards. So I'm going to change the
definition of the reward function. If this turns
out, it won't be a huge deal. In particular,
I change reward function to be a function
mapping from a state action pair to the real numbers.
What I mean by this is just the following.
You sell off in some state in zero. You take an
action A zero as a result of your state of action
choice. You transition to some new state,
S1. You take some action, A1. You transition to
some new state, S2. You take some
action, A2, and so on. so this is a,  it's a
state action sequence that you see.
So in an MPP where you have a state action
reward, your total payoff is now defined as
this, where your reward function is now a
function both of the current state and of the
action you took in the current state.
So this is my total payoff.
Then as usual, my goal will be to find a policy
to find the function mapping from the
state's actions, so that when I execute that
policy, I can maximize the expected value of
my total payoff. So this definition, it actually
turns out that given an MDP with state
action rewards, you can actually
so by filling in with the definitions
of the states, you can actually reduce
this back to an MDP
with only rewards that function in the states.
that may or may not be obvious.
Don't worry if it isn't. But using state action
rewards allows you to more directly model
problems in which different actions,
we have different costs.
So a running example is the robot.
so maybe for a robot, and it's more costly for
the robot to move than for it to stay still.
If you give an action to stay still, and the action
to stay still may have a lower cost because
you're not using a battery power as you would
recharge it for that action.
Another example would be actually, another
navigation example would be if you have
an outdoor vehicle. You need to drive over
some sort of outdoor terrain, like very rough
rocks or driving over grass. It may be costly,
more difficult, than driving over, say, a
paved road. So you may assign an action that
requires driving over grass or driving over
rocks to be more costly
than driving over paved road.
So this really isn't a huge change to the
definition of an MDP. I won't really bother to
justify this a lot, but [inaudible] equations is
generalizing the way that you probably
expect it. V star of S is now equal to that.
So previously, when the reward function was
just a function of the state, S, we could take
the max and push it in here. But now that the
rewards is a function of the action you're
taking as well, the max comes outside. So this
says that your expected total payoff,
starting from the state, as executing the auto policy, is
equal to first your immediate reward,
RFSA, for executing some action, A, in state S.
Then plus gamma times your future expected
total payoff. So this is your expected total
payoff if you take the action, A, from the
current state. So while these [inaudible] optimal
value functions. So your actually optimal
expected total payoff is the max of all actions
of this thing on the right.
Let's see. Value iteration,
which I'm abbreviating VI,
is really the same algorithm. B of S
is updated as max over A, RFSA, same thing.
just lay it on the right-hand side of
those equations be updating V of S using
[inaudible] equations. Again, you get value
iteration, exactly the same way.
Then finally, having found the optimal value
function, V star, using the value iteration
algorithm, you can then compute the optimal
policy, pi star of S as same as before. The
best action to take in the state, S, is the action,
A, that maximizes the thing on the right-
hand side. So having used value iteration to
compute the optimal value function, you can
then find pi star using that.
So this was the easier of the two variations of
MDPs so far. Any questions?
Actually, are there questions about this?
So the other variation, the other alternative
definition, will be finite horizon MDPs.
So finite horizon MDP comprises of the
[inaudible] SA state transition probabilities
with these, and the parameter T and the
reward function. Here, T is a parameter called
the horizon time. Concretely, what this
really means is that we'll be taking actions in
the MDP only for a total of capital T times
this. So we won't use this counting anymore.
[Audio cuts out]
In some state as zero, take action A0. Get to some
other state S1, take action A1 and so on.
Eventually, you get to some state, STAT
after T times [inaudible]. So my total payoff, now, will
be given by this sum from time zero up to time
T of my sum over rewards. Okay?
My goal, as usual so this is my total payoff.
My goal, as usual, is to maximize the expected
value of my total payoff. We want to
come up with a policy to maximize the
expected value of this total payoff. The key
difference is that the world only will exist
[inaudible], and after that, there's no more
rewards to be corrected.
So this turns out to be [inaudible] of a
difference because it turns out that the optimal
policy may be non-stationary. The term,
stationary, means that it doesn't depend on time.
Non-stationary means that it may depend on
time. So non-stationary roughly means that
my optimal action to take will be different for
different time steps. That's what non-
stationary means.
Just as an example of that, imagine that we
have some robot. Let's say the robot is here.
Let's say that there's a great sell over
there with a plus one reward. Much further
away, there's a plus ten reward. So depending
on how much time you have left on the
clock, it may be better to go after the plus one
or the plus ten reward.
If it's still early in the game, you still have a lot
of time, it may be better to head toward
the plus-ten rewards junction and get a much
larger reward. If you only have a couple of
time sets left, if the clock has nearly reached
the time, capital T, then you may not have
enough time to get to a plus ten reward. You've
be better off heading for the plus one
reward that's much more close by.
So what this example illustrates is that when
you're in that state, the best action to take
could be to go left or to go right, depending on
what time it is. So just as an example,
illustrating how the actually policy can be
non-stationary.
In fact, since we have non-stationary policies
do next, I'm going to allow non-stationary
transition probabilities as well. So I'll just
write that up there. What I mean is that so far,
assuming that the state ST plus one, is
joined from the state transition probabilities
index by the previous states and the
previous action.
I've been assuming that these state transition
probabilities are the same for all times.
So I want to say in some state and take some
action, the distribution of an innate state doesn't
matter. It doesn't depend on time. So I'm going
to allow a study more general definition
as well, in which we have non-stationary state
transition probabilities so that the chance
of where you end up [inaudible] may also
depend on what time it is.
So as examples of this non-stationary state
transition probabilities, one example would be
if you model flying an aircraft over a long
distance. Then as the aircraft flies, you burn
fuel and become lighter. So the dynamics of the
aircraft actually change over time. The
mass of the aircraft can change significantly
over time as you burn fuel. So depending on
what time it is, your mixed state could actually
depend on not only your current state and
your action, but also on how much fuel you
burn, therefore, what time it is.
Other examples, another aerospace one, is if
you have the weather forecast for the next
24 hours, say, you know what the winds and
precipitation are going to be like over the
next 24 hours. Then again, if you fly the aircraft
from, say, here to New York, it may cost
different amounts to fly different routes at
different times. Maybe flying over the
Rockies may cost different amounts, depending
on whether you do it now, when there's
really great weather, or if you do it a few hours
from now, when the weather may be
forecast really bad.
For an example you see everyday, same thing
for traffic, right?
There's at least depending on where you live,
certainly here in California,
there are times of day
where traffic is really bad in lots of places.
So the costs of driving certain roads
may vary, depending on
what time of day it is.
Lots of other examples. Industrial automation,
different machines in the factory may be
available to different degrees at different times
of day. They cost different amounts to hire
different workers, depending on whether you
pay overtime for pretty late in night or whatever. So the
cost of doing different things in the factory
can also be a function of time.
The state transition probabilities can also be a
function of time. Lastly, while we're doing
this as well, to make this fully general, we
might as well have non-stationary rewards
as well, where you might also index the reward
function of these times and prescripts,
where the cost of doing different things may
depend on the time as well.
Actually, there's more examples of
non-stationary MDPs, so let's
so now we have a non-stationary policy.
Let's talk about an algorithm
to actually try to find the optimal policy.
So let me define the following.
This is now a slightly modified definition
of the optimal value function.
I'll just write this down, I guess.
So I'm going to define the optimal value
function, and this going to be indexed by T,
with a subscript T. The optimal value of a state
for time, T, we're going to define as your
optimal sum of rewards for if you start the MDP
at that state, S, and if the clock starts off
at time, lowercase T.
So the optimal value of a state will depend on
what time it is and how much time you
have lest to run this MDP. Therefore, the sum
on the right sums only for time T, time T
plus one, time T plus two up to time, capital T.
I'll just state in English again, this is your
expected optimal total payoff if you start your
system in a state, S, and if the clock is
already at time, lowercase T.
So it turns out then there's a value iteration,
you can value that [inaudible]. Let me just write
out the value [inaudible] algorithm for this. It
turns out you can well, let me just write
this out. I'll write this below. It turns out you
can compute the optimal value function for
the MDP using the following recursion, which
is very similar to what we have for value
iteration. We're going to set V of S to be equal
to [inaudible] over A,
same as before, right?
Okay? So if I start the clock at time T and from
state S, my expected total payoff is equal
to the maximum [inaudible] actions I may take
of my immediate reward. Taking that
action, A, in that state, S. Them plus my
expected future payoff. So if I take action, A,
I would transition with [inaudible] P, subscript
SA, S prime to some new state, S prime.
If I get to the state, S prime,
my total expected payoff from
the state S prime would be these [inaudible]
now subscript T plus one, that's prime.
Subscript T plus one reflects that
after I've taken one action, my clock will have
advanced from time T to time T plus one.
So this is now V star subscript T plus one.
So this expresses V star of T in terms of V star
T plus one. Then lastly, to start off this
recursion, you would have V star, capital T is
equal to it's just equal to that. If you're
already at time, capital T, then you just get to
take one action, and then the clock runs out.
So this is V star capital T. Your value of starting
in some state, S, with no time with just
one time step, with no time left on the clock.
So in the case of finite horizon MDP,
this actually gives up a very nice dynamic
programming algorithm in which you can start
off by computing V star of T. Then you
use this backward [inaudible] to compute V star
of capital T minus one, capital T minus
two and so on. We compute V star of T and T
minus one and so on. It recurs backwards
onto your computer,
V star for all of your time steps.
Can you see this board? Cool.
Then the final step is previously,
we said that pi star of S
I'm going to come back and change this a bit
was the [inaudible] A of R plus A plus
[inaudible] PSA this is sort of what we had. In
the finite horizon case, the ultimate
action may depend on what time it is. So the
ultimate action to take it, time T, is
[inaudible] actions, A.
This is basically the augmat of exactly that
same thing on the right-hand side as we had in
our dynamic programming algorithm. So you
do this for every time step, and now you
compute it, your optimal policy for different
time steps. Again, this is a non-stationary
policy because pi star of S my depend on what
time it is.
So one minor difference the difference between this and
the early version of the earlier version of
value iteration is that so what you do is you
complete V star of T. Then using the
backwards recursion of that [inaudible]
algorithm, you computer V star T minus one.
Then V star T minus two and so on down to V
star of zero. Then from these, you
compute pi star.
So one there's not a huge difference, but one
minus difference [inaudible] the infinite
horizon discounted case is that by running this
recursion once, you now have exactly the
right value function. So this just computes the
value function, rather than merely
converging [inaudible]. This just gives you the
right value function with one pass.
Cool. Any questions there? Yeah. Interviewee:
[Inaudible].
This computation's much shorter than
valuations. So sort of yes and no. It depends on
how large capital T is.
Interviewee: [Inaudible] the normal MDP,
could [inaudible] and then use
this case for that case?
I see. So for the normal MDP,
can you assume capital T and then assume this?
So it actually turns out that that's a great
question. Let me just answer this
in a hand-wavy way. So it actually turns out
for a discounted infinite horizon MDP
where some discount factor gamma. So what
you can do is you can see, after T times X,
gamma to the T would be really small. It would
be like [inaudible] something. I don't
really care what happens after that many times
because the rewards are multiplied by
gamma to the T. After that, I don't really care.
So you can ask, can I take
my infinite horizon discounted MDP
and approximate that with a finite horizon MDP
where the number of times, steps T,
is chosen so that holds true.
So it turns out you can do that.
Then you end up with some value for T.
You can solve for T so that this holds true.
It turns out you can prove
that if you took the original value
iteration algorithm and if you run the
original value of the iteration algorithm
the version for discounted MDPs.
If you run that for this same number
of time steps, you will end up
with an approximation to
the value function that is about this close,
up to some small constant factors.
So to do that, you end up with roughly the same
amounts of computation anyway. Then
you actually end up with a non-stationary
policy, which is more expensive to keep
around. You need to keep around the different
policy every time step, which is not as nice
as if you had the stationary policy, same policy
for all times.
So there are other reasons, but sometimes you
might take an infinite horizon discounted
problem and approximate it to a finite horizon
problem. But this particular reason is not
the one. That makes sense. More questions?
Interviewee: [Inaudible]?
Is there a gamma in this?
So if you want, you can actually
change the definition of an MDP and use a
finite horizon discounted MDP. If you want,
you can do that. You can actually come in and
put a gamma there, and use this counting
the finite horizon. It turns out that usually, for
most problems that people deal with, you
either use discounting or
you use the finite horizon.
It's been less common to do both, but you can
certainly do as well. One of the nice things
about discounting, it makes such your value
function is finite. Algorithmically and
mathematically, one of the reasons to use
discounting is because you're multiplying your
rewards exponentially. It's a geometrically
[inaudible] series. It shows that the value
function is always finite. This is a really nice
mathematical properties when you do
discounting.
So when you have a finite horizon anyway, then
the value function's also guaranteed to
be finite. So with that, you don't have to use
discounting. But if you want, you can
actually discount as well.
Interviewee: [Inaudible].
Yeah, yes, you're right. If you want,
you can redefine the reward function
to go downward into the to the reward function,
since we have non-stationary rewards as well.
So that was finite horizon MDPs. What I want
to do now is actually use both of these
ideas, your state action rewards and your finite
horizon MDPs to describe a special case
of MDPs that makes very strong assumptions
about the problem. But these assumptions
are reasonable for many systems. With these
assumptions, what we come up with, I think,
are very nice and very elegant algorithms for
solving even very large MDPs.
So let's talk about linear quadratic regulation.
We just talked about dynamic
programming for finite horizon MDPs, so just
remember that algorithm. When I come
back to talk about an algorithm for solving
LQR problems, I'm actually going to use
exactly that dynamic programming algorithm
that you just saw for finite horizon MDPs.
I'll be using exactly that algorithm again.
So just remember that for now.
So let's talk about LQR. So I want to take these
ideas and apply them to MDPs with
continuous state spaces and maybe even
continuous action spaces. So to specify and
MDPs, I need to give you this fivetuple of state
actions, transition probabilities in the reward. I'm
going to use the finite horizon, capital T, rather
than discounting.
So in LQR problems, I'm going to assume the
following. I'm going to assume that the
state space is in dimensional is RN. And I'm
going to assume, also, a continuous set of
actions lie in RT. To specify the state transition
probabilities, PSA, I need to tell you
what the distribution of the mixed state is,
given the current state and the current action.
So we actually saw a little bit of this in the last
lecture. I want to assume the next state,
ST plus one, is going to be a linear function of
WT oh, excuse me. I meant to subscript that.
Where WT is Gaussian [inaudible] would mean
zero and some covariance given by sigma W.
Subscripts at A and B here with subscripts T to
show that these matrixes could change
over time. So this would be non-stationary
dynamics. As a point of notation, unfortunately
compiling ideas from multiple literatures,
so it's sort of unfortunately that capital A
denotes both a set of actions as well as a matrix.
When you see A later on, A will usually be used
to denote a matrix, rather than a set of
actions. So [inaudible] overload notation again,
but unfortunately the notational
conventions when you have research ideas in
multiple research communities, often they
share the same symbol. So just to be concrete,
AT is a matrix that's N by N. [Inaudible]
matrixes that are N by D. Just to be completely
clear, right, the matrixes A and B, I'm
going to assume, are fixed and known in
advance. So I'm going to give you the matrixes,
A and B, and I'm going to give you sigma W.
Your job is to find a good policy
for this MDP.
So in other words, this is my specification of
the state transition probabilities. Looking
ahead, we see this later, it turns out this noise
term is not very important. So it turns out
that the treatment of the noise term is not very
important. We'll see this later. We can
pretty much ignore the noise term, and we'll
still do fine. This is just a warning in the
sequel, what I do later, I might be slightly
sloppy in my treatment of the noise term.
In this very special case,
it would be unimportant.
The last thing I have to specify is some horizon
time, and then I also have some reward
function. For LQR control, I'm going to assume
that a reward function can be written as
this, where UT is a matrix that's N by N. VT is
a matrix that's D by D. I'll assume that UT
and VT are both positive semi-definite. Are
both PSD. So the fact that UT and VT are
both positive semi-definite matrixes, that
implies that ST transpose, UT, ST [inaudible]
zero. Similarly, ST transpose are VT, AT,
[inaudible] zero. So this implies that your
rewards are always negative. This is a
somewhat depressing MDP in which there are
only costs and no positive rewards,
right, because of the minus sign there.
So as a complete example for how you might
want to apply this, you've seen my helicopter
videos, right? So one thing is, for example,
suppose you have a helicopter, and
you want the state ST to be as close to zero as
possible. Then you might choose UT to be
equal to the identity matrix. This will make R
of STAT be equal to ST transpose ST. But
that's just I'll just write that down. [Inaudible]
oh, excuse me minus. The squared
negative of the squared [inaudible] vector.
So this would be penalizing the system
quadratically for having a state that's half of
zero, assuming that zero's the origin state. So if
it goes to make a helicopter hover around the
state zero, then you might choose this sort of
reward function.
It turns out it's also very common for action to
choose a cost for the action. So suppose I
choose VT to be equal to an identity matrix.
I get minus AT transpose AT here.
Then minus [inaudible] actions as well.
Including a quadratic cost for actions,
it's also a fairly common thing to do.
In practice, this tends to be effective of
discouraging your system from jerking
the controls around. This discourages
making very huge control commands.
Having a term like this reward function often
makes many systems behave better.
Of course, [inaudible] choose different values,
we have different values on the diagonal to
give different state variables, different weight
and so on. So lots of possible choices for U
and B. This is one example.
So for the next few steps, I'm going to write out
things, I'm going to derive things,
for the general case of non-stationary dynamics.
I'm going as I write out more math and more
equations for LQR, I'm going to try write it out
for the fairly general case of time varied
dynamics and time varied reward functions.
So I'm [inaudible] function. But for purposes
of understanding this material, you might want
to think of just ignoring many of the
subscripts, in terms of T.
So for the sake of [inaudible] material,
you might want to mentally assume
that there are some fixed matrix, A,
so that A is equal to A1, A2, equals A3
and so on. Similarly, there's some matrix B.
Okay? So write it out for the fully general,
non-stationary case, but you might just want to
ignore many of the time subscripts and imagine
the stationary case for now.
Quite a bit later, we're going to talk about an
extension of this called differential dynamic
programming that will actually use
a non-stationary [inaudible] to a very powerful
effect for a specific algorithm.
But for most of what we're about to do,
just pretend that MDP is stationary.
Okay. So before I talk about models,
let me jus say a couple of words about how you
would go about coming up with the linear
models. The key assumption in this model is
that the dynamics are linear. There's also the
assumption the reward function is quadratic,
but let's talk about the assumption that the
dynamics are linear.
ST plus one equals AST plus VAT.
Maybe time varying, maybe stationary. I'm just
writing stationary for now.
So how do you getmodels like this?
We actually saw one example of this already
in the previous lecture.
If you have an inverted pendulum system,
and you want to model the inverted pendulum
using a linear model like this, maybe
[inaudible]. I'm not going to write that down.
One thing you could do is run your inverted
pendulum, start it off in some state as zero,
take some action, A0, have it get to some state,
S1. Take action A1 and so on, get to some
state ST. Our index is one to denote that this is
my first trial.
Then you can repeat this a bunch of times.
You can repeat this N times. I'm just executing
actions on your physical robot. It could be a
robot, it could be a chemical plant. It could
be whatever. Trying out different actions in
your system and watch what states it gets to.
So for the linear model to your data, and choose
the parameters A and B, that minimize
the quadratic error term. So this says how well
does AST plus BAT predict ST plus one.
So you minimize the quadratic penalty term.
This would be one reasonable way to
estimate the parameters of a linear dynamical
system for a physical robot or a physical
chemical part of whatever they may have.
Another way to come up with a linear model
consistently, if I want to control, is to take a
nonlinear model and to linearize it. Let me
show you what I mean by that. So you can
linearize a nonlinear model. So let's say you
have some nonlinear model that expresses
ST plus one as some function of ST and AT. In
the example in the previous lecture, I said
for the inverted pendulum [inaudible]. By
referring to the laws of physics. It was actually
by downloading off the shelf software for doing
physics simulations. So if you haven't
seen this all before, you can go online. You
can easily find many open-source
packages for simulating the physics of simple
devices like these.
Download the software, type
in the specifications of your robot,
and it will simulate the physics that you use.
There's lots of open-source software patches
like that. You can just download them.
But something like that, you can now build
a physics simulator that predicts the state
as a function of the previous state
and the previous action.
So you actually come up with some function
that says that the state [inaudible] next time.
The [inaudible] vector will be some function of
the current state and the current action,
where the action in this case is just
a real number that says
how hard you accelerated to the left or right.
Then you can take this nonlinear model.
I actually wrote down a sample of
a model in the last lecture,
but in general, F would be some nonlinear
function. [Inaudible] of a linear function.
So what I mean by linearize is the following.
So here's just a cartoon.
I'll write down the math in a second.
Let's say the horizontal acces is the input state,
ST, and the output state, ST plus one, as I
said. Here's the function at F. So the next state,
ST plus one, will be some function of the
previous state, ST and the action AT. So to
linearize this model, what you would do is
you would choose a point. We'll call this bar T.
Then you would take the derivative of
this function. For the [inaudible] straight line to
that function.
So this allows you to express the next state,
ST plus one. You can approximate the next
state, ST plus one, as this linear function of the
previous state, ST. So to make this
cartoon really right, the horizontal access here
is really a state action pair. You're
linearizing around. So this is just a cartoon. The
horizontal access represents the input
state and the input action.
So just to write this out in math, I'll write out
the simple case first and the fully general
one in a second. Suppose the horizontal access
was only this state. So let's pretend
interactions they [inaudible] now. ST plus one
is just some function of ST, than that
linear function I drew would be ST plus one.
We're approximating as F prime evaluated
at some point as bar T times ST times S bar T.
Plus S bar T. So with this, you'd express
ST plus one as a linear function of ST. Just note
that S bar T is a constant.
It's not a variable.
Does that make sense? S bar T is a constant. F
prime of S bar T is gradient of the function
F at the point S bar T. This is really just the
equation of that linear function. So you can
then convert this to A and B matrixes.
Jumping back one board, I'm going to point out
one other thing. Let's say I look at this
straight line, and I ask how well does this
straight line approximate my function F, my
original simulator, my original function F. Then
you sort of notice that in this
neighborhood, in the neighborhood of S bar,
there's a pretty good approximation. It's
fairly close. But then as you move further away,
moving far off to the left here, it
becomes a pretty terrible approximation.
So when you linearize a nonlinear model to
apply LQR, one of the parameters you have
to choose would be the point around which to
linearize your nonlinear model. So if you
expect your inverted pendulum system to spend
most of its time in the vicinity of this
state, then it'd be reasonable to linearize around
this state because that means that the
linear approximation would be a good
approximation, usually, for the states that you
expect [inaudible] to spend most of this time.
If conversely, you expect the system to spend
most of its time at states far to the left, then
this would be a terrible location to linearize.
So one rule of thumb is to choose the
position to linearize according to where you
expect the system to spend most of its time
so that the linear approximation will tend to be
an accurate approximation in the vicinity
of the states [inaudible]. Just to be fair, it is
about choosing the point, S bar, A bar, that
we'll use to come up with a linear function that
we'll pretend it's a good approximation to
my original nonlinear function, F.
So for an example like the inverted pendulum
problem, this problem, if you expect to do
pretty well in this problem, then you would
expect the state to often be near the zero state.
If S equals zero corresponds to X being the
center of the railway track that the inverted
pendulum lives on. You expect to do fairly well.
You expect the pole to mostly be upright
[inaudible] upright at zero degrees or 90
degrees, I guess. So you choose whatever state
corresponds to having the pole upright.
The zero velocity [inaudible], near zero
velocity in the middle of the track.
So you usually choose that as a state
to linearize your inverted pendulum dynamics
around. That's a region where you might want
your approximation to be good.
So I wrote this down. To come back to this
formula, I wrote this down for the special
case of a one D state variable. If there are no
actions. The general formula for the
linearization approximation is ST plus one were
approximate as F of S bar T. A bar T plus
Okay? Where these upside down triangles are
an unusual symbol for taking the derivative
of F with respect to [inaudible] vector value,
second argument. So by choosing an
appropriate state as bar T, A bar T to linearize
around, you'd now express ST plus one as
a linear function of the current state and the
current action, AT. Again, these things, S bar
T, is a constant that you choose ahead of time.
Same for A bar T.
Lastly, having linearized this thing, you can
then convert it to matrixes like that.
So the ST plus one is now a linear function of
ST and AT. Questions about this?
So just one tiny detail, and it's really not
a huge deal, is that this thing below is
technically an [inaudible] function. There might
actually be an extra constant there, but
this is not a difficult generalization of a linear
dynamical system definition. One way to
deal with that constant is actually to do
something like take your
definition for this state,
let's say XX dot theta theta dot.
You can then augment your state vector
to have an extra interceptor,
one. With the interceptor one and working out
the A matrix, you can then take care of
the extra constant, C, as well.
So you can deal with this thing being
Technically it's an affine function because of
this extra offset, rather than a linear function.
But this is just a little bit of bookkeeping
[inaudible] for yourself
and shouldn't be a huge deal.
So to summarize,
you see I have this up,
you can learn a model,
you can take a nonlinear model.
Your nonlinear model can be a physics
model or a nonlinear model you learned
and linearize it. Now I'll post an LQR problem
in which we have specification of the
MDP in which the states are in RN, the actions
are in RD, and the state has zero
probabilities given by the [inaudible] linear
equation. SD plus one equals ATST plus
BTAT. Our rewards are going to be these
quadratic functions.
So the specification of the MDP means
that we know the A matrixes, the B matrixes,
the U matrixes and the V matrixes.
Our goal is to come up with
a policy to maximize our finite horizon
sum of rewards. So our goal is
to come up with a policy, first, to maximize
the expected value of this finite
horizon sum of rewards.
Okay. So our approach to solving this problem
will be exactly that finite horizon dynamic
programming algorithm that we worked out a
little earlier in this lecture. In particular, my
strategy for finding the optimal policy will be
to first find V star of T, the capital T, and
then I'll apply by a recursion to find V star of T
minus one, V star of T minus two and so on.
In the dynamic programming algorithm we
worked out, V star subscript T of the state ST,
this is the maximum [inaudible] actions you
might take at that time of R of STAT. Again,
just for the sake of understanding this material,
you can probably pretend the rewards and
the dynamics are actually stationary.
I'll write out all these superscripts all the time
[inaudible] if you're reading
this for the first time.
The reward is equal to max of AT of minus
right? I hope this isn't confusing.
The superscript Ts denote transposes.
The lowercase Ts denote the time index
capital T. So that's just a definition of
my next quadratic awards.
So this is clearly maximized as minus
ST transpose UTST because that last term is
this is greater than or equal to zero.
That gives me my assumption
that VT is [inaudible] semi-definite.
So the best action to take in
the last time step is just the action zero.
So pi star subscript T of ST is equal to the
[inaudible] of actions of that same thing.
It's just zero. It's by choosing the zero action,
AT transpose VTAT becomes zero, and that's
how this reward is maximized.
Any questions, or is something illegible?
Okay. So now let's do the dynamic
programming step where my goal is given VT
plus one, I want to compute VT.
Given V star T plus one,
I want to compute V star of T.
So this is the dynamic programming step.
So the DP steps I wrote down previously
was this. So for the finite state case,
I wrote down the following.
So this is exactly the equation I wrote down
previously, and this is what I wrote down for
finite states, where you have these discreet state
transition probabilities, and we can sum
over this discreet set of states. Now we're going
to continue as an infinite state again, so
this sum over state should actually become an
integral. I'm going to actually skip the
integral step. We'll just go ahead and write this
last term here as an expectation. So this is
going to be max over actions AT plus and
then this becomes and expectation over the
random mixed state, ST plus one, [inaudible]
from state transition probabilities given by
P of STAT of V star T plus one, ST plus one. So
this is the same equation written down
as an expectation.
So what I need to do is given a representation
of V star T plus one, I need to find V star
of T. So it turns out that LQR has the following
useful property. It turns out that each of
these value functions can be represented as a
quadratic function. So concretely, let's
suppose that V star T plus one suppose that
this can be expressed as a quadratic
function, written like so, where the matrix phi T
plus one is an N by N matrix, and psi T
plus one is just a real number.
So in other words, suppose V star T plus one is
just a quadratic function of the state ST
plus one. We can then show that when you do
one dynamic programming step when
you plug this definition of V star T plus one
into your dynamic programming step in the
equation I had just now, you can show that you
would get that V star T as well, will also
be a quadratic function of the same form.
[Inaudible] here, right? The sum-appropriate
matrix, phi T and sum appropriate real number,
psi of T.
So what you can do is stall off the recursion
with well, does that make sense? So what
you can do is stall off the recursion as follows.
So previously, we worked out that V star
capital T, we said that this is
minus ST transpose UTST.
So we have that phi of capital T
is equal to minus UT, and psi of capital T is
equal to zero. Now V star T of ST is equal to
ST transpose phi of T, ST plus psi of T.
So you can start out the recursion this way with
phi of T equals minus UT
and psi of T equals zero.
Then work out what the recursion is.
I won't actually do the full derivation.
This may be algebra, and you've actually
done this sort of Gaussian expectation math
a lot in your homework by now.
So I won't do the full derivation.
I'll just outline the one-ish G step.
So in dynamic programming step,
V star ST is equal to max over actions
AT of the median reward.
So this was R of SA from my equation in the
dynamic programming step. Then plus an
expected value over the random mixed state, ST
plus one, drawn from the Gaussian
distribution would mean ATST plus BTAT and
covariant sigma W. So what this is, this
is really my specification for P of STAT. This is
my state transition distribution in the
LQR setting. This is my state transition
distribution [inaudible] take action AT in the
state ST. Then my next state is distributed
Gaussian would mean ATST plus BTAT and
covariant sigma W. Then of the this state.
This, of course, is just V star T plus one of ST
plus one. I hope this makes sense. This is
just taking that equation I had previously in the
dynamic programming step. So the V star
of T, ST equals max over actions of the
immediate rewards plus an expected value over
the mixed state of V star of the mixed state with
the clock advanced by one. So I've just
plugged in all the definitions as a reward of the
state [inaudible] distribution and of the
value function.
Actually, could you raise your hand
if this makes sense? Cool.
So if you write this out and you expand
the expectation I know you've done
this many times, so I won't do it
this whole thing on the right-hand side
simplifies to a big quadratic
function of the action,
AT. So this whole thing simplifies to a big
quadratic function of the action AT. We want
to maximize this with respect to the actions AT.
So to maximize a big quadratic function,
you just take the derivatives of the functions
with respect to the action AT, set the
derivative equal to zero, and then you've
maximized the right-hand side, with respect to
the action, AT.
It turns out I'm just going to write this
expression down for completeness. You can
derive it yourself at any time. It turns out if you
actually maximize that thing on the right hand
side as a function of the actions, AT, you find
that [inaudible] AT is going to be that
times ST. Don't worry about this expression.
You can get it from [inaudible]
and derive it yourself.
But the key thing to note is that the optimal
action, AT, is going to be some big matrix.
We're going to call this thing LT times ST. In
other words, the optimal action to take in
this given state is going to be some linear
function of the state, ST. So having done
dynamic programming, you remember also
when we worked out the dynamic
programming algorithm for finite horizon
MDPs, we said that the way you compute the
optimal policy, pi star of T of ST. This is always
the [inaudible] of the same thing.
[Inaudible] of actions AT of the same thing.
STAT plus your expected value of
[inaudible] PSTAT, P-star, T plus one, ST plus
one. This thing on the right-hand side is
always the same thing as the thing we
maximized [inaudible].
So what this means is that
when I said this a value of A to the maximize of
this. So what this means is that the
optimal action to take from the state of ST is
actually equal to LT times ST.
What was shown is that when you're
in some state, ST,
the optimal action for that state is going to be
some matrix, LT, which can compute, times the
state, ST. In other words, the optimal action
is actually a linear function of the state.
I'm just going to point out, this is not a function
of approximation here, right. What we did not
do, we did not say, let's find the optimal linear
policy. We didn't say, let's look at the optimal
policy, and then we'll fit this straight line to
the optimal policy.
This is not about approximating
the optimal policy with a straight line.
This derivation is saying that the optimal policy
is a straight line. The optimal action is a
linear function of the current state. Moreover,
when you've worked out this is a value for
AT that maximizes this thing on the right-hand
side. So you take this and plug it back in
to do the dynamic programming recursion.
What you find is that so you take AT and
plug it back in to do the maximization. It will
actually get you this formula, so V star TST.
So you find that it will indeed be a quadratic
function like this of the following form
where and I just write out the equations for
the sake of completeness. Don't worry too
much about their forms.
You can derive this yourself.
So just to summarize, don't worry too much
about the forms of these equations.
What we've done is written down the recursion
to the expressor phi T and psi T as a function of
phi T plus one and psi T plus one.
So this allows you to compute
the optimal value function
for when the clock is at time lowercase T,
as a function of the optimal value function
for when the clock is at time T plus one.
So to summarize, GSELQG
here's a finite horizon of
actually, just to give this equation
a name as well. This recursion, in terms of
the phi Ts, this is called the discrete time
Bacardi equation. [Inaudible] recursion that
gives you phi T in terms of phi T plus one.
So to summarize, our algorithm for finding the
exact solution to finite horizon LQR
problems is as follows. We initialize phi T to be
equal to minus UT and psi T to be equal
to zero. Then recursively, calculate phi T and
psi T as a function of phi T plus one and psi
T plus one with the discrete time actually,
excuse me. So recursively calculate phi T
and psi T as a function of phi T plus one and psi
T plus one, as I showed, using the
discrete time Bacardi equation. So you do this
for T equals T minus one, T minus two
and so on, down to time zero.
Then you compute LT as a function of
actually, is it phi T or phi T plus one? Phi T plus
one, I think. As a function of phi T plus one and
psi T plus one. This is actually a function
of only phi T plus one. You don't really need psi
T plus one. Now you have your optimal policy.
So having computed the LTs, you now have the
optimal action to take in the state ST,
just given by this linear equation.
How much time do I have left? Okay. Let me
just say one last thing about this before I
close. Maybe I'll do it next week. I think I'll do
it next session instead. So it actually turns
out there's one cool property about this that's
kind of that is kind of subtle, but you'll find
it out in the next lecture. Are there question
about this before we close for today, then?
So the very cool thing about the solution of
discrete time LQR problems finite horizon
LQR problems is that this is a problem in an
infinite state, with a continuous state. But
nonetheless, under the assumptions we made,
you can prove that the value function is a
quadratic function of the state. Therefore, just
by computing these matrixes phi T and the
real numbers psi T, you can actually exactly
represent the value function, even for these
infinitely large state spaces, even for
continuous state spaces.
So the computation of these algorithms scales
only like the cube, scales only as a polynomial
in terms of the number of state variables
whereas in [inaudible] dimensionality
problems, with [inaudible], we had algorithms
of a scale exponentially dimensional problem.
Whereas LQR scales only are like the cube of
the dimension of the problem.
So this easily applies to problems
with even very large state spaces.
So we actually often apply variations of this
algorithm to some subset, to some particular
subset for the things we do on our helicopter,
which has high dimensional state spaces,
with twelve or higher dimensions. This has
worked very well for that. So it turns out
there are even more things you can do with this,
and I'll continue with that in the next