Let's see.
Okay. So welcome back,
and let's continue
our discussion of reinforcement learning algorithms.
On for today, the first thing I want to do
is actually talk a little bit
about debugging reinforcement learning algorithms
and then I'll continue the technical discussion
from last week on LQR, on linear-quadratic regulation.
In particular,
I want to tell you about an algorithm called
the French dynamic programming,
which I think is actually a very effective
absolute controls lack reinforcement learning algorithm
for many problems.
Then we'll talk about Kalman filters
and linear-quadratic Gaussian control, LGG.
Let's start with debugging RL algorithms.
And can I switch to the laptop display, please?
And so this was actually what I'm about to do here is
this is actually a specific example that I had done earlier
in this quarter, but that I promised to do again.
So remember, you know, what was it?
Roughly halfway through the quarter
I'd given a lecture on debugging learning algorithms, right?
This idea
that very often you run a learning algorithm and it,
you know, maybe does roughly what you want to
and maybe it doesn't do as well as you're hoping.
Then what do you do next?
And the talk of this idea that, you know,
some of the really, really good people in machine learning,
the people that really understand learning algorithms,
they're really good at getting these things to work.
Very often what they're really good at is at figuring out why
a learning algorithm is working or is not working
and that prevents them from doing things for six months
that someone else may be able to just look at and say gee,
there was no point collecting more training data,
because your learning algorithm had high bias
rather than high variance.
So that six months you spent collecting more training data
I could have told you six months ago
it was a waste of time. Right?
So these are sorts of things that
some of the people are really good at machine learning,
that they really get machine learning,
are very good at.
Well, just a few of my slides.
These slides I won't actually talk about these,
but these are exactly the same slides you saw last time.
Actually, I'll just skip ahead, I guess.
So last time you saw this discussion on right.
Diagnostics for whether you happen to have a bias
problem, or a variance problem,
or in other cases where the
your optimization algorithm is converging
or whether it's the [inaudible] optimization objective
and so on. And we'll talk about that again,
but the one example that I, sort of, promised to show again
was actually a reinforcement learning example,
but at that time we hadn't talked about reinforcement
learning yet,
so I promised to do exactly the same example again,
all right?
So let's go for the example.
The motivating example was robotic control.
Let's see. Write a let's say
you want to design a controller for this helicopter.
So this is a very typical way by which
you might apply machine-learning algorithm or several
machine-learning algorithms to a control problem, right?
Which is you might first build a simulator
so control problem is
you want to build a controller
to make the helicopter hover in place, right?
So the first thing you want to do is
build a simulator of the helicopter.
And this just means model of the state transition
probabilities, a piece of SA of the helicopter,
and you can do this by many different ways.
Maybe you can try reading a helicopter textbook
and building a simulator based on
what's known about aerodynamics of helicopters.
It actually turns out this is very hard to do.
Another thing you could do is collect data
and maybe fit a linear model,
or maybe fit a non-linear model,
to what the next stage is as a function of current state
and current action. Okay?
So there's different ways of
estimating the state transition probabilities.
So, now, you now have a simulator
and I'm showing a screen shot of our simulator
we have a stand fit on the upper right there.
Second thing you might do is
then choose a reward function.
So you might choose this sort of quadratic cos function,
right?
So the reward for being at a state X
is going to be minus the norm difference between a
current state and some desired state of your one simple
example of a reward function.
And this, sort of, quadratic reward function is what we've
been using in the last lecture in LQR control,
linear-quadratic regulation control.
And finally, right?
Random reinforcement learning algorithm in simulation,
meaning that you use your model of the dynamics
to try to maximize that final horizon sum of rewards
and when you do that you get a policy out,
which I'm gonna call the policy pi subscript RL to denote
the policy output by the reinforcement learning algorithm.
Okay?
Let's say you do this and the resulting controller gets much
worse performance than a human pilot that you hireto fly
the helicopter for you.
So how do you go about figuring out what to do next?
Well, actually, you have several things you might do,
right?
You might try to improve the simulator,
so there are exactly three steps.
You want say
maybe after the new model from the helicopter dynamics,
but I think it's non it is actually non-linear.
Or maybe you want to collect more training data,
so you can get a better estimates of
the transition probabilities of the helicopter.
Or maybe you want to fiddle with
the features you used to model the dynamics of your
helicopter,  right?
Other things you might do is,
you might modify the reward function R if you think,
you know, it's not just a quadratic function,
maybe it's something else.
I don't know.
Or maybe you're unsatisfied with the
reinforcement learning algorithm.
Maybe you think, you know,
the algorithm isn't quite doing the right thing.
Or maybe you think you need to
discritize the states more finely
in order to apply your reinforcement learning algorithm.
Or maybe you need to fiddle with
the features you used in value function approximations.
Okay?
So these are three examples of things you might do and,
again, quite often if you chose the wrong one to
work on you can easily spend, you know –
actually this one I don't want to say six months.
You can easily spend a year or two
working on the wrong thing.
Hey, Dan, this is a favor.
I'm, sort of, out of chalk could you wander around
and help me get? Thanks.
So the team does three things;
they'll copy the yellow box to the upper right of this slide.
What can you do?
So this is the, sort of,
reasoning we actually
go through on the helicopter project often
and to decide what to work on.
So let me just step for this example fairly slowly.
So this, sort of, reasoning you might go through.
Suppose these three assumptions hold true, right?
Suppose that the helicopter simulator is accurate,
so let's suppose that you built
an accurate model of the dynamics.
And suppose that, sort of,
I turned two under slides,
so suppose that the reinforcement learning algorithm
correctly controls the helicopter in simulation.
So it's a maximized that expected payoff, right?
And suppose that maximizing the expected payoff
corresponds to autonomous flight, right?
If all of these three assumptions holds true,
then that means that you would expect
the learned controller pi subscript RL
to fly well on the actual helicopter. Okay?
So this is the I'm, sort of, showing you the source of the
reasoning that I go through when I'm trying to come up
with a set of diagnostics for this problem.
So these are some of the
diagnostics we actually use routinely
on various revised control problems.
So pi subscript RL, right?
We said it doesn't fly well on the actual helicopter.
So the first diagnostic you want to run
is just check if it flies well in simulation,
all right?
So if it flies well in simulation,
but not in real life,
then the problem is in the simulator, right?
Because the simulator predicts that your controller,
the pi subscript RL, flies well,
but it doesn't actually fly well in real life.
So if this holds true,
then that suggests a problem is in the simulator.
Question?
Student:[Inaudible]
the helicopter pilots try to fly on the simulator?
Do you have the real helicopter pilots
try to fly on the simulator?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):
Do I try to have the real helicopter flying simulator?
Student:Real helicopter pilots.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, I see.
Do we ask the helicopter pilots to fly in simulation?
So, yeah.
It turns out one of the later diagnostics you could do that.
On our project we don't do that very often.
We informally ask the pilot,
who's one of the best pilots in the world,
Gary Zoco, to look at the simulator sometimes.
We don't very often ask him to fly in the simulator.
That answers your question.
But let me actually go on and show you some of the
other diagnostics that you might use then. Okay?
Second is let me use pi subscript human
to denote the human control policy, right?
This is pi subscript human is policy that, you know,
however the human flies it.
So one thing to do is look at the value of pi RLcompared to
the value of pi subscript human. Okay?
So what this means really is,
look at how the helicopter looks like
when it's flying under control of the pi subscript RL
and look at what the helicopter does when it's flying under
the human pilot control
and evaluate and then,
sort of, compute the sum of rewards, right?
For your human pilot performance
and compute
the sum of rewards for the learning controller performance
and see on, say,
the real helicopter or that question
or you can do this on the real helicopter
or on simulation actually,
but you can see does the human obtain
a higher or a lower sum of rewards on average
than does the controller you just learned. Okay?
And then the way you do this
you actually can go and fly the helicopter
and just measure the sum of rewards, right?
On the actual sequence of states the helicopter flew
through, right?
So if this condition holds true, right?
Where my mouse pointer is if oh, excuse me. Okay.
If this condition holds true where my mouse pointer is,
if it holds true
that pi subscript RL is less than pi subscript human,
those of you watching online
I don't know if you can see this,
but this V pi subscript RL of as zero
less than V pi subscript human of as zero.
But if this holds true,
then that suggests
that a problem is in the reinforcement learning algorithm
because the human has found a policy that obtainsa higher
reward than does the reinforcement learning algorithm.
So this proves, or this shows,
that your reinforcement learning algorithm
is not maximizing the sum of rewards, right?
And lastly, the last condition is this
the last test is this,
if the inequality holds in the opposite direction
so if the reinforcement learning algorithm
obtains a higher sum of rewards
on average than does the human,
but the reinforcement learning algorithm
still flies worse than the human does, right?
Then this suggests that
the problem is in the cos functions than
the reward function
because the reinforcement learning algorithm
is obtaining a higher sum of rewards than the human,
but it still flies worse than the human.
So that suggests that maximizing the sum of rewards
does not correspond to very good autonomous flight.
So if this holds true,
then the problem is in your reward function.
Or in other words,
the problem is in your optimization objective
and then rather than the algorithm
that's trying to maximize the optimization objective and,
so you might change your optimization objective.
In other words, you might change reward function. Okay?
So, of course, this is just one example of
how you might debug a reinforcement learning algorithm.
And these particular set of diagnostics
happen to apply only
because we're fortunate enough to be able to
an amazingly good human pilot
who can fly a helicopter for us, right?
If you didn't have a very good pilot
then maybe some of these diagnostics won't apply
and you'll have to come up with other ones.
But want to go through this
again as an example of the source of diagnostics you use to
debug a reinforcement learning algorithm.
And the point of this example
isn't so much that I want you to remember
the specifics of the diagnostics, right?
The point of this is really for your own problem,
be it supervised learning,
unsupervised learning, reinforcement learning,
whatever.
You very often have to come up with your own diagnostics,
your own debugging tools,
to figure out why an algorithm is working
and why an algorithm isn't working.
And this is
one example of what we actually do on the helicopter.
Okay?
Questions about this? Yeah, Justin?
Student:I'm just curious how do you collect,
like, training data?
Like in our homework
the pendulum fell over lots of times,
but how do you work that with an expensive helicopter?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
So, I see, right.
So on the helicopter
the way we collect data
to learn [inaudible] and improbabilities
is we usually not done lots of things,
but to first approximation,
the most basic merger is
if you ask a human pilot
tojust fly the helicopter around for you
and he's not gonna crash it.
So you can collect lots of data as
is being controlled by a human pilot.
And, as I say, it turns out
in data collection the, sort of,
a few standard ways to collect data
are to let you so a helicopter can do lots of things
and you don't want to collect data
representing only one small part of the flight regime.
So concretely what we often do is
ask the pilot to carry out frequency sweeps and
what that means, very informally,
is you imagine them holding a control stick, right?
In their hand.
Frequency sweeps are a process
where you start off making very slow
oscillations and then you start taking your control stick
and moving it back and forth faster and faster,
so you sort of sweep out the range of
frequencies ranging from very slow slightly [inaudible]
by oscillations until you go faster and faster
and you're sort of directing the control seat back and forth.
So this is oh, good. Thank you.
So that's, sort of,
one standard way that we use to collect data on
various robotics.
It may or may not apply to different robots
or to different systems you work on.
And, as I say,
in reality we do a lot of things.
Sometimes we have a controllers
collect data autonomously too,
but that's other more complex algorithms. Anything else?
Student:In the first point the goal communicates
that the other is perhaps not mapping
the actions similar to the simulator,
so in [inaudible] this could be very common
that you could have [inaudible]?
Just any specific matter that
pilots use to take care of that variable, so all [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, right.
So you're saying like point one may not
be simulated accurate;
it may be that the hardware is
doing something strange with the control.
There is concluding the controls through some action and
through some strange transformation
because it's actually simulating it as a helicopter.
I don't know. Yeah.
I've definitely seen that
happen on some other robots before.
So maybe diagnostic one here is a better form as deciding
whether the simulator matches the actual hardware,
I don't know. Yeah.
That's another class of those to watch out for.
If you suspect that's the case,
I can't think of a good, sort of, diagnostic right now
to confirm that,
but that, again, before
that would be a good thing
to try to come up with a diagnostic for to see
if there might be something wrong with the hardware.
And I think these are by no means
the definitive diagnostics or anything like that.
It's just sort of an example, but it would be great
if you come up with other diagnostics
to check that the hardware is working properly
that would be a great thing to do, too. Okay.
Is this okay,
last couple of questions before we move on?
Student:You said the reward function was?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, in this example,
what I was just using a quadratic constant.
On the helicopter
we often use things that are much more complicated.
Student:[Inaudible] You have no way of knowing
what is the, like, desired focus?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah. So you can, sort of,
figure out where ask the human pilot to hover in place
and guess what his desire was.
Again, these aren't constants telling you to, yeah.
Student:[Inaudible]
physics that are based learning problems.
Do you does it actually
work best to use a physical finian model?
You know, just, sort of,
physics tell or you just sort of do learning on [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
The physics models work well, right?
So the answer is it varies a lot from problem to problem.
It turns out that the aerodynamics of helicopters,
I think, aren't understood well enough
that you can look at the "specs" of a helicopter and
build a very good physics simulator.
So on the helicopter, we actually learn the dynamics.
And I don't know how to build a physics model.
For other problems, like if you actually have an inverted
pendulum problem or something,
there are many other problems for
which the aerodynamics are much better understood
and for which physic simulators work perfectly fine,
but it depends a lot
on some problems physic simulators work great
on some they probably aren't great on all. Okay? Cool.
So, I guess, retract the chalkboard, please. All right.
So how much time do I have? Twenty minutes. Okay.
So let's go back to our discussion on LQR Control,
linear-quadratic regulation control,
and then I want to take that a little bit further and tell you
about the, sort of, one variation on the LQR
called differential dynamic programming.
Just to recap,
just to remind you of what LQR,
or linear-quadratic regulation control, is,
in the last lectureI defined
a horizon problem where your goal is to maximize, right?
Just sort of find the horizon sum of rewards,
and there's no discounting anymore,
and then we came up with this
dynamic programming algorithm, right? Okay.
Then we came up with this
dynamic programming algorithm in the last lecture,
where you compute V star of
capital T that's one value function for the last time step.
So, in other words,
what's the value if your star in the state S
and you just get to take one action
and then the clock runs out.
The aerodynamic programming algorithm
that we repeatedly compute V
star lowercase t in terms of V
star t plus one, so we compute V star capital T
and then recurs backwards, right?
And so on, until we get down to V star zero
and then pi star was given by, as usual,
the augmax of the thing we had in the definition of the
value function.
So last time, the specific example
we saw of or one specific example,
that sort of define a horizon problem
that we solved by DP
was the LQR problem where we worked directly
with continuous state and actions.
And in the LQR problem
we had these linear dynamics
where the state ST plus one is a linear function
of the previous state and action
and then plus this Gaussian noise WT,
which is covariance sigma W.
And I said briefly last time,
that one specific way to come up with these
linear dynamics, right?
Oh, excuse me.
One specific way to take
a system and come up with a linear model for it is
if you have some simulator, say, right?
So in this cartoon,
the vertical axis represents ST plus one and
the horizontal axis represents STAT.
So say you have a simulator, right?
And let's say it determines [inaudible] simulator,
so we have a [inaudible] simulator
that tells you what the next state is ST plus one
is a function of previous state and action.
And then you can choose a point around which
to linearize this simulator,
by which I mean that you choose a point,
an approximate your
approximate the function F using a linear function,
this tangent, to the function F at that point.
So if you do that
you have ST plus one equals shoot.
Sorry about writing down so many lines,
but this will be
the linearization approximation to the function F
where I've taken a linearization around the specific point as
bar T, A bar T. Okay?
And so you can take those
and just narrow it down to a linear equation
like that where the next state ST plus one
is now some linear function of the previous state
ST and AT and these matrixes, AT and BT,
will depend ony your choice of
location around which to linearize this function. Okay?
I said last time, that this linearization approximation you,
sort of, expect to be particularly good
in the vicinity of, as bar T, A bar T
because this linear function
is a pretty good approximation to F, right?
So if in this little neighborhood there. And yes?
Student:[Inaudible] is there an assumption
that you are looking at something the second recently
indicates like the helicopter,
are you assuming pilot behavior is the same as
[inaudible] behavior or
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, right.
So let me not call this as an assumption.
Let me just say that when I use this algorithm,
when I choose to linearize this way,
then my approximation would be physically good
in the vicinity here and it may be less good elsewhere and,
so let me when I actually talk about DDP
I actually make use of this property.
Which is why I'm going over it now. Okay?
But, yeah. There is an intuition that
you want to linearize near the vicinity—
near of states,
so you expect your system to spend the most time.
Right.
So, okay. So this is how you might come up with a linear
model and if you do that then, oh, you can
let's see.
So for LQR
we also have this sort of quadratic reward function, right?
Where the matrixes UT and VT are positive semi-definite,
so the rewards are always negative, that's this minus sign.
And then if you take
exactly the dynamic programming algorithm,
that I've written down just now, then lets see.
It turns out that the value function at every state,
excuse me.
It turns out the value function for every time
step will be a quadratic function of the state
and can be written like that.
And so you initialize
the dynamic programming algorithm as follows.
And I just write this down, but
there's actually just one property I want to point out later,
but this equation is, well, somewhat big and hairy,
but don't worry about most of its details.
Let me just put this. Shoot,
there's one more equation I want to fit in. Well, okay.
All right. So it turns out the value function is
a quadratic function where V star T is this and,
so you initialize the dynamic programming step with this.
This fi and this si gives you V capital T
and then it records backwards.
So these two equations express
will give you V subscript T as a function of VT plus one.
Okay? So it incurs backwards for this learning algorithm.
And the last thing, get this on the same board,
so sorry about the disorganized use of the boards.
I just wanted this on the same place.
And, finally, the actual policy pi star of ST is given by
some linear function of ST,
so LT here is a matrix
where LT is equal to
numerous times. Okay?
And so when you do this
you now have the actual policy, right?
So just concretely,
you run the dynamic programming algorithm
to compute fi T and si T for all values of T
and then you plug it in to compute the matrixes LT
and now you know the optimal action stake and
[inaudible]. Okay?
So there's one very interesting property
these equations are a huge mess,
but you can re-derive them yourself,
but don't worry about the details.
But this is one specific property of this dynamic
programming algorithm
that's very interesting that I want to point out.
Which is the following.
Notice that to compute the optimal policy
I need to compute these matrixes LT
and notice that LT depends on A,
it depends on B, it depends on D, and it depends on fi,
but it doesn't depend on si, right?
Notice this further
that when I carry out my dynamic programming algorithm
my recursive definition for si well it depends on oh,
excuse me. It should be si T, right. Si T plus one. Okay.
In order to carry out my dynamic programming algorithm,
right?
For si T I need to know what si T plus one is.
So si T depends on these things,
but in order to carry out the dynamic programming for fi T,
fi T doesn't actually depend on si T plus one, right?
And so in other words in order to compute the fi T's
I don't need these si's.
So if all I want is the fi's
I can actually omit this step of the
dynamic programming algorithm
and not bother to carry out
the dynamic programming algorithm in terms of the fi's.
And then having done my dynamic programming algorithm
just for excuse me, I misspoke.
You I can forget about the si's
and just do the dynamic programming updates for the fi
matrixes and then having done my DP updates for the fi T
I can then plug this into this formula to compute LT.
Okay?
And so one other thing about it is you can,
to be slightly more efficient
efficiency isn't really the issue,
but if you want you can actually forget about the fi T's.
You actually don't need to compute that at all.
Now, the other interesting property of this is
that the matrix sigma W appears only
in my DV update for the si T's.
It doesn't actually appear in my updates for the fi T's.
So you remember well,
my model was that ST plus one equals ATST plus VT, AT
plus WT where these noise terms, WT,
had a covariance sigma W
and so the only place that appears
the covariance of the noise
terms of appears is in those IT's,
but I just said that
they can do this entire [inaudible]
ordering algorithm without the si T's.
So what this means is
that you can actually find the optimal policy
without knowing what the covariance of the noise terms
are. Okay?
So this is a very special property of LQR systems
and once you change anything,
once you go away from a linear dynamical system,
or once you change almost any aspect of
this because at discreet states or discreet actions
or whatever
and once you change almost any aspect of this problem
this property will no longer hold true
because this is a very special property of LQR systems that
the optimal policy does not actually depend on the
noise magnitude of these noise terms. Okay?
And the only important property is that the
noise function of zero mean.
So there's this intuition that to compute the optimal policy
you can just ignore the noise terms.
Or as if, so as long as you know
the expected value of your state ST plus one write down.
On average ST plus one is ATST plus BTAT,
then there's as if you can ignore the noise in your next
state ST plus one.
And the optimal policy doesn't change. Okay?
So we'll actually come back to this in a minute.
Later on we'll talk about Kalman filters.
We'll actually use this property of LQR systems.
Just to point out, note that the value function does depend
on the noise covariance, right?
The value function here does depend on si T.
So the larger the noise in your system
the worse your value function.
So this does depend on the noise,
but it's the optimal policy
that doesn't depend on the noise.
We'll use this property later. Okay.
So let's see how we're doing on time.
Let's see. Right. Okay.
So let's put this aside for now.
What I want to do now is tell you about one
specific way of applying LQR
that's called differential dynamic programming.
And as in most of the example,
think of try to control a system,
like a helicopter or a car or even a chemical plant,
with some continuous state.
So for the sake of thinking through this example,
just imagine trying to control a helicopter.
And let's say you have some simulator
that espece with the next state is a function of the previous
data in action, right?
And for this let's say
the model of your simulator is non-linear,
but and determinalistic. Okay?
So I say just now,
that the noise terms don't matter very much.
So let's just work with the term simulator for now,
but let's say F is non-linear.
And let's say there's some specific trajectory
that you want the helicopter to follow, all right?
So I want to talk about how to apply LQR
to get helicopter or a car or a chemical plant
where your state variables may depend on the amounts of
different chemicals and
the mixes of chemicals you have in different batch, really.
It's really easy to think about a helicopter.
Let's say
there's some trajectory you want the helicopter to follow.
So
here's what the differential dynamic programming it does.
First step is
come up with what I'm gonna call some nominal trajectory,
right?
And so we're gonna call this S zero A zero. Okay?
So one way to come up with this would be
if you had some very bad controller
someone hacked a controller for flying a helicopter
is not a good controller at all.
But you might then go ahead and fly the helicopter using a
very bad, a very sloppy, controller
and you get out some
sequence of states and actions, right?
So I'm gonna
and I just call this sequence of states and actions the
trajectory the nominal trajectory.
Then I will linearize F around this normal trajectory.
Okay? So i.e., right?
I'll use that same thing.
So for times si T our approximate ST plus one,
as this linearization thing that we just saw,
times plus the other term. Okay?
And then you distill this down to sum ATST plus BTST.
Okay?
So this will actually be the first time
that I'll make explicit use of the ability of LQR
or these finer horizon problems
to handle non-stationery dynamics.
In particular, for this example,
it will be important that AT and BT depend on time
–	oh,excuse me. Okay?
So the intuition is that
even if this is a pretty sloppy controller,
or even if you had a pretty bad controller
come up with your original normal trajectory,
you still expect maybe, right?
You'd expect your state and action at time T
to be maybe reasonably similar to
what even the sloppy controller had done, right?
So you want a fly trajectory
maybe you want to make a 90-degree turn.
Maybe if a bad controller
that does a pretty sloppy job,
but at any given in time
you're still moving around this trajectory.
So this is really telling you where along, say,
the 90-degree turn trajectory, just very roughly,
where along the trajectory
you expect to be at any given time
and so let's linearize around that point. Okay?
Then you would having found the linear model
you run LQR to get the
optimal policy for this specific linear model
and now you have a better policy.
And the final thing you do is boy,
I'll write this on a different board, I guess. Okay. Shoot.
The last step is you use a simulator, a model,
to come up with a new normal trajectory.
So i.e., okay?
So now you take the controller you just learned
and basically try flying your helicopter in your simulator.
So you initialize the simulator to the initial state,
and I'll call the S bar zero,
and you'll run every time step.
You choose an action which I'll call A bar T,
using the controller pi T that you just learned using LQR.
And then you simulate forward in time, right?
You use the simulator, the function F,
to tell you what the next state S bar T plus one will be
when your previous state and action is bar T A bar T.
And then you linearize around this new trajectory
and repeat. Okay?
So now you have a new normal trajectory
and you linearize your simulator around this new trajectory
and then you repeat the whole procedure.
I guess going back to step two of the algorithm.
And this turns out to be a surprisingly effective procedure.
So the cartoon of what this algorithm may do is as follows.
Let's say
you want to make a 90-degree turn on the helicopter
let's see one, you know,
a helicopter to follow a trajectory like that.
Follow up of a very bad controller,
I just, you know,
hack up some controller, whatever.
Have some way to come up with
an initial normal trajectory.
Maybe your initial controller overshoots the turn,
takes the turn wide, right?
But now you can use
these points to linearize the simulator.
So linearize in a very non-linear simulator
and the idea is that
maybe this state isn't such a bad approximation.
That maybe a linearization approximation
at this sequence of states will actually be reasonable
because your helicopter won't exactly be on the states,
but will be close to the sequence of states of every time
step. So after one duration of DDP,
that's the target trajectory, maybe you get a little bit closer
and now you have an even better place around
to linearize.
Then after another linearization of DDP
you get closer and closer to
finding exactly the trajectory you want. Okay?
So turns out DDP is a sort of
it turns out to be a form of a local search algorithm in
which you on each iteration
you find a slightly better place to linearize.
So you end up with a slightly better control and you repeat.
And we actually do this –
this is actually one of the things we do on the helicopter.
And this works very well on many this works
surprisingly well this works very well
on many problems. Cool.
think I was actually going to show some
helicopter videos,
but in the interest of time,
let me just defer that to the next lecture.
I'll show you a bunch of cool helicopter things
in the next lecture,
but let me just check if
there are questions about this before I move on. Yeah?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):In this sample?
Yes, yeah, right, yeah. So I'm going to
let's pick some kind of horizon T.
So I'm going to run through my entire trajectory in my
simulator, so I end up with a new nominal trajectory
to linearize around, right? Okay?
Yeah?
Student:So does this method give you,
like, a Gaussian for performing, like, a certain action?
Like you talked about, like,
the 90-degree turn thing or something.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Right.
Student:So is this from one, like,
is this from one, like, one 90-degree turn or can you
[inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah. So
it turns out what so this is used clear
let's see.
Go and think about this
as if there's a specific trajectory that you want to follow.
I'm just gonna,
car or helicopter or it could be in a chemical plant,
right?
If there's some specific sequence of states
you expect the system to go through over time,
so that you actually want to linearize at different times
excuse me. So, therefore, the different times you
want different linear approximations, your dynamics, right?
So I actually start to laugh over stationary simulator,
right? I mean, this function F,
it may be the same function F for all time steps,
but the point of DDP is
that I may want to use different linearizations for
different time steps.
So a lot of the inner loop of the algorithm
is just coming up with better and better
places around to linearize.
Where at different times
I'll linearize around different points. Does that make sense?
Cool. Okay, cool. So that was DDP.
And I'll show examples of DDP results in the next lecture.
So the last thing I wanted to do
was talk about Kalman filters and LQG control,
linear-quadratic Gaussian control.
And what I want to do is
actually talk about a different type of MDP problem
where we don't get to observe the state explicitly, right?
So far in every one I've been talking about,
I've been assuming that every time step
you know what the state of the system is,
so you can compute
a policy to some function of the state is in.
If you've all ready had that,
you know, the action we take is LT times ST,
right?
So to compute the action
you need to know what the state is.
What I want to do now is
talk about the different type of problem
where you don't get to observe the state explicitly.
The fact before we even talk about the control
let me just talk about the different problem where
just forget about control for now
and just look at some dynamical systems
where you may not get to observe the state explicitly
and then only later we'll tie this back to controlling some
systems. Okay? As a concrete example,
let's say as, sort of,
just an example to think about,
imagine using a radar to track the helicopter, right?
So we may model a helicopter,
and this will be an amazingly simplified model of a
helicopter, as, you know, some linear dynamical systems.
So [inaudible] ST plus one equals AST plus WT,
and we'll forget about controls for now, okay?
We'll fill the controls back in.
And just with this example,
I'm gonna use an extremely simplified state, right?
Where my state is just
a position in velocity in the X and Y directions,
so you may choose an A matrix like this as a okay?
As an extremely simple as a, sort of,
an extremely simplified model
of what the dynamics of, like, a plane or object
moving in 2-D may look like.
So just imagine that you have simulation
and you have a radar
and you're tracking blips on your radar
and you want to estimate the position,
or the state, of the helicopter as just as its XY position and
its XY velocity and you have a very simple dynamical model
of what the helicopter may do.
So this matrix, this just says
that XT plus one equals XT plus X star T plus noise,
so that's this first equation.
The second equation says that X star T plus one
equals 0.9 times X star T plus nine.
Yes, this is an amazingly simplified model
of what a flying vehicle may look like.
Here's the more interesting part,
which is that with
if you're tracking a helicopter with some sensor
you won't get to observe the full state explicitly.
But just for this cartoon example,
let's say that we get to observe YT,
which is CST plus VT where the VT is a random variables
Gaussian random variables with, say,
zero mean and a Gaussian noise with covariance
given by sigma V. Okay?
So in this example let's say that C is that and
so CST is equal to XY, right?
Take this state vector and multiply it by Z, you just get XY.
So let's see what the sensor,
maybe a radar, maybe a vision system,
I don't know, something that only gets to observe the
position of the helicopter that you're trying to track.
So here's the cartoon.
So a helicopter may fly through some sequence of states,
let's say it flies through some smooth trajectory,
whatever.
It makes a slow turn.
So the true state is four-dimensional,
but I'm just drawing two dimensions, right?
So maybe you have a camera sensor down here,
or a radar or whatever, and for this cartoon example,
let's say the noise in your observations is
largerin the vertical axis than the horizontal axis.
So what you get is actually
one sample from the sequence of five Gaussians.
So you may observe the helicopter there at times step one,
observe it there at time step two,
observe it there at time three, time four, time five.
Okay?
All right. So that's what your –
there's a sequence of positions
that your camera estimate gives you.
And given these sorts of observations,
can you estimate the actual state of the system? Okay?
So these orange things, I guess, right? Okay?
These orange things are your observations YT.
And test for the state of helicopter every time.
Just for it, so the position of the helicopter at every time.
Clearly you don't want to just rely on the orange crosses
because that's too noisy
and they also don't give you velocities, right?
So you only observe the subset of the state of variables.
So what can you do? So concretely well,
you don't actually ever get to observe the true positions,
right?
All you get to do is observe those orange crosses.
I guess I should erase the ellipses if I can. Right.
You get the idea. The question is given yeah.
You know what I'm trying to do.
Given just the orange crosses
can you get a good estimate of the state of the system
at every time step?
So it turns out that well,
so what you want to do is to estimate the distribution on
the state given all the previous observations, right?
So given observations, you know,
one, two, three, four, and five,
where is the helicopter currently?
So it turns out that the random variables,
S zero, S one, up to ST and Y1 are to ST,
have a joint Gaussian distribution, right?
So one thing you could do is
construct a joint Gaussian distribution
can define vector value random variable Z, S zero, S one,
up to ST, Y1 up to YT, right?
So it turns out that
Z will have some Gaussian distribution with some mean
and some covariance matrix.
Using the Gaussian marginalization
and conditioning formulas.
But I think way back
when we talked about factor analysis in this class,
we talked about how to compute marginal distributions
and conditional distributions of Gaussians.
But using those formulas
you can actually compute this thing.
can compute, right?
You can compute that conditional distribution.
This will give a good estimate of the current state ST. Okay
But clearly this is
a extremely computationally inefficient way to do so
because these means and covariance matrixes will
grow linearly with the number of time steps as you're t
racking a helicopter over tens of thousands of time steps.
They were huge covariance matrixes,
so this is a conceptually correct way,
but just a computational
not reasonable way to perform this computation.
So, instead,
there's an algorithm called the Kalman filter that
allows you to organize your computations
efficiently and do this.
Just on the side, if you remember
Dan's discussion section on HMM's the Kalman filter model
turns out to actually be a hidden Markov model.
These Kalman's are only for those of you
that attended Dan's discussion section.
If not then what I'm about to say may not make sense.
But if you remember
Dan's kind of section of the hidden Markov model,
it actually turns out that the Kalman filter model,
this linear dynamical system with observations
is actually an HMM problem where
let's see. Unfortunately, the notation's a bit different
because Dan was drawing from, sort of, a clash of
multiple research communities using these same ideas.
So the notation that Dan used, I think,
was developed in a different community that clashes a bit
with the reinforcement learning community notations.
So in Dan's notation in the HMM section,
Z and X were used to
denote the state and the observations.
Today, I'm using S and X
to denote the state and the observations. Okay?
But it turns out what I'm about to do
turns out to be a hidden Markov model with continuous
states rather than discrete states,
which is under the discretion section. Okay.
If you didn't attend that discussion section
then forget everything I just said in the last minute.
So here's the outline of the Kalman filter.
It turns out that, so it's a cursive algorithm.
So it turns out that if I have computed P of ST
given Y1 up to YT,
the Kalman filter organizes these computations into steps.
The first step is called the predict step.
Where given P of ST
where you all ready have P of ST given Y1 up to YT and
you compute what P of ST plus one given Y1 up to YT is.
And then the other step is called the update step.
Where given this second line you compute this third line.
Okay? Where having taken account only observations of
the time T you know incorporate the lots of the
observations up to time T plus one.
So concretely oh, and let's see.
In the predict step it turns out that
so what I'm going to do
is actually just outline the main steps of the Kalman filter.
I won't actually derive the algorithm
and prove it's correct.
It turns out that, I don't know,
working out the actual proof of what I'm about to derive is
probably significantly it's probably, I don't know,
about as hard,or maybe slightly easier,
than many of the homework's you've done already.
So and you've done some pretty amazingly hard
homework, so you can work out the proof for yourself.
It's just write out the main outlines
and the conclusion of the algorithm.
So for the acceptance of the vest T given Y1 after YT.
If that is given by that
then where okay?
So given ST,
having computed the distribution ST given Y1 through YT
and computed the distribution of ST plus one given Y1
through YT as Gaussian,
with this mean and this covariance,
where you compute
the mean and covariance using these two formulas.
And just as a point of notation, right?
I'm using ST and YT
to denote the true states in observations.
So the ST is the unknown true state. Okay?
ST is whatever state this one is in and you actually don't
know what ST is because you don't get to observe this.
And, in contrast,
I'm using these things like ST given T,
ST plus one given T, sigma T given T, and so on.
These things are the results of your computations, right?
So these things are actually things you compute.
So I hope the notations are okay,
but these ST is the unknown true state, right?
Whereas these things, ST equals one given T and so on,
these are things that you compute inside your algorithm.
Okay?
So that was the predict step.
And in the update step, you find that well, okay?
And so that's the updates of the Kalman filterwhere
you compute this in terms of your ST given Y1 through YT.
So after having performed the most recent Kalman filter
update you find that, right?
Your perceived distribution on the estimate of ST plus one,
given all your observations so far,
is that it's Gaussian with mean given by this and
variance given by that.
So, informally,
this thing ST plus one
given T plus one is our best estimate for ST plus one,
right? Given
all the observations we've had up to that time.
Okay?
And, again, the correctness of these equations the fact
that I'm actually computing this mean
and covariance of this conditional Gaussian distribution,
you can I'll leave you to sort of
prove that at home if you want. Okay?
I'm actually gonna put this together with LQR control
in a second, but, so before I do that let me check
if you've got questions about this?
Actually let me erase the board
while you take a look at that. Right. Okay.
Any questions for Kalman filters? Yeah?
Student:How is it computationally less intensive
than compute some drawing Gaussian distribution
and then find the conditional
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Very quickly. Yeah, of course.
So how is this less computationally intensive
than the original method I talked about, right?
So in the original method I talked about wow,
this is really back and forth.
I said, let's construct a Z,
which was this huge Gaussian thing, right?
And figure out what the mean and covariance matrix of Z
is. So sigma will be like R it'll be well,
it'll be roughly, right? A T by T matrix, right?
This is actually or the T by T is actually T times
number of state variables plus
number of observation variables by that.
This is a huge matrix
and as the number of times it increases
sigma will become bigger and bigger.
So the conditional and marginalization operations require
things like computing the inverse of T or subsets of T.
So the nave way of doing this
will cos on the order of TQ computation,
if you do things naively, right?
If because inverting
like a T by T matrix cos on the order of TQ, roughly.
In contrast, the Kalman filter algorithm,
like I said, over here.
I just have the update step. On the other board
I had the predict step.
But you can carry out
the computation on both of these lines
and it's actually constant time.
So on every time step you
perform these Kalman filter updates.
So if every time you get one more observation
you perform one more Kalman filter update
and the computation of that doesn't depend on it's
or the one time for every time step.
So the amount of stuff you need to keep around in memory
doesn't grow linearly with the number of time steps you
see. Okay?
Because actually what
I think I just realized why so, yes.
Actually this is the way we actually run Kalman filters,
which is initially I have just my first observation.
So I then compute P of X1 given Y1, right?
And now I know why I think
my helicopter is at time step one.
Having computed this
there may be some time passes,
like a second passes, and then I get another observation
and what I'll do is I
'll combine these two together to get P of X2
given Y1 and Y2, right?
And then may be another second passes in time
and I get another observation.
So my helicopters move a little bit more,
because another second's passed
and I get another observation.
What I do is I combine these two to compute P of SV
given Y1, Y2, Y3.
And it turns out that in order to compute this
I don't need to remember any of these earlier
observations. Okay?
So this is how you actually run it in real time say. Okay?
Cool. So oh, drat, running out of time.
The last thing I want to do is actually
put these things together.
So putting it together
putting Kalman filters together with LQR control you get an
algorithm called LQG control,
which stands for linear-quadratic Gaussian.
But in this type of control problem,
we have a linear dynamical system.
So I'm now adding actions back in, right?
So now B times AT. Okay?
And then, so LQG problem,
or linear-quadratic Gaussian problem,
I have a linear dynamical system that I want to control
and I don't get to observe the states directly.
I only get to observe these variables YT. Okay?
So I only get noisy observations of the actual state.
So it turns out that
you can solve an LGG control problem as follows.
At every time step,
we'll use a Kalman filter to estimate the state, right?
So concretely let's say you know the initial state.
Then you initialize this to be like that.
If you know that the initial state is some state as zero,
you initialize that as zero and that or, whatever, right?
And this is just well, okay?
If you don't know the initial state exactly,
then this is just a mean of your initial state estimate
and that would be your
covariance or your initial state estimate.
So just initialize your Kalman filter this way.
And then you use the Kalman filter on every step
to estimate what the state is.
So here's the predict step, right?
Previously we had ST plus one give T equals and so on.
So this is your predict step
and then you have an update step, same as before.
The one change I'm gonna make to the predict step
is now I'm going to take this into account as well.
This is just saying suppose my previous state was
ST given T,
what do I think my next state ST plus one given T
will be given no other
observations and the answer is, you know,
it's really just this equation, AST given T plus BAT.
And then, so this takes care of, sort of, the observations.
And then the other thing you do
is compute LT's using LQR, right?
Assuming then the other thing you do
is you just look at the linear dynamical systems,
and forget about the observations for now,
and compute the optimal policy oh, right.
Previously we had
that you would choose actions AT equals to LT times ST,
right?
So the optimal policy we said was these matrixes,
LT times ST.
So the other part of this problem
you would use LQR to compute these matrixes LT,
ignoring the fact that you don't actually observe the state.
And the very final step of LQR control is that –
well, when you're actually flying a helicopter,
when you're actually doing whatever you're doing,
you can't actually plug in the actual state
because in LGG problem
you don't get to observe the state exactly.
So what you do when you actually execute the policy is
you choose the action
according to your best estimate of the state. Okay?
So in other words,
you don't know what ST is,
but your best estimate of the state at any time
is this S of T given T.
So you just plug those in
and take LT times your best estimate of the state
and then you go ahead and
execute the action AT on your system, on your helicopter,
or whatever. Okay?
And it turns out that for this specific class of problems,
this is actually optimal procedure.
This will actually cause
you to act optimally in your LQG problem.
And there's this intuition that,
earlier I said, in LQR problems it's almost
as if the noise doesn't matter
and in a pure LQR problem the WT terms don't matter. It's
as if you can ignore the noise.
So it turns out that by elaborating that proof,
which I'm not gonna do you can
you're welcome to proof for yourself at home.
It's that intuition means that you can actually ignore
the noise in your observations as well.
The ST given T is some of your best estimate.
So it's as if your true state
ST is equal to ST given T plus noise.
So in LQG control,
what we're going to do is ignore the noise
and just plug in this ST given T
and this turns out the optimal thing to do.
I should say, this turns out to be a
very special case of a problem
where you can ignore the noise
and still act optimally and this property
this actually is something called the separation principle
where you can design an algorithm for estimate the states
and design an algorithm for controlling your system.
So just glom the two together
and that turns out to be optimal.
This is a very unusual property
and it pretty much was true only for LQG.
It doesn't hold true for many systems.
Once you change anything,
one's that's non-linear, you know, some other noise
model of one that's non-linear once this I don't know.
Once you change almost anything in this problem
this will no longer hold true.
The and just estimate the states
and plug that into a controller that was designed,
assuming you could observe the states fully.
But that once you change almost anything
this will no longer turn out to be optimal.
But for the LQG problem specifically,
it's kind of convenient that you can do this.
Just one quick question to actually close
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, yes. Yeah.
In every embassy wing
in everything I've described
I'm assuming that you're already learned A and B or s
omething, so to
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, right. Okay.
Sorry we're running a little bit late;
let's close for today and next time
I'll talk a bit more about
these partially observed problems.