So welcome back.
And what I wanna do today is
continue our discussion on support vector machines.
And in particular,
I wanna talk about the optimal margin classifier.
Then I wanna take a brief digression
and talk about primal and dual optimization
problems, and in particular,
what's called the KKT conditions.
And then we'll derive the dual to
the optimization problem that I had posed earlier.
And that will lead us into a discussion of kernels,
which I won't really
which we just get to say couple words about,
but which I'll do probably only in the next lecture.
And as part of today's lecture,
I'll spend some time talking about optimization problems.
And in the little time I have today,
I won't really be able to do this topic justice.
I wanna talk about convex optimization
and do that topic justice.
And so at this week's discussion session,
the TAs will have more time
will teach a discussion session
focus on convex optimization
sort of very beautiful and useful theory.
So you want to learn more about that,
listen to this Friday's discussion session.
Just to recap what we did in the previous lecture,
as we were beginning on developing
on support vector machines,
I said that a hypothesis represented as
H sub [inaudible] wb as g of w transpose
[inaudible] x + b, where g will be +1 or -1,
depending on whether z is greater than 0.
And I said that in our development
of support vector machines, we'll use
we'll change the convention of letting y be +1,
-1 to note the class labels. So last time,
we also talked about the functional margin,
which was this thing, gamma hat i.
And so we had the intuition that
the if functional margin is a large positive number,
then that means that we are classifying
a training example correctly and very confidently.
So yi is +1.
We would like w transpose xi + b to be very large.
And it makes i if, excuse me, if yi is -1,
then we'd w transpose xi + b to be
a large negative number.
So we'd sort of like functional margins to be large.
We also said functional margin
is a strange property
that you can increase functional margin just by,
say, taking your parameters, w and b,
and multiplying them by 2.
And then we also defined the geometric margin,
which was that we just essentially,
the functional margin divided by the normal w.
And so the geometric margin had
the interpretation as being
I'll give you a few examples.
The geometric margin, for example, is
has the interpretation as a distance between
a training example and a hyperplane.
And it'll actually be a signed distance,
so that this distance will be positive
if you're classifying the example correctly.
And if you misclassify the example,
this distance it'll be the minus of the distance,
reaching the point, reaching the training example.
And you're separating hyperplane.
Where you're separating hyperplane is defined
by the equation w transpose x + b = 0.
So oh, well, and I guess also defined
these things as the functional margin,
geometric margins,
respect to training set
I defined as the worst case
or the minimum functional
geometric margin.
So in our development of
the optimal margin classifier,
our learning algorithm would choose parameters w
and b so as to maximize the geometric margin.
So our goal is to find the separating hyperplane that
separates the positive and negative examples
with as large a distance as possible between
hyperplane and the positive and negative examples.
And if you go to choose parameters w and b
to maximize this, [inaudible] one copy
of the geometric margin is that
you can actually scale w and b arbitrarily.
So you look at this definition for the geometric margin.
I can choose to multiply my parameters w and b by 2
or by 10 or any other constant.
And it doesn't change my geometric margin.
And one way of interpreting that
is you're looking at just separating hyperplane.
You look at this line you're separating by
positive and negative training examples.
If I scale w and b,
that doesn't change the position of this plane,
though because the equation wh + b = 0
is the same as equation 2 w transpose x + 2b = 0.
So it use the same straight line.
And what that means is that
I can actually choose whatever scaling for w and b
is convenient for me.
And in particular, we use in a minute,
I can [inaudible] perfect constraint like that
the normal w [inaudible] 1 because this means that
you can find a solution to w and b.
And then by rescaling the parameters,
you can easily meet this condition,
this rescaled w [inaudible] 1.
And so I can add the condition like this
and then essentially not change the problem.
Or I can add other conditions.
I can actually add a condition that
excuse me, the absolute value of w1 = 1.
I can have only one
of these conditions right now [inaudible].
And adding condition to the absolute value
the first component of w must be to 1.
And again, you can find the absolute solution
and just rescale w and meet this condition.
And it can have other,
most esoteric conditions like that because again,
this is a condition that
you can solve for the optimal margin,
and then just by scaling, you have w up and down.
You can you can then ensure
you meet this condition as well.
So again, [inaudible]
one of these conditions right now,
not all of them.
And so our ability to choose any scaling condition
on w that's convenient to us will
be useful again in a second. All right.
So let's go ahead and break down the optimization problem.
And again, my goal is to choose parameters w and b
so as to maximize the geometric margin.
Here's my first attempt at
writing down the optimization problem.
Actually wrote this one down right
at the end of the previous lecture.
Begin to solve the parameters
gamma w and b such that
that [inaudible] i for in training examples.
Let's say I choose to add this normalization condition.
So the norm condition that w
the normal w is equal to 1 just makes
the geometric and the functional margin the same.
And so I'm saying I want to find a value
I want to find a value for gamma as big as possible
so that all of my training examples
have functional margin greater than or equals gamma,
and with the constraint that normal w equals 1,
functional margin and geometric margin
are the same. So it's the same.
Find the value for gamma so that all the values
all the geometric margins
are greater or equal to gamma.
So you solve this optimization problem,
then you have derived the optimal margin classifier
that there's not a very nice optimization problem
because this is a nasty, nonconvex constraints.
And [inaudible] is asking that you solve for
parameters w that lie on the surface
of a unisphere, lie on his [inaudible].
It lies on a unicircle a unisphere.
And so if we can come up with
a convex optimization problem,
then we'd be guaranteed that
our [inaudible] descend to other local
[inaudible] will not have local optimal.
And it turns out this is an example
of a nonconvex constraint.
This is a nasty constraint that
I would like to get rid of.
So let's change the optimization problem
one more time. Now, let me pose
a slightly different optimization problem.
Let me maximize the functional margin divided
by the normal w subject to yi w transpose xi.
So in other words, once you find a number,
gamma hat, so that every one of
my training examples has functional margin
greater than the gamma hat,
and my optimization objective is
I want to maximize gamma hat divided
by the normal w.
And so I wanna maximize the function margin
divided by the normal w.
And we saw previously the function margin
divided by the normal w is just a geometric margin,
and so this is a different way of
posing the same optimization problem.
[Inaudible] confused, though.
Are there questions about this?
Student:[Inaudible] the second statement has
to be made of the functional margin y divided by
why don't you just have it the geometric margin?
Why do you [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):[Inaudible] say it again?
Student:For the second statement,
where we're saying the data of
the functional margin is divided [inaudible].
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, I see, yes.
Student:[Inaudible] is that [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):So let's see,
this is the function margin, right?
This is not the geometric margin.
Student:Yeah.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):So oh,
I want to divide by the normal w
of my optimization objective.
Student:I'm just wondering how come
you end up dividing also under the second stage
[inaudible] the functional margin.
Why are you dividing there by the normal w?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
I'm not sure I get the question.
Let me try saying this again. So here's my goal.
My I want [inaudible]. So let's see,
the parameters of this optimization problem where
gamma hat w and b
so the convex optimization software
solves this problem
for some set of parameters gamma w and b.
And I'm imposing the constraint that whatever
values it comes up with,
yi x x5 + b must be greater than gamma hat.
And so this means that the functional margin
of every example had better be greater than
equal to gamma hat.
So there's a constraint to the function margin
and a constraint to the gamma hat.
But what I care about is not really
maximizing the functional margin.
What I really care about in other words,
in optimization objective,
is maximizing gamma hat divided by the normal w,
which is the geometric margin.
So in other words, my optimization [inaudible]
is I want to maximize the function margin
divided by the normal w. Subject to that,
every example must have function margin
and at least gamma hat.
Does that make sense now?
Student:[Inaudible] when you said that
to maximize gamma or gamma hat,
respect to gamma w and with respect to
gamma hat so that [inaudible] gamma hat
are no longer [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):So this is the
so it turns out so this is how I write down the
this is how I write down an optimization problem
in order to solve for the geometric margin.
What is it so it turns out that the question of this
is the gamma hat the function of w and b?
And it turns out that
in my previous mathematical definition, it was,
but the way I'm going to pose this
as an optimization problem
is I'm going to ask the convex optimization solvers
and this [inaudible] software
unless you have software for
solving convex optimization problems
hen I'm going to pretend that
these are independent variables
and ask my convex optimization software
to find me values for gamma, w, and b,
to make this value as big as possible
and subject to this constraint.
And it'll turn out that when it does that,
it will choose or obviously,
it will choose for gamma to be as big as possible
because optimization objective is this:
You're trying to maximize gamma hat.
So for x value of w and b, my software,
which choose to make gamma hat as big as possible
well, but how big can we make gamma hat?
Well, it's limited by use constraints.
It says that every training example
must have function margin greater than
equal to gamma hat. And so my
the bigger you can make gamma hat will
be the value of the smallest functional margin.
And so when you solve this optimization problem,
the value of gamma hat you get out will be,
indeed, the minimum of the functional margins
of your training set. Okay, so Justin?
Student:Yeah, I was just wondering,
I guess I'm a little confused because it's like, okay,
you have two class of data. And you can say,
"Okay, please draw me a line such that
you maximize the distance between
the smallest distance that [inaudible] between
the line and the data points."
And it seems like that's kind of what
we're doing, but it's
it seems like this is more complicated than that.
And I guess I'm wondering what is the difference.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):I see. So I mean, this is –
the question is [inaudible]. Two class of data
trying to find separate hyperplane.
And this seems more complicated than
trying to find a line [inaudible].
So I'm just repeating the questions in case
since I'm not sure how all the audio catches it.
So the answer is this is
actually exactly that problem.
This is exactly that problem of
given the two class of data,
positive and negative examples,
this is exactly the formalization of the problem
where I go is to find a line that separates the two
the positive and negative examples,
maximizing the worst-case distance between
the [inaudible] point and this line.
Okay? Yeah, [Inaudible]?
Student:So why do you care about
the worst-case distance [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, let me for now,
why do we care about the worst-case distance?
For now, let's just say
let's just care about the worst-case distance for now.
We'll come back, and we'll fix that later. We'll
that's a caring about the worst case is is just
is just a nice way to
formulate this optimization problem.
I'll come back, and I'll change that later.
Okay, raise your hand if this makes sense
if this formulation makes sense? Okay, yeah, cool.
Great. So let's see
so this is just a different way of
posing the same optimization problem.
And on the one hand, I've got to get rid of this nasty,
nonconvex constraint, while on the other hand,
I've now added a nasty, nonconvex objective.
In particular, this is not a convex function
in parameters w. And so you can't
you don't have the usual guarantees like
if you [inaudible] global minimum.
At least that does not follow immediately from this
because this is nonconvex.
So what I'm going to do is, earlier,
I said that can pose any of a number of
even fairly bizarre scaling constraints on w.
So you can choose any scaling constraint like this,
and things are still fine.
And so here's the scaling I'm going to choose to add.
Again, I'm gonna assume for the purposes
of today's lecture, I'm gonna assume that
these examples are linearly separable,
that you can actually separate
the positive and negative classes,
and that we'll come back and fix this later as well.
But here's the scaling constraint
I want to impose on w.
I want to impose a constraint that
the functional margin is equal to 1.
And another way of writing that is that
I want to impose a constraint that min over i, yi
that in the worst case, function y is over 1.
And clearly, this is a scaling constraint
because if you solve for w and b,
and you find that your worst-case function margin
is actually 10 or whatever,
then by dividing through w and b by a factor of 10,
I can get my functional margin to be over 1.
So this is a scaling constraint [inaudible] would imply.
And this is just more compactly written as follows.
This is imposing a constraint that
the functional margin be equal to 1.
And so if we just take what I wrote down as No.2
of our previous optimization problem
and add the scaling constraint,
we then get the following optimization problem:
min over wb.
I guess previously, we had a maximization
over gamma hats divided by the normal w.
So those maximize 1 over the normal w,
but so that's the same as
minimizing the normal w squared. It was great.
Maximum normal w is min w normal w squared.
And then these are our constraints.
Since I've added the constraint,
the functional margin is over 1.
And this is actually my final
well, final formulation
of the optimal margin classifier problem,
at least for now.
So the picture to keep in mind for this, I guess,
is that our optimization objective
is once you minimize the normal w.
And so our optimization objective is just the
[inaudible] quadratic function.
And [inaudible] those pictures [inaudible] can draw it.
So it if [inaudible] is w1 and w2,
and you want to minimize
the quadratic function like this
so quadratic function just has [inaudible]
that look like this.
And moreover, you have a number of
linear constraints in your parameters,
so you may have linear constraints that
eliminates that half space or linear constraint eliminates
that half space [inaudible].
So there's that half space and so on.
And so the picture is you have a quadratic function,
and you're ruling out various half spaces where
each of these linear constraints. And I hope
if you can picture this in 3D,
I guess [inaudible] kinda draw our own 3D,
hope you can convince yourself that
this is a convex problem that has no local optimum.
But they be run great [inaudible] within
this set of points that hasn't ruled out,
then you convert to the global optimum.
And so that's the convex optimization problem.
The does this [inaudible] nice and [inaudible].
Questions about this?
Actually, just raise your hand if this makes sense.
Okay, cool. So this gives you
the optimal margin classifier algorithm.
And it turns out that
this is the convex optimization problem,
so you can actually take this formulation of the problem
and throw it at off-the-shelf software
what's called a QP or quadratic program software.
This [inaudible] optimization is called
a quadratic program,
where the quadratic convex objective function
and [inaudible] constraints
so you can actually download software
to solve these optimization problems for you.
Usually, as you wanna use the
use [inaudible]
because you have constraints like these,
although you could actually modify
[inaudible] work with this, too.
So we could just declare success and say that
we're done with this formulation of the problem.
But what I'm going to do now
is take a digression to talk about primal
and duo optimization problems.
And in particular, I'm going to
later, I'm going to come back
and derive yet another very different form
of this optimization problem.
And the reason we'll do that is
because it turns out this optimization problem
has certain properties that
make it amenable to very efficient algorithms.
And moreover, I'll be deriving what's called
the duo formulation of this that allows us
to apply the optimal margin classifier
even in very high-dimensional feature spaces
even in sometimes infinite dimensional feature spaces.
So we can come back to that later. But let me know,
since I'm talking about convex optimization.
So how many here is
how many of you, from, I don't know, calculus,
remember the method of Lagrange multipliers
for solving an optimization problem like minimum
minimization, maximization problem subject
to some constraint?
How many of you remember the method
of Lagrange multipliers for that?
Oh, okay, cool. Some of you, yeah.
So if you don't remember, don't worry. I
I'll describe that briefly here as well,
but what I'm really gonna do is talk about
the generalization of this method
of Lagrange multipliers that you may
or may not have seen in some calculus classes.
But if you haven't seen it before,
don't worry about it.
So the method of Lagrange multipliers is was
well, suppose there's some function
you want to minimize, or minimize f of w.
We're subject to some set of constraints that
each i of w must equal 0 for i = 1 [inaudible] l.
And given this constraint,
I'll actually usually write it in vectorial form in which
I write h of w as this vector value function.
So that is equal to 0, where 0 is the arrow on top.
I used that to denote the vector of all 0s.
So you want to solve this optimization problem.
Some of you have seen method
of Lagrange multipliers where
you construct this [inaudible] Lagrangian,
which is the original optimization objective
plus some [inaudible] Lagrange multipliers
the highest constraints.
And these parameters they derive
we call the Lagrange multipliers.
And so the way you actually solve
the optimization problem is you take
the partial derivative of this with respect to
the original parameters and set that to 0.
So the partial derivative with respect to
your Lagrange multipliers [inaudible],
and set that to 0.
And then the same as theorem through [inaudible],
I guess [inaudible] Lagrange was that for w
for some value w star to get a solution,
it is necessary that –there exists beta star
Student:Right.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):The backwards e
there exists.
So there exists beta star such that
those partial derivatives are equal to 0.
So the method of Lagrange multipliers
is to solve this problem, you construct a Lagrangian,
take the derivative with respect to
the original parameters b, the original parameters w,
and with respect to the Lagrange multipliers beta.
Set the partial derivatives equal to 0,
and solve for our solutions.
And then you check each of the solutions to see
if it is indeed a minimum. Great. So great
so what I'm going to do
is actually write down the generalization of this.
And if you haven't seen that before,
don't worry about it. This is [inaudible].
So what I'm going to do is actually write down
the generalization of this
to solve a slightly more difficult type
of constraint optimization problem,
which is suppose you want to minimize f of w subject
to the constraint that gi of w, excuse me,
is less than equal to 0, and that hi of w is equal to 0.
And again, using my vector notation,
I'll write this as g of w is equal to 0.
And h of w is equal to 0.
So in [inaudible]'s case,
we now have inequality for constraint
as well as equality constraint.
I then have a Lagrangian, or it's actually still
called say generalized Lagrangian,
which is now a function
of my original optimization for parameters w,
as well as two sets of Lagrange multipliers,
alpha and beta. And so this will be f of w.
Now, here's a cool part.
I'm going to define theta subscript p of w
to be equal to max of alpha beta subject
to the constraints that the alphas are,
beta equal to 0 of the Lagrange.
And so I want you to consider
the optimization problem min over w
of max over alpha beta, such that
the alpha is a greater than 0 of the Lagrange.
And that's just equal to min over w, theta p of w.
And just to give us a name, the [inaudible]
the subscript p here is a sense of primal problem.
And that refers to this entire thing.
This optimization problem that written down
is called a primal problem.
This means there's the original optimization problem
in which [inaudible] solving.
And later on, I'll derive in another version of this,
but that's what p stands for. It's a
this is a primal problem.
Now, I want you to look at
consider theta over p again.
And in particular, I wanna consider the problem
of what happens if you minimize w
minimize as a function of w this quantity theta over p.
So let's look at what theta p of w is.
Notice that if gi of w is greater than 0,
so let's pick the value of w.
And let's ask what is the state of p of w?
So if w violates one of your primal problems constraints,
then state of p of w would be infinity. Why is that?
[Inaudible] p [inaudible] second.
Suppose I pick a value of w that
violates one of these constraints.
So gi of w is positive. Then well, theta p is this
maximize this function of alpha
and beta the Lagrange.
So one of these gi of w's is this positive, then
by setting the other responding alpha i to plus infinity,
I can make this arbitrarily large.
And so if w violates one of
my primal problem's constraints in one of the gis,
then max over alpha of this Lagrange
will be plus infinity.
There's some of and in the same way
I guess in a similar way,
if hi of w is not equal to 0,
then theta p of w also
be infinity for a very similar reason
because if hi of w is not equal to 0
for some value of i, then in my Lagrange,
I had a beta i x hi theorem.
And so by setting beta i to be plus infinity
or minus infinity depending on the sign of hi,
I can make this plus infinity as well.
And otherwise, theta p of w is just equal to f of w.
Turns out if I had a value of w that
satisfies all of the gi and the hi constraints,
then we maximize in terms of alpha and beta
all the Lagrange multiply theorems will actually
be obtained by setting all the Lagrange
multiply terms to be 0,
and so theta p just left with f of w.
Thus, theta p of w is equal to f of w
if constraints are satisfied [inaudible]
the gi in hi constraints,
and is equal to plus infinity otherwise.
So the problem I wrote down that
minimizes the function of w theta p of w –
this is [inaudible] problem.
That's just exactly the same problem
as my original primal problem
because if you choose a value of w that
violates the constraints, you get infinity.
And if you satisfy the constraints, you get f of w.
So this is really just the same as –
well, we'll say,
"Satisfy the constraints, and minimize f of w."
That's really what minimizing the state of p of w is.
Raise your hand if this makes sense. Yeah, okay, cool.
So all right. I hope no one's getting mad at me
because I'm doing so much work,
and when we come back,
it'll be exactly the same thing we started with.
So here's the cool part.
Let me know if you find it in dual problem.
To find theta d and d [inaudible] duo,
and this is how the function of alpha and beta is.
It's not the function of the Lagrange multipliers.
It's not of w. To find this,
we minimize over w of
my generalized Lagrange.
And my dual problem is this.
So in other words, this is max over that.
And so this is my dual optimization problem.
To maximize over alpha and beta,
theta d over alpha and beta.
So this optimization problem, I guess,
is my dual problem.
I want you to compare this to
our previous primal optimization problem.
The only difference is that I took the max and min,
and I switched the order around with the max and min.
That's the difference in the primal
and the dual optimization [inaudible].
And it turns out that it's a it's sort of
it's a fact it's true, generally, that d star
is less than [inaudible] p star. In other words,
I think I defined p star previously.
P star was a value of the prime optimization problem.
And in other words, that it's just generally true that
the max of the min of something is less than
equal to the min of the max of something.
And this is a general fact.
And just as a concrete example,
the max over y in the set 01 x oh, excuse me,
of the min of the set in 01 of indicator x = y
this is [inaudible] equal to min.
So this equality this inequality actually
holds true for any function you might find in here.
And this is one specific example where
the min over xy excuse me,
min over x of [inaudible] equals y
this is always equal to 0 because whatever y is,
you can choose x to be something different.
So this is always 0,
whereas if I exchange the order to min and max,
then thing here is always equal to 1.
So 0 [inaudible] to 1.
And more generally, this min/max
excuse me, this max/min,
thus with the min/max holds true
for any function you might put in there.
But it turns out that sometimes
under certain conditions,
these two optimization problems have the same value.
Sometimes under certain conditions, the primal
and the dual problems have the same value.
And so you might be able to solve the dual problem
rather than the primal problem.
And the reason to do that is that sometimes,
which we'll see in the optimal margin classifier problem,
the support vector machine problem,
the dual problem turns out to be much easier than it
often has many useful properties that
will make user compared to the primal.
So for the sake of
so what I'm going to do now
is write down formally the certain conditions under
which that's true
where the primal and the dual problems are equivalent.
And so our strategy for working out
the [inaudible] of support
vector machine algorithm will be that
we'll write down the primal optimization problem,
which we did previously, and maximizing classifier.
And then we'll derive
the dual optimization problem for that.
And then we'll solve the dual problem.
And by modifying that a little bit,
that's how we'll derive this support vector machine.
But let me ask you for now, let me just first,
for the sake of completeness,
I just write down the conditions under which
the primal and the duo optimization problems
give you the same solutions. So let f be convex.
If you're not sure what convex means,
for the purposes of this class,
you can take it to mean that the Hessian,
h is positive. [Inaudible], so it just means
it's a [inaudible] function like that.
And once you learn more about optimization
again, please come to this week's discussion session
taught by the TAs. Then suppose hi
the hi constraints is affine,
and what that means is that hi of w
equals alpha i transpose w plus vi.
This actually means the same thing as linear.
Without the term b here,
we say that hi is linear where
we have a constant interceptor as well.
This is technically called
affine other than linear.
And let's suppose that gi's are strictly feasible.
And what that means is that
there is just a value of the w such that from i,
gi of w is less than 0.
Don't worry too much [inaudible].
I'm writing these things down
for the sake of completeness,
but don't worry too much about
all the technical details. Strictly feasible,
which just means that there's a value of w such that
all of these constraints are satisfy were stricter than
the equality rather than
what less than equal to.
Under these conditions, there were exists w star,
alpha star, beta star such that
w star solves the primal problem.
And alpha star and beta star,
the Lagrange multipliers, solve the dual problem.
And the value of the primal problem
will be equal to the value of the dual problem
will be equal to the value
of your Lagrange multiplier excuse me,
will be equal to the value of your generalized Lagrange,
the value of that w star, alpha star, beta star.
In other words, you can solve either the primal
or the dual problem. You get the same solution.
Further, your parameters will
satisfy these conditions.
Partial derivative perspective parameters would be 0.
And actually, to keep this equation in mind,
we'll actually use this in a second when
we take the Lagrange, and we
and our support vector machine problem,
and take a derivative with respect to w to solve a
to solve our to derive our dual problem.
We'll actually perform this step ourselves in a second.
Partial derivative with respect to
the Lagrange multiplier beta is equal to 0.
Turns out this will hold true, too.
This is called the well
this is called the KKT complementary condition.
KKT stands for Karush-Kuhn-Tucker,
which were the authors of this theorem.
Well, and by tradition, usually this [inaudible]
KKT conditions. But the other two are
just so the [inaudible] is greater than 0,
which we had previously and that
your constraints are actually satisfied.
So let's see. [Inaudible] All right.
So let's take those and apply this to
our optimal margin optimization problem that
we had previously.
I was gonna say one word about this, which is
was gonna say one word about
this KTT complementary condition is that
a condition that is a
at your solution, you must have that
alpha star i times gi of w is equal to 0. So let's see.
So the product of two numbers is equal to 0.
That means that at least one of these things
must be equal to 0.
For the product of two things to be equal to 0, well,
that's just saying either alpha or i or gi is equal to 0.
So what that implies is that the
just Karush-Kuhn-Tucker most people just say KKT,
but we wanna show you the right
spelling of their names.
So KKT complementary condition implies that
if alpha i is not 0,
that necessarily implies that gi of w star
is equal to 0. And usually, it turns out
so all the KKT condition guarantees is that
at least one of them is 0.
It may actually be the case that
both alpha and gi are both equal to 0. But in practice,
when you solve this optimization problem,
you find that to a large part, alpha i star
is not equal to 0 if and only gi of w star 0, 0.
This is not strictly true because it's possible that
both of these may be 0. But in practice, when we
because when we solve problems like these,
you're, for the most part,
usually exactly one of these will be non-0.
And also, when this holds true,
when gi of w star is equal to 0, we say that gi
gi of w, I guess, is an active constraint
because we call a constraint
our constraint was a gi of w
must be less than or equal to 0.
And so it is equal to 0,
then we say that that's a constraint that
this is an active constraint.
Once we talk about [inaudible],
we come back and [inaudible]
and just extend this idea a little bit more.
[Inaudible] board.
[Inaudible] turn to this board in a second, but
so let's go back and work out one of the primal
and the dual optimization problems for
our optimal margin classifier for
the optimization problem that
we worked on just now.
As a point of notation,
in whatever I've been writing down so far
in deriving the KKT conditions,
when Lagrange multipliers were alpha i and beta i,
it turns out that when applied as [inaudible] dm,
turns out we only have
one set of Lagrange multipliers alpha i. And also,
as I was working out the KKT conditions,
I used w to denote the parameters of
my primal optimization problem.
[Inaudible] I wanted to minimize f of w.
In my very first optimization problem,
I had that optimization problem
[inaudible] finding the parameters w.
In my svn problem,
I'm actually gonna have two sets of parameters,
w and b. So this is just a
keep that sort of slight notation change in mind.
So problem we worked out previously
was we want to minimize the normal w squared
and just add a half there by convention
because it makes other work
math work a little nicer.
And subject to the constraint that
yi x w [inaudible] xi + v must be = greater than 1.
And so let me just take this constraint,
and I'll rewrite it as a constraint. It's gi of w, b.
Again, previously, I had gi of w,
but now I have parameters w and b.
So gi of w, b defined as 1.
So let's look at the implications of this in terms of
the KKT dual complementary condition again.
So we have that alpha i is basically equal to 0.
That necessarily implies that gi of w, b is equal to 0.
In other words, this is an active constraint.
And what does this mean? It means that
it actually turns out gi of wb equal to 0 that is
that means exactly that the training example xi,
yi has functional margin equal to 1.
Because this constraint was that
the functional margin of every example
has to be greater equal to 1.
And so if this is an active constraint, it just
inequality holds
that equality.
That means that my training example
i must have functional margin equal to exactly 1.
And so actually, yeah, right now,
I'll do this on a different board, I guess.
So in pictures, what that means is that,
you have some training sets,
and you'll have some separating hyperplane.
And so the examples with functional margin
equal to 1 will be exactly those which are
so they're closest to my separating hyperplane.
So that's my equation. [Inaudible] equal to 0.
And so in this in this cartoon example that
I've done, it'll be exactly
these three examples that
have functional margin equal to 1,
and all of the other examples as being further away
than these three will have functional margin that
is strictly greater than 1.
And the examples with functional margin equal to 1
will usually correspond to the ones
where the corresponding Lagrange multipliers
also not equal to 0.
And again, it may not hold true.
It may be the case that gi and alpha i equal to 0.
But usually, when gi's not is 0, alpha i will be non-0.
And so the examples of functional margin
equal to 1 will be the ones where
alpha i is not equal to 0.
One useful property of this is that
as suggested by this picture and
so true in general as well,
it turns out that we find a solution to this
to the optimization problem,
you find that relatively few training examples
have functional margin equal to 1.
In this picture I've drawn,
there are three examples
with functional margin equal to 1.
There are just few examples of this minimum
possible distance to your separating hyperplane.
And these are three
these examples of functional margin equal to 1
they are what we're going to call the support vectors.
And this needs the name support vector machine.
There'll be these three points
with functional margin 1 that
we're calling support vectors.
And the fact that they're relatively
few support vectors also means that usually,
most of the alpha i's are equal to 0.
So with alpha i equal to 0, for examples,
though, not support vectors.
Let's go ahead
and work out the actual optimization problem.
So we have a [inaudible] margin optimization problem.
So there we go and write down the margin,
and because we only have inequality constraints
where we really have gi star constraints,
no hi star constraint.
We have inequality constraints
and no equality constraints,
I'll only have Lagrange multipliers of type alpha
no betas in my generalized Lagrange.
But my Lagrange will be one-half w squared minus.
That's my Lagrange.
And so let's work out what the dual problem is.
And to do that,
I need to figure out what theta d of alpha
and I know again, beta's there
so what theta d of alpha is min
with respect to wb of lb alpha.
So the dual problem is the maximize theta d
as the function of alpha.
So as to work out what theta d is,
and then that'll give us our dual problem.
So then to work out what this is,
what do you need to do?
We need to take a look at Lagrange
and minimize it as a function of lv and b so
and what is this?
How do you minimize Lagrange?
So in order to minimize the Lagrange
as a function of w and b, we do the usual thing.
We take the derivatives of w
Lagrange with respect to w and b.
And we set that to 0.
That's how we minimize the Lagrange
with respect to w and b.
So take the derivative
with respect to w of the Lagrange. And I want –
I just write down the answer.
You know how to do calculus like this.
So I wanna minimize this function of w,
so I take the derivative
and set it to 0. And I get that.
And then so this implies that w must be that.
And so w, therefore,
is actually a linear combination
of your input feature vectors xi.
This is sum of your various weights given
by the alpha i's and times the xi's,
which are your examples in your training set.
And this will be useful later.
The other equation we have is
here, partial derivative of Lagrange
with respect to p is equal to
minus sum of i plus 1 to m [inaudible] for i.
And so I'll just set that to equal to 0.
And so these are my two constraints.
And so [inaudible].
So what I'm going to do is
I'm actually going to take these two constraints,
and well, I'm going to take
whatever I thought to be the value for w.
And I'm gonna take what
I've worked out to be the value for w,
and I'll plug it back in there to figure out
what the Lagrange really
is when I minimize with respect to w.
[Inaudible] and I'll deal with b in a second.
So let's see. So my Lagrange
is 1/2 w transpose w minus.
So this first term, w transpose w
this becomes sum y equals one to m,
alpha i, yi, xi transpose.
This is just putting in the value for w that
I worked out previously.
But since this is w transpose w
and so when they expand out of this quadratic function,
and when I plug in w over there as well,
I find that I have that. Oh, where I'm using these
angle brackets to denote inner product,
so this thing here, it just means the inner product,
xi transpose xj.
And the first and second terms
are actually the same except for the minus one half.
So to simplify to be equal to that.
So let me go ahead and call this w of alpha.
My dual problem is, therefore, the following.
I want to maximize w of alpha,
which is that [inaudible].
And I want to the
I realize the notation is somewhat unfortunate.
I'm using capital W of alpha to denote that
formula I wrote down earlier.
And then we also had our lowercase w.
The original [inaudible] is the primal problem.
Lowercase w transpose xi.
So uppercase and lowercase w
are totally different things, so unfortunately,
the notation is standard as well,
as far as I know, so.
So the dual problem is that
subject to the alpha [inaudible] related to 0,
and we also have that the sum of i,
yi, alpha i is related to 0.
That last constraint was the constraint
I got from this the sum of i
sum of i, yi alpha i equals to 0.
But that's where that [inaudible] came from.
Let me just I think in previous years that
I taught this, where
this constraint comes from is just
is slightly confusing.
So let me just take two minutes to say
what the real interpretation of that is.
And if you don't understand it,
it's not a big deal, I guess.
So when we took the partial derivative
of the Lagrange with respect to b,
we end up with this constraint that sum of i,
yi, alpha i must be equal to 0.
The interpretation of that, it turns out,
is that if sum of i, yi, alpha i is not equal to 0,
then theta d of wb is actually, excuse me.
Then theta d of alpha is equal to
minus infinity for minimizing.
So in other words, it turns out my Lagrange
is actually a linear function of my parameters b.
And so the interpretation of that
constraint we worked out previously was that
if sum of i or yi, alpha i is not equal to 0,
then theta d of alpha is equal to minus infinity.
And so if your goal is to maximize
as a function of alpha, theta d of alpha,
then you've gotta choose values of alpha
for which sum of yi alpha is equal to 0.
And then when sum of yi alpha is equal to 0,
then theta d of alpha is equal to w of alpha.
And so that's why we ended up
deciding to maximize w of alpha subject to that
sum of yi alpha is equal to 0.
Yeah, the unfortunately,
the fact of that d would be [inaudible] adds just
a little bit of extra notation
in our derivation of the dual. But by the way,
and [inaudible] all the action
of the optimization problem is with w
because b is just one parameter. So let's check.
Are there any questions about this? Okay, cool.
So what derived a dual optimization problem
and really, don't worry about this
if you're not quite sure where this was.
Just think of this as we worked out this constraint,
and we worked out,
and we took partial derivative with respect to b,
that this constraint has the [inaudible] and so
I just copied that over here. But so
worked out the dual of the optimization problem,
so our approach to finding
to deriving the optimal margin classifier
or support vector machine will be that
we'll solve along this dual optimization problem
for the parameters alpha star.
And then if you want, you can then
this is the equation that we worked out
on the previous board.
We said that w this [inaudible] alpha
w must be equal to that.
And so once you solve for alpha,
you can then go back and quickly derive w
in parameters to your primal problem.
And we worked this out earlier.
And moreover, once you solve alpha and w,
you can then focus back into your
once you solve for alpha and w,
it's really easy to solve for b,
so that b gives us the interpretation of
[inaudible] training set,
and you found the direction for w.
So you know where
your separating hyperplane's direction is.
You know it's got to be one of these things.
And you know the orientation
and separating hyperplane.
You just have to decide
where to place this hyperplane.
And that's what solving b is.
So once you solve for alpha and w,
it's really easy to solve b.
You can plug alpha and w back into
the primal optimization problem and solve for b.
And I just wrote it down
for the sake of completeness, but
and the intuition behind this formula is just that
find the worst positive [inaudible]
and the worst negative example.
Let's say this one and this one say [inaudible]
and [inaudible] the difference between them.
And that tells you where
you should set the threshold for where
to place the separating hyperplane.
And then that's the this is the optimal margin classifier.
This is also called a support vector machine.
If you do not use one y [inaudible],
it's called kernels.
And I'll say a few words about that.
But I hope the process is clear.
It's a dual problem.
We're going to solve the dual problem
for the alpha i's.
That gives us w, and that gives us b.
So there's just one more thing
I wanna point out as I lead into the next lecture,
which is that I'll just write this out again,
I guess which is that it turns out
we can take the entire algorithm,
and we can express the entire algorithm
in terms of inner products.
And here's what I mean by that.
So say that the parameters w
is the sum of your input examples.
And so we need to make a prediction.
Someone gives you a new value of x.
You want a value of the hypothesis
on the value of x.
That's given by g of w transpose x plus b,
or where g was this threshold function that
outputs minus 1 or plus 1.
And so you need to compute w transpose x plus b.
And that is equal to alpha i, yi.
And that can be expressed as
a sum of these inner products between
your training examples and this new value
of x [inaudible] value [inaudible].
And this will lead into our next lecture,
which is the idea of kernels.
And it turns out that
in the source of feature spaces where
used to support vector machines
it turns out that sometimes your training examples
may be very high-dimensional.
It may even be the case that
the features that you want to use
are infinite-dimensional feature vectors.
But despite this, it'll turn out that
there'll be an interesting representation that
you can use that will allow you
to compute inner products like these efficiently.
And this holds true only for certain feature spaces.
It doesn't hold true for arbitrary sets of features.
But we talk about the idea of kernels.
In the next lecture,
we'll see examples where even though
you have extremely high-dimensional feature vectors,
you can compute
you may never want to represent xi,
explicitly because xi is
an infinite-dimensional feature vector.
You cannot even store in computer memory.
But you will nonetheless be able to
compute inner products between different
[inaudible] feature vectors very efficiently.
And so you can for example,
you can make predictions by
making use of these inner products.
This is just xi transpose. You will compute
these inner products very efficiently and,
therefore, make predictions.
And this pointed also
the other reason we derive the dual
was because on this board,
when we worked out what w of alpha is,
w of alpha actually are the same property
w of alpha is again written
in terms of these inner products.
And so if you actually look at
the dual optimization problem and step
for all the steps of the algorithm,
you'll find that you actually do everything you want
learn the parameters of alpha.
So suppose you do an optimization problem,
go into parameters alpha,
and you do everything you want without
ever needing to represent xi directly.
And all you need to do
is represent this compute inner products
with your feature vectors like these.
Well, one last property of this algorithm
that's kinda nice is that I said previously that
the alpha i's are 0 only for the
are non-0 only for the support vectors,
only for the vectors
that function y [inaudible] 1.
And in practice, there are usually fairly few of them.
And so what this means is that
if you're representing w this way,
then w when represented
as a fairly small fraction of training examples
because mostly alpha i's is 0
and so when you're summing up the sum,
you need to compute inner products
only if the support vectors,
which is usually a small fraction of your training set.
So that's another nice [inaudible]
because [inaudible] alpha is 0.
And well, much of this will make much more sense
when we talk about kernels.
[Inaudible] quick questions before I close? Yeah.
Student:It seems that for anything
we've done the work,
the point file has to be really well behaved,
and if any of the points
are kinda on the wrong side
Instructor (Andrew Ng):No, oh, yeah, so again,
for today's lecture asks you that
the data is linearly separable
that you can actually get perfect [inaudible].
I'll fix this in the next lecture as well.
But excellent assumption. Yes?
Student:So can't we assume that [inaudible]
point [inaudible], so [inaudible] have [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, so unless I
says that there are ways to generalize this
in multiple classes that
I probably won't [inaudible]
but yeah, that's generalization [inaudible].
Okay. Let's close for today, then.
We'll talk about kernels in our next lecture.