Okay, so welcome back.
And what I want to do today is talk about
new test methods algorith for
fitting models like logistic regression,
and then we'll talk about exponential family
distributions and generalized linear models.
It's a very nice class of ideas that will tie together,
the logistic regression
and the ordinary V
squares models that we'll see.
So hopefully I'll get to that today.
So throughout the previous lecture
and this lecture,
we're starting to use increasingly
large amounts of material on probability.
So if you'd like to see a refresher on sort of the
foundations of probability if you're not sure
if you quite had your prerequisites for this
class in terms of a background in probability
and statistics, then the discussion section
taught this week by the TA's will go over
so they can review a probability.
At the same discussion sections also for the TA's,
we'll also briefly go over sort of
matlab and octave notation
which you need to use for your problem sets.
And so if you any of you want to see a review
of the probability and statistics pre-reqs,
or if you want to [inaudible] octave,
please come to this the next discussion section.
All right. So just to recap briefly,
towards the end of the last lecture I talked about
the logistic regression model where we had
which was an algorithm for [inaudible]
We had that [inaudible] of [inaudible]
if an XFY equals one, give an X theta
by theta under this model, all right.
If this was one over one [inaudible] theta,
transpose X. And then you can write down
the log likelihood like given the training sets,
which was that.
And by taking the derivitive of this,
you can derive sort of a gradient ascent rule
for finding the maximum likelihood estimate
of the parameter theta
for this logistic regression model.
And so last time I wrote down the learning rule
for batch gradient ascent, but the [inaudible] has to
be gradient ascent where you look at just
one training example at a time,
would be like this, okay.
So last time I wrote down batch gradient ascent.
This is stochastic gradient ascent.
So if you want to fit
a logistic regression model,
meaning find the value of theta that
maximizes this log likelihood,
gradient ascent or stochastic gradient ascent
or batch gradient ascent
is a perfectly fine algorithm to use.
But what I want to do is talk about a different
algorithm for fitting models
like logistic regression. And this would be
an algorithm that will, I guess,
often run much faster
than gradient ascent.
And this algorithm is called Newton's Method.
And when we describe Newton's Method
let me ask you I'm actually going to ask you
to consider a different problem first,
which is let's say you have a function F of theta,
and let's say you want to find the
value of theta so that F of theta is equal to zero.
Let's start the [inaudible], and then we'll
sort of slowly change this until it becomes
an algorithm for fitting
maximum likelihood models, like logistic regression.
So let's see. I guess that works. Okay,
so let's say that's my function F.
This is my horizontal axis of theta,
and so we're really trying to find this value for theta,
and which F of theta is equal to zero.
This is a horizontal axis.
So here's the algorithm we use.
I'm going to initialize theta as some value.
We'll call theta superscript zero.
And then here's what Newton's Method does.
We're going to evaluate the function F
at a value of theta, and then we'll compute
the derivitive of that, and we'll use
the linear approximation
to the function F of that value of theta.
So in particular, I'm going to take the tangents
to my function hope that makes sense
starting the function [inaudible] work out nicely.
I'm going to take the tangent to my function
at that point theta zero, and I'm going to
sort of extend this tangent down until
it intersects the horizontal axis.
I want to see what value this is.
And I'm going to call this theta one, okay.
And then so that's one iteration
of Newton's Method.
And what I'll do then is the same thing
with this point. Take the tangent down here,
and that's two iterations of the algorithm.
And then just sort of keep going,
that's theta three and so on, okay.
So let's just go ahead and write down
what this algorithm actually does.
To go from theta zero to theta one,
let me call that length
let me just call that capital delta.
So capital so if you remember the definition
of a derivative [inaudible],
derivative of F evaluated at theta zero.
In other words, the gradient of this first line,
by the definition of gradient is going to be equal
to this vertical length,
divided by this horizontal length.
A gradient of this so the slope of this function
is defined as the ratio between this vertical
height and this width of triangle.
So that's just equal to F of theta zero,
divided by delta,
which implies that delta is equal to F of theta zero,
divided by a prime of theta zero, okay.
And so theta one is therefore theta zero
minus delta, minus capital delta,
which is therefore just F theta zero
over F prime of theta zero, all right.
And more generally,
one iteration of Newton's Method precedes this,
theta T plus one equals theta T minus F of theta T
divided by F prime of theta T.
So that's one iteration of Newton's Method.
Now, this is an algorithm for finding
a value of theta for which F of theta equals zero.
And so we apply the same idea
to maximizing the log likelihood, right.
So we have a function L of theta,
and we ant to maximize this function.
Well, how do you maximize the function?
You set the derivative to zero.
So we want theta such that.
L prime of theta is equal to zero,
so to maximize this function we
want to find the place where the derivative
of the function is equal to zero,
and so we just apply the same idea.
So we get theta one equals theta T minus L
prime of theta T over L double prime of T,
L double prime of theta T, okay.
Because to maximize this function,
we just let F be equal to L prime.
Let F be the first derivitive  of L, and then we want to
find the value of theta for which
the derivative of L is zero,
and therefore must be a local optimum.
Does this make sense? Any questions about this?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):The answer to that
is fairly complicated.
There are conditions on F that
would guarantee that this will work.
They are fairly complicated,
and this is more complex than
I want to go into now. In practice,
this works very well for logistic regression,
and for sort of
generalizing linear models I'll talk about later.
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, it usually
doesn't matter. When I implement this,
I usually just initialize theta zero to zero
to just initialize the parameters to the
vector of all zeros, and usually this works fine.
It's usually not a huge deal
how you initialize theta.
Student:[Inaudible]
or is it just different conversions?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let me say some
things about that that'll sort of answer it.
All of these algorithms tend not to
converges problems, and all of these algorithms
will generally converge, unless you choose too
large a linear rate for
gradient ascent or something.
But the speeds of conversions
of these algorithms are very different.
So it turns out that Newton's Method
is an algorithm that enjoys extremely fast
conversions. The technical term is that it enjoys
a property called quadratic conversions.
Don't know about what that means,
but just stated informally,
it means that [inaudible] every iteration
of Newton's Method will double the number
of significant digits that your solution
is accurate to. Just lots of constant factors.
Suppose that on a certain iteration your solution
is within 0.01 at the optimum,
so you have 0.01 error. Then after one iteration,
your error will be on the order of 0.001,
and after another iteration, your error
will be on the order of 0.0000001.
So this is called quadratic conversions
because you essentially get to square
the error on every iteration of Newton's Method.
[Inaudible] result that holds only
when your [inaudible] cause the optimum anyway,
so this is the theoretical result that says it's true,
but because of constant factors and so on,
may paint a slightly rosier picture
than might be accurate.
But the fact is, when you implement
when I implement Newton's Method
for logistic regression, usually converges
like a dozen iterations or so
for most reasonable size problems
of tens of hundreds of features.
So one thing I should talk about,
which is what I wrote down over
there was actually Newton's Method for the
case of theta being a single-row number.
The generalization to Newton's Method for
when theta is a vector rather than
when theta is just a row number
is the following,
which is that theta T plus one is theta T plus
and then we have the second derivative divided
by the first the first derivative divided
by the second derivative.
And the appropriate generalization is this,
where this is the usual gradient of your
objective, and H here is a matrix
called a Hessian, which is just a matrix of
second derivative where HIJ equals okay.
So just to sort of the first derivative divided
by the second derivative, now you have a
vector of first derivatives times sort of
the inverse of the matrix of second derivatives.
So this is sort of just the same thing
[inaudible] of multiple dimensions.
So for logistic regression, again, use the
for a reasonable number of features and
training examples when I run this algorithm,
usually you see a conversion anywhere
from sort of [inaudible] to like
a dozen or so other [inaudible].
To compare to gradient ascent,
it's [inaudible] to gradient ascent,
this usually means far fewer iterations
to converge. Compared to gradient ascent,
let's say batch gradient ascent,
the disadvantage of Newton's Method is that
on every iteration you
need to invert the Hessian.
So the Hessian will be an N-by-N matrix,
or an N plus one by N plus one-dimensional
matrix if N is the number of features.
And so if you have a large number of features in
your learning problem, if you have tens of
thousands of features, then inverting H could be
a slightly computationally expensive step.
But for smaller, more reasonable numbers of
features, this is usually a very fast algorithm.
Question?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
I think you're right.
That should probably be a minus.
Do you have [inaudible]? Yeah, thanks.
Yeah, X to a minus.
Thank you. [Inaudible] problem also.
I wrote down this algorithm to find the maximum
likely estimate of the parameters
for logistic regression.
I wrote this down for maximizing a function.
So I'll leave you to think about this yourself.
If I wanted to use Newton's Method to minimize
the function, how does the algorithm change?
All right. So I'll leave you to think about that.
So in other words, it's not the maximizations.
How does the algorithm change
if you want to use it for minimization?
Actually, the answer is that it doesn't change.
I'll leave you to work that out yourself why, okay.
All right. Let's talk about generalized linear models.
Let me just say, just to give a recap
of both of the algorithms we've talked about
so far. We've talked about two different
algorithms for modeling PFY
given X and parameterized by theta.
And one of them R was a real number
and we assume that. And we sort of the
[inaudible] has a Gaussian distribution,
then we got, you know,
ordinary least squares of linear regression.
In the other case, we saw that if
was a classification problem where Y took
on a value of either zero or one. In that case,
well, what's the most natural distribution
of zeros and ones is the Bernoulli.
The Bernoulli distribution models random
variables with two values,
and in that case we got logistic regression.
So along the way, some of the questions that
came up were for logistic regression,
where on earth did I get the
sigmoid function from? And then so there are the choices
you can use for, sort of, just where
did this function come from?
And there are other functions I could've
plugged in, but the sigmoid function turns out
to be a natural default choice that lead us
to logistic regression. And what I want to do
now is take both of these algorithms and
show that they are special cases of
a broader class of algorithms
called generalized linear models, and there will be
pauses for it will be as a broader class
of algorithms that think that the sigmoid
function will fall out very naturally as well.
So, let's see just looking for a longer piece
of chalk. I should warn you, the ideas in
generalized linear models are somewhat complex,
so what I'm going to do today is try to
sort of point you point out the key ideas and
give you a gist of the entire story.
And then some of the details in the map
and the derivations I'll leave you to work through
by yourselves in the intellection [inaudible],
which posts online.
So [inaudible] these two distributions,
the Bernoulli and the Gaussian.
So suppose we have data that is zero-one valued,
and we and we want to model it
with a Bernoulli random variable
variable parameterized by phi.
So the Bernoulli distribution has
the probability of Y equals one,
which just equals the phi, right.
So the parameter phi in the Bernoulli
specifies the probability of Y being one.
Now, as you vary the parameter theta,
you get you sort of get different Bernoulli distributions
distributions. As you vary the value of theta
you get different probability distributions on
Y that have different probabilities of being
equal to one. And so I want you to think of
this as not one fixed distribution,
but as a set where there are a class
of distributions that you get as you vary theta.
And in the same way, if you consider
Gaussian distribution, as you vary [inaudible] you
would get different Gaussian distributions.
So think of this again as a class
or as a set to distributions.
And what I want to do now is show that
both of these are special cases of the class of
distribution that's called the exponential
family distribution. And in particular,
we'll say that the class of distributions,
like the Bernoulli distributions that you get
as you vary theta, we'll say the class
of distributions is in the exponential family
if it can be written in the following form.
P of Y parameterized by theta is
equal to B of Y [inaudible], okay.
Let me just get some of these terms, names,
and then let me I'll say a bit more about
what this means. So [inaudible] is called
the natural parameter of the distribution,
and T of Y is called the sufficient statistic.
Usually, for many of the examples we'll see,
including the [inaudible] and the Gaussian,
T of Y is just equal to Y. So for most of this
lecture you can mentally replace T of Y
to be equal to Y, although this won't be true for
the very fine example we do today,
but mentally, you think of T of Y as equal to Y.
And so for a given choice of these functions,
A, B and T, all right so we're gonna sort
of fix the forms of the functions A, B and T.
Then this formula defines, again, a set of
distributions. It defines the class of distributions
that is now parameterized by [inaudible].
So again, let's write down specific formulas for A,
B and T, true specific choices of A, B
and T. Then as I vary [inaudible]
I get different distributions.
And I'm going to show that
the [inaudible] I'm going to show that
the Bernoulli and the Gaussians are special
cases of exponential family distributions.
And by that I mean that I can choose specific
functions, A, B and T, so that this becomes
the formula of the distributions of
either a Bernoulli or a Gaussian.
And then again, as I vary [inaudible],
I'll get [inaudible], distributions with different
means, or as I vary [inaudible],
I'll get Gaussian distributions with different means
for my fixed values of A, B and T.
And for those of you that know
what a sufficient statistic and statistics is,
T of Y actually is a sufficient statistic
in the formal sense of sufficient statistic
for a probability distribution.
They may have seen it in a statistics class.
If you don't know what a sufficient statistic is,
don't worry about.
We sort of don't need that property today.
Okay. So oh, one last comment. Often,
T of Y is equal to Y, and in many of these cases,
[inaudible] is also just a real number.
So in many cases,
the parameter of this distribution
is just a real number, and [inaudible] transposed
T of Y is just a product of real numbers.
So again, that would be true
for our first two examples,
but now for the last example I'll do today.
So now we'll show that the [inaudible] and
the Gaussian are examples
of exponential family distributions.
We'll start with the [inaudible].
So the [inaudible] distribution with
[inaudible] I guess I wrote this down already.
PFY equals one [inaudible] by phi,
[inaudible] equal to phi.
So the parameter of phi specifies
the probability that Y equals one.
And so my goal now is to choose T, A and B,
or is to choose A, B and T so that my formula
for the exponential family becomes identical
to my formula for the distribution of a [inaudible].
So probability of Y parameterized by phi
is equal to that, all right. And you already saw
sort of a similar exponential notation
where we talked about logistic regression.
The probability of Y being one is phi,
the probability of Y being zero is one minus phi,
so we can write this compactly as phi
to the Y times one minus phi to the one minus Y.
So I'm gonna take the exponent of the log of this,
an exponentiation in taking log
[inaudible] cancel each other out [inaudible].
And this is equal to E to the Y.
And so [inaudible] is to be T of Y,
and this will be minus A of [inaudible].
And then B of Y is just one,
so B of Y doesn't matter.
Just take a second to look through this
and make sure it makes sense.
I'll clean another board while you do that.
So now let's write down a few more things.
Just copying from the previous board,
we had that [inaudible] zero four equal
to log phi over one minus phi.
It turns out, so if I want
to do the algebra, it turns out we
take this formula, and if you invert it,
if you solve for phi excuse me, if you solve
for theta as a function of phi, which is really
[inaudible] is the function of phi.
Just invert this formula. You find that phi
is one over one plus [inaudible] minus [inaudible].
And so somehow the logistic function
magically falls out of this.
We'll take this even this even further later.
Again, copying definitions from the board on
from the previous board, A of [inaudible]
I said is minus log of one minus phi.
So again, phi and [inaudible] are function of each
other, all right. So [inaudible] depends on phi,
and phi depends on [inaudible].
So if I plug in this definition for [inaudible]
into this excuse me, plug in this definition
for phi into that, I'll find that A of [inaudible]
is therefore equal to log one plus
[inaudible] to [inaudible]. And again,
this is just algebra.
This is not terribly interesting. .
And just to complete excuse me.
And just to complete the rest of this,
T of Y is equal to Y,
and B of Y is equal to one, okay.
So just to recap what we've done, we've come up
with a certain choice of functions A,
T and B, so then my formula
for the exponential family distribution
now becomes exactly the formula
for the distributions, or for the probability
mass function of the [inaudible] distribution.
And the natural parameter [inaudible]
has a certain relationship of the original parameter
of the [inaudible]. Question?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see. [Inaudible].
Student:The second to the last one.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, this answer is fine.
Student:Okay.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see. Yeah,
so this is well, if you expand this term out,
one minus Y times log Y minus phi, and
so one times log one minus phi becomes this.
And the other term is minus Y times log Y
minus phi. And then so the minus of a log is
log one over X, or is just log one over whatever.
So minus Y times log one minus phi
becomes sort of Y times log,
one over one minus phi. Does that make sense?
Student:Yeah.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, cool.
Anything else? Yes?
Student:[Inaudible] is a scalar, isn't it? Up there
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes.
Student:– it's a [inaudible] transposed,
so it can be a vector or
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, [inaudible].
So let's see. In most in this and the next
example, [inaudible] will turn out
to be a scalar. And so well, on this board.
And so if [inaudible] is a scalar and T of Y
is a scalar, then this is just a real number times
a real number. So this would be like a
one-dimensional vector transposed
times a one-dimensional vector.
And so this is just real number times real number.
Towards the end of today's lecture,
we'll go with just one example where
both of these are vectors.
But for many distributions,
these will turn out to be scalars.
Student:[Inaudible] distribution [inaudible].
I mean, it doesn't have the zero probability
or [inaudible] zero and one.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):I see. So yeah.
Let's for this, let's imagine that we're
restricting the domain of the input of the
function to be Y equals zero or one.
So think of that as maybe
in implicit constraint on it. [Inaudible].
But so this is a probability mass
function for Y equals zero or Y equals one.
So write down Y equals zero one.
Let's think of that as an implicit constraint.
So cool. So this takes the Bernoulli
distribution and writes in the form of
exponential family distribution. Let me just
do that very quickly for the Gaussian.
I won't do the algebra for the Gaussian.
I'll basically just write out the answers.
So with a normal distribution
with mean μ and variance
sigma squared, and so you remember,
was it two lectures ago, when we were
deriving the maximum likelihood excuse me,
oh, no, just the previous lecture when we were
deriving the maximum likelihood estimate
for the parameters of ordinary least squares.
We showed that the parameter for
sigma squared didn't matter.
When we derive the probabilistic model for
least square regression, we said that
no matter what sigma square was,
we end up with the same value of the parameters.
So for the purposes of just writing lesson,
today's lecture, and not taking account
sigma squared, I'm just going
to set sigma squared to be for the one,
okay, so as to not worry about it.
Lecture [inaudible] talks a little bit more
about this, but I'm just gonna just to make
[inaudible] in class a bit easier and simpler today,
let's just say that sigma square
equals one. Sigma square is essentially
just a scaling factor on the variable Y.
So in that case, the Gaussian density is given
by this, [inaudible] squared. And well, by
a couple of steps of algebra, which I'm not
going to do, but is written out in [inaudible] in
the lecture notes so you can download.
This is one root two pie,
E to the minus one-half Y squared times E to E.
New Y minus one-half [inaudible] squared,
okay. So I'm just not doing the algebra.
And so that's B of Y, we have [inaudible]
that's equal to [inaudible]. T(y)equals Y,
and well, A of [inaudible] is equal
to minus one-half actually, I think that
should be plus one-half. Have I got that right?
Yeah, sorry. Let's see excuse me.
Plus sign there, okay. If you minus
one-half [inaudible] squared, and because
[inaudible] is equal to [inaudible], this is just
minus one-half [inaudible] squared, okay.
And so this would be a specific choice again of A,
B and T that expresses the Gaussian density
in the form of an exponential family distribution.
And in this case, the relationship between
[inaudible] and [inaudible] is that [inaudible]
is just equal to [inaudible],
so the [inaudible] of the Gaussian
is just equal to the natural parameter of
the exponential family distribution.
Student:Minus half.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, this is minus half?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, okay, thanks.
And so guessing that should be plus then.
Is that right? Okay. Oh, yes, you're right.
Thank you. All right.
And so that turns out that if you've
taken a look in undergraduate statistics class,
turns out that most of the "textbook distributions,
not all, but most of them, can be written in the
form of an exponential family distribution.
So you saw the Gaussian,
the normal distribution.
It turns out the multivariate normal
distribution, which is a generalization
of Gaussian random variables,
so it's a high dimension to vectors.
The [inaudible] normal distribution
is also in the exponential family.
You saw the Bernoulli as an exponential family.
It turns out the multinomial distribution is too,
all right. So the Bernoulli models outcomes
over zero and one.
They'll be coin tosses with two outcomes.
The multinomial models outcomes
over K possible values.
That's also an exponential families distribution.
You may have heard of the Poisson distribution.
And so the Poisson distribution
is often used for modeling counts.
Things like the number of radioactive decays
in a sample,
or the number of customers to your website,
the numbers of visitors arriving in a store.
The Poisson distribution
is also in the exponential family.
So are the gamma and the exponential
distributions, if you've heard of them.
So the gamma and the exponential distributions
are distributions of the positive numbers.
So they're often used in model intervals,
like if you're standing at the bus stop
and you want to ask,
"When is the next bus likely to arrive?
How long do I have to wait for my bus to arrive?"
Often you model that with sort of gamma
distribution or exponential families,
or the exponential distribution.
Those are also in the exponential family.
Even more [inaudible] distributions,
like the beta and the Dirichlet distributions,
these are probably distributions over fractions,
are already probability distributions
over probability distributions.
And also things like the Wishart distribution,
which is the distribution over covariance matrices.
So all of these, it turns out, can be written in the
form of exponential family distributions.
Well, and in the problem set where
he asks you to take one of these distributions and
write it in the form of the exponential
family distribution, and derive
a generalized linear model for it, okay.
Which brings me to the next topic of
having chosen and exponential family distribution,
how do you use it
to derive a generalized linear model?
So generalized linear models
are often abbreviated GLM's. And I'm going to
write down the three assumptions.
You can think of them as assumptions,
or you can think of them as design choices,
that will then allow me to sort of turn a crank
and come up with a generalized linear model.
So the first one is I'm going to assume
that given my input X and my parameters theta,
I'm going to assume that the variable Y,
the output Y, or the response variable Y I'm
trying to predict is distributed exponential family
with some natural parameter [inaudible].
And so this means that there is some
specific choice of those functions, A, B and T
so that the conditional distribution of Y
given X and parameterized by theta, those
exponential families with parameter [inaudible].
Where here,
[inaudible] may depend on X in some way.
So for example, if you're trying to predict
if you want to predict how many customers
have arrived at your website, you may choose
to model the number of people
the number of hits on your website
by Poisson Distribution, since Poisson Distribution
is natural for modeling count data.
And so you may choose the exponential family
distribution here to be the Parson distribution.
[Inaudible] that given X, our goal is to output
the expective value of Y given X.
So given the features in the website examples,
I've given a set of features about
whether there were any proportions,
whether there were sales,
how many people linked to your website,
or whatever. I'm going to assume that our goal
in our [inaudible] problem is to estimate the
expected number of people that will arrive
at your website on a given day.
So in other words, you're saying that
I want HFX to be equal to oh, excuse me.
I actually meant to write T of Y here.
My goal is to get my learning algorithms
hypothesis to output the expected
value of TFY given X.
But again, for most of the examples,
T of Y is just equal to Y.
And so for most of the examples,
our goal is to get our learning algorithms output,
T expected value of Y given X
because T of Y is usually equal to Y. Yes?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, same thing, right.
T of Y is a sufficient statistic. Same T of Y.
And lastly, this last one I wrote down
these are assumptions. This last one you might
maybe wanna think of this as a design choice.
Which is [inaudible] assume that the distribution
of Y given X is a distributed exponential family
with some parameter [inaudible].
So the number of visitors on the website on any
given day will be Poisson or some parameter
And the last decision I need to make
is was the relationship between my input features
and this parameter [inaudible] parameterizing
my Parson distribution or whatever.
And this last step, I'm going
to make the assumption, or really a design choice,
that I'm going to assume the relationship between
[inaudible] and my [inaudible] axi s linear,
and in particular that they're governed by this
that [inaudible] is equal to theta, transpose X.
And the reason I make this design choice
is it will allow me to turn the crank of the
generalized linear model of machinery and
come off with very nice algorithms for fitting
say Poisson Regression models or performed
regression with a gamma distribution outputs
or exponential distribution outputs and so on.
So let's work through an example.
[Inaudible] equals theta transpose X works for the
case where [inaudible] is a real number.
For the more general case, you would have
[inaudible] I equals theta I, transpose X
if [inaudible] is a vector rather than a real
number. But again, most of the examples
[inaudible] will just be a real number.
All right. So let's work through the Bernoulli
example. You'll see where Y given X
parameterized by theta this is a
distributed exponential family with
natural parameter [inaudible].
And for the [inaudible] distribution,
I'm going to choose A, B and T to be the
specific forms that cause those exponential
families to become the Bernoulli distribution.
This is the example we worked through just now,
the first example we worked through just now.
So oh, and we also have so for any fixed
value of X and theta, my hypothesis,
my learning algorithm will make a prediction,
or will make will sort of output [inaudible]
of X, which is by my,
I guess, assumption [inaudible].
Watch our learning algorithm to
output the expected value of Y given X and
parameterized by theta, where Y can take
on only the value zero and one,
then the expected value of Y is just equal
to the probability that Y is equal to one.
So the expected value of a Bernoulli random variable is
just equal to the probability that it's equal to one.
And so the probability that Y equals one
is just equal to phi because that's the parameter
of my Bernoulli distribution. Phi is,
by definition, I guess, is the probability of my
Bernoulli distribution [inaudible] value of one.
Which we worked out previously,
phi was one over one plus E to the negative
[inaudible]. So we worked this out
on our previous board. This is the relationship
so when we wrote down the Bernoulli
distribution in the form of an exponential family,
we worked out what the relationship was
between phi and [inaudible], and it was this.
So we worked out the relationship
between the expected value of Y
and [inaudible] was this relationship.
And lastly, because we made the design choice,
or the assumption that [inaudible] and theta are
linearly related. This is therefore equal to one
over one plus E to the minus theta, transpose X.
And so that's how I come up with the
logistic regression algorithm when you have a
variable Y when you have a [inaudible]
variable Y, or also response variable Y that
takes on two values, and then you choose to
model variable [inaudible] distribution.
Are you sure this does make sense?
Raise your hand if this makes sense.
Yeah, okay, cool.
So I hope you get the ease of use of this,
or sort of the power of this. The only decision I
made was really, I said Y let's say I have
a new machine-learning problem and I'm
trying to predict the value of a variable
Y that happens to take on two values.
Then the only decision I need to make
is I chose [inaudible] distribution.
I say I want to model I want to assume
that given X and theta, I'm going to assume Y is
distributed [inaudible].
That's the only decision I made.
And then everything else follows automatically
having made the decision to model Y given X
and parameterized by theta as being [inaudible].
In the same way you can choose a
different distribution, you can choose Y
as Parson or Y as
gamma or Y as whatever,
and follow a similar process and come up with
a different model and different learning algorithm.
Come up with a different generalized linear model
for whatever learning algorithm you're faced with.
This tiny little notation, the function G that
relates G of [inaudible] that relates the natural
parameter to the expected value of Y,
which in this case, one over one plus [inaudible]
minus [inaudible], this is called the
canonical response function. And G inverse
is called the canonical link function.
These aren't a huge deal. I won't use
this terminology a lot. I'm just mentioning
those in case you hear about people talk about
generalized linear models, and if they talk about
canonical response functions or canonical
link functions,
just so you know there's all of this.
Actually, many techs actually use the reverse way.
This is G inverse and this is G, but
this notation turns out to be more consistent
with other algorithms in machine learning.
So I'm going to use this notation.
But I probably won't use the terms
canonical response functions and canonical
link functions in lecture a lot, so just
I don't know. I'm not big on memorizing
lots of names of things. I'm just tossing those
out there in case you see it elsewhere.
Okay. You know what, I think in the interest
of time, I'm going to skip over the Gaussian
example. But again, just like I said, [inaudible],
Y is [inaudible], different variation I get
of logistic regression. You can do the same
thing with the Gaussian distribution and end
up with ordinary [inaudible] squares model.
The problem with Gaussian is that it's almost
so simple that when you see it for the first
time that it's sometimes more confusing
than the [inaudible] model
because it looks so
simple, it looks like it has to be more complicated.
So let me just skip that and leave you to read
about the Gaussian example
in the lecture notes.
And what I want to do is actually go through
a more complex example. Question?
Student:[Inaudible]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Okay, right.
So how do choose what theta will be?
We'll get to that in the end. What you have
there is the logistic regression model,
which is a probabilistic model that assumes
the probability of Y given X
is given by a certain form.
And so what you do is you can write down
the log likelihood of your training set,
and find the value of theta that maximizes
the log likelihood of the parameters.
Does that make sense?
So I'll say that again towards
the end of today's lecture.
But for logistic regression, the way you
choose theta is exactly maximum likelihood,
as we worked out in the previous lecture,
using Newton's Method or gradient ascent or
whatever. I'll sort of try to do that again
for one more example
towards the end of today's lecture.
So what I want to do is actually use the remaining,
I don't know, 19 minutes or so of this class,
to go through the one of the more
it's probably the most complex example of a
generalized linear model that I've used.
This one I want to go through because it's
a little bit trickier than many of the other
textbook examples of generalized linear models.
So again, what I'm going to do is go through
the derivation reasonably quickly and give
you the gist of it,
and if there are steps I skip
or details omitted, I'll leave you to read
about them more carefully in the lecture notes.
And what I want to do is talk about Multinomial.
And Multinomial is the distribution over K
possible outcomes. Imagine you're now in
a machine-learning problem where the value of Y
that you're trying to predict can take on K possible
outcomes, so rather than only two outcomes.
So obviously, this example's already
if you want to have a learning algorithm,
or to magically send emails for you into your
right email folder, and you may have a dozen
email folders you want your algorithm
to classify emails into.
Or predicting if the patient either has
a disease or does not have a disease, which
would be a binary classification problem.
If you think that the patient may have
one of K diseases, and you want other than have a
learning algorithm figure out which
one of K diseases your patient has is all.
So lots of multi-class classification problems
where you have more than two classes.
You model that with Multinomial.
And eventually so for logistic regression,
I had [inaudible] like these where you
have a training set and you find
a decision boundary that separates them.
[Inaudible], we're going to entertain the
value of predicting, taking on multiple values,
so you now have three classes,
and the learning algorithm will learn some way
to separate out three classes or more,
rather than just two classes.
So let's write Multinomial in the form of
an exponential family distribution.
So the parameters of a Multinomial are phi one,
phi two [inaudible] phi K.
I'll actually change this in a second
where the probability of Y equals I is phi I,
right, because there are K possible outcomes.
But if I choose this
as my parameterization
of the [inaudible], then my parameter's
actually redundant because if these are
probabilities, then you have to sum up the one.
And therefore for example,
I can derive the last parameter, phi K,
as one minus phi one, up to phi K minus one.
So this would be a redundant
parameterization from [inaudible].
The result is over-parameterized.
And so for purposes of this [inaudible],
I'm going to treat my parameters of my
[inaudible] as phi one, phi two, up to phi
K minus one. And I won't think of phi K as a
parameter. I'll just so my parameters are just
I just have K minus one parameters,
parameterizing my [inaudible].
And sometimes I write phi K in my derivations
as well, and you should think of phi K as
just a shorthand for this, for one minus
the rest of the parameters, okay.
So it turns out the [inaudible] is one of the
few examples where T of Y it's one of the
examples where T of Y is not equal to Y.
So in this case, Y is on of K possible values.
And so T of Y would be defined as follows;
T of one is going to be a vector with a one
and zeros everywhere else.
T of two is going to be a zero, one, zero and so on.
Except that these are going to
be K minus one-dimensional vectors.
And so T of K minus one is going to be zero,
zero, zero, one. And T of K
is going to be the vector of all zeros.
So this is just how I'm choosing to define T
of Y to write down the [inaudible] in the form
of an exponential family distribution. Again,
these are K minus one-dimensional vectors.
So this is a good point to introduce one more
useful piece of notation, which is called
indicator function notation. So I'm going
to write one, and then curly braces.
And if I write a true statement inside, then
the indicator of that statement is going to be one.
Then I write one, and then I write a false
statement inside, then the value of this indicator
function is going to be a zero.
For example, if I write indicator two equals
three [inaudible] that's false,
and so this is equal to zero.
Whereas indicator [inaudible] plus one equals two,
I wrote down a true statement inside.
And so the indicator of the statement
was equal to one. So the indicator function
is just a very useful notation for indicating
sort of truth or falsehood of the statement inside.
And so actually, let's do this here.
To combine both of these, right,
if I carve out a bit of space here so if I use
so TY is a vector. Y is one of K values,
and so TY is one of these K vectors.
If I use TY as [inaudible] to denote
the [inaudible] element of the vector TY, then TY
the [inaudible] element of the vector TY is
just equal to indicator for whether Y is equal to I.
Just take a let me clean a couple more boards.
Take a look at this for a second and make
sure you understand why that make sure you
understand all that notation and why this is true.
All right. Actually, raise your hand if this
equation makes sense to you.
Most of you, not all, okay. [Inaudible].
Just as one kind of [inaudible],
suppose Y is equal to one let's say let me see.
Suppose Y is equal to one, right,
so TY is equal to this vector,
and therefore the first element of this vector
will be one, and the rest of the elements
will be equal to zero.
And so let me try that again, I'm sorry.
Let's say I want to ask I want to look at the
[inaudible] element of the vector TY,
and I want to know is this one or zero. All right.
Well, this will be one.
The [inaudible] element of the vector TY
will be equal to one if, and only if Y is equal to I.
Because for example, if Y is equal to one,
then only the first element of this vector will
be zero. If Y is equal to two,
then only the second element of the vector
will be zero and so on. So the question of
whether or not whether the [inaudible] element
of this vector, TY, is equal to one
is answered by just asking is Y equal to I.
Okay. If you're still not
quite sure why that's true,
go home and think about it a bit more.
And I think I and take a look at the
lecture notes as well, maybe that'll help.
At least for now, only just take my word for it.
So let's go ahead and write out the distribution
for the [inaudible] in an exponential family form.
So PFY is equal to phi one. Indicator Y
equals one times phi two.
Indicator Y equals to up to phi K times indicator
Y equals K. And again, phi K is not a parameter
of the distribution. Phi K is a shorthand for
one minus phi one minus phi two minus the rest.
And so using this equation on the left as well,
I can also write this as phi one times TY
one, phi two, TY two, dot, dot, dot.
Phi K minus one, TY, K minus one times phi K.
And then one minus [inaudible]. That should be j.
And it turns out it takes some of the
steps of algebra that I don't have time to show.
It turns out, you can simplify this into well,
the exponential family form where [inaudible]
is a vector, this is a K minus
one-dimensional vector, and well, okay.
So deriving this is a few steps of algebra
that you can work out yourself, but I won't do
here. And so using my definition for TY,
and by choosing [inaudible] A and B this way,
I can take my distribution
from [inaudible] and write it out
in a form of an exponential family distribution.
It turns out also that let's see. [Inaudible],
right. One of the things we did was we also
had [inaudible] as a function of phi, and then
we inverted that to write out phi as a function of
[inaudible]. So it turns out you can do that as well.
So this defines [inaudible] as a function
of the [inaudible] distributions parameters phi.
So you can take this relationship between
[inaudible] and phi and invert it, and write out
phi as a function of [inaudible]. And it turns out,
you get that phi I is equal to [inaudible]
excuse me. And you get that phi I
is equal to [inaudible] I of one plus that.
And the way you do this is you just
this defines [inaudible] as a function of the phi,
so if you take this and solve for [inaudible],
you end up with this. And this is again,
there are a couple of steps of algebra
that I'm just not showing.
And then lastly, using our assumption
that the [inaudible] are a linear function of the
[inaudible] axis, phi I is therefore equal to E
to the theta I, transpose X, divided by one
plus sum over J equals one, to K minus one,
E to the theta J, transpose X. And this is just
using the fact that [inaudible] I equals theta I,
transpose X, which was our earlier design
choice from generalized linear models.
So we're just about down.
So my learning algorithm [inaudible].
I'm going to think of it as [inaudible] the expected
value of TY given X and [inaudible] by theta.
So TY was this vector indicator function.
So T one was indicator Y equals one,
down to indicator Y equals K minus one.
All right. So I want
my learning algorithm
to output this; the expected value of this vector
of indicator functions.
The expected value of indicator Y equals one
is just the probability that Y equals one,
which is given by phi one.
So I have a random variable that's one
whenever Y is equal to one and zero otherwise,
so the expected value of that,
of this indicator Y equals one is just
the probability that Y equals one,
which is given by phi one.
And therefore, by what we were taught earlier,
this is therefore [inaudible] to the theta
one, transpose X over well okay.
And so my learning algorithm will output the
probability that Y equals one, Y equals two,
up to Y equals K minus one.
And these probabilities are going
to be parameterized by these functions like these.
And so just to give this algorithm a name,
this algorithm is called softmax regression,
and is widely thought of as the generalization
of logistic regression, which is regression of
two classes. Is widely thought of
as a generalization of logistic regression
to the case of K classes rather than two classes.
And so just to be very concrete about what you do,
right. So you have a machine-learning
problem, and you want to apply
softmax regression to it. So generally,
work for the entire derivation [inaudible].
I think the question you had is about
how to fit parameters.
So let's say you have a machine-learning problem,
and Y takes on one of K classes.
What you do is you sit down and say,
"Okay, I wanna model Y
as being [inaudible] given any
X and then theta." And so you chose [inaudible]
as the exponential family.
Then you sort of turn the crank.
And everything else I wrote down
follows automatically from you have
made the choice of using [inaudible]
distribution as your choice of exponential family.
And then what you do is you then have
this training set, X, I, Y, I up to X, M, Y, M.
So you're doing the training set.
We're now [inaudible] the value of
Y takes on one of K possible values.
And what you do is you then find the
parameters of the model by maximum likelihood.
So you write down the likelihood of
the parameters, and you maximize the likelihood.
So what's the likelihood? Well, the likelihood,
as usual, is the product of your training set
of P of YI given XI parameterized by theta.
That's the likelihood, same as we had before.
And that's product of your training set of
let me write these down now. YI equals one
times phi two of indicator YI equals two, dot,
dot, dot, to phi K of indicator YI equals K.
Where, for example, phi one depends on
theta through this formula. It is E to the theta
one, transpose X over one plus sum over J
well, that formula I had just now. And so phi
one here is really a shorthand for this formula,
and similarly for phi two and so on,
up to phi K, where phi K is one minus
all of these things. All right.
So this is a –this formula looks more
complicated than it really is.
What you really do is you write this down,
then you take logs, compute a derivative
of this formula [inaudible] theta, and apply
say gradient ascent to maximize the likelihood.
Student:What are the rows of theta?
[Inaudible] it's just been a vector, right?
And now it looks like it's two-dimensional.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah. In the notation
of the [inaudible] I think have theta one through
theta K minus one. I've been thinking of each
of these as and N plus one-dimensional vector.
If X is N plus one-dimensional,
then I've been see, I think if you have a set of
parameters comprising K minus one vectors,
and each of these is a you could group all
of these together a matrix,
but I just haven't been doing that. [Inaudible]
the derivative of K minus one parameter vectors.
Student:[Inaudible], what do they correspond to?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):[Inaudible].
We're sort of out of time. Let me take that offline.
It's hard to answer in the same way that
the logistic regression what does theta
correspond to in logistic regression?
You can sort of answer that as sort of
Student:Yeah.
It's kind of like the [inaudible] feature
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
Sort of similar interpretation, yeah.
That's good. I think I'm running a little bit late.
Why don't I
why don't we officially close for the day,
but you can come up if you more questions