MachineLearning-Lecture16
All right, so welcome back.
What I want to do today is start a new chapter,
a new discussion on machine learning
and in particular, I want to talk about
a different type of learning problem
called reinforcement learning,
so that's Markov Decision Processes,
value functions, value iteration,
and policy iteration.
Both of these last two items are algorithms
for solving reinforcement learning problems.
As you can see, we're also taping
a different room today,
so the background is a bit different.
So just to put this in context, the first of
the four major topics we had in this class was
supervised learning and in supervised learning,
we had the training set in which we were
given sort of the "right" answer of every
training example and it was then just a drop of
the learning algorithms to replicate
more of the right answers.
And then that was learning theory and then we
talked about unsupervised learning, and in
unsupervised learning, we had just a bunch of
unlabeled data, just the x's, and it was the
job in the learning algorithm to discover
so-called structure in the data and several
algorithms like cluster analysis, K-means, a
mixture of all the sort
of the PCA, ICA, and so on.
Today, I want to talk about a different class of
learning algorithms that's sort of in
between supervised and unsupervised, so there
will be a class of problems where there's
a level of supervision that's also much less
supervision than what we saw in supervised
learning. And this is a problem in formalism
called reinforcement learning. So next up
here are slides. Let me show you. As a moving
example, here's an example of the sorts of
things we do with reinforcement learning.
So here's a picture of some of this I talked
about in Lecture 1 as well, but here's a
picture of the we have an autonomous
helicopter we have at Stanford. So how would
you write a program to make a helicopter like
this fly by itself? I'll show you a fun video.
This is actually, I think, the same video that I
showed in class in the first lecture, but
here's a video taken in the football field at
Stanford of using machine learning algorithm
to fly the helicopter.
So let's just play the video.
You can zoom in the camera and see the trees in
the sky. So in terms of autonomous
helicopter flight, this is written then by some of
my students and me. In terms of
autonomous helicopter flight, this is one of the
most difficult aerobatic maneuvers flown
and it's actually very hard to write a program to
make a helicopter do this and the way
this was done was with what's called
a reinforcement learning algorithm.
So just to make this more concrete, right, the
learning problem in helicopter flight is ten
times per second, say. Your sensors on the
helicopter gives you a very accurate estimate
of the position of orientation of the helicopter
and so you know where the helicopter is
pretty accurately at all points in time. And your
job is to take this input, the position
orientation, and to output a set of numbers that
correspond to where to move the control
sticks to control the helicopter, to make it fly, to
right side up, fly upside down, actually
whatever maneuver you want.
And this is different from supervised learning
because usually we actually don't know
what the "right" control action is. And more
specifically, if the helicopter is in a certain
position orientation, it's actually very hard to
say when the helicopter is doing this, you
should move the control sticks exactly these
positions. So it's very hard to apply
supervised learning algorithms to this problem
because we can't come up with a training
set where the inputs of the position and the
output is all the "right" control actions. It's
really hard to come up with
a training set like that.
Instead of reinforcement learning, we'll give
the learning algorithm a different type of
feedback, basically called a reward signal,
which will tell the helicopter when it's doing
well and when it's doing poorly. So what we'll
end up doing is we're coming up with
something called a reward signal and I'll
formalize this later, which will be a measure of
how well the helicopter is doing, and then it
will be the job of the learning algorithm to
take just this reward function
as input and try to fly well.
Another good example of reinforcement
learning is thinking about getting a program to
play a game, to play chess, a game of chess. At
any stage in the game, we actually don't
know what the "optimal" move is, so it's very
hard to pose playing chess as a supervised
learning problem because we can't say the x's
are the board positions and the y's are the
optimum moves because we just don't know
how we create any training examples of
optimum moves of chess.
But what we do know is if you have a computer
playing games of chess, we know when
its won a game and when its lost a game, so
what we do is we give it a reward signal, so
give it a positive reward when it wins a game of
chess and give it a negative reward
whenever it loses,
and hopefully have it learn to
win more and more games by itself over time.
So what I'd like you to think about
reinforcement learning is think about training a
dog. Every time your dog does something good,
you sort of tell it, "Good dog," and every time
it does something bad, you tell it, "Bad dog,"
and over time, your dog learns to do more
and more good things over time.
So in the same way, when we try to fly a
helicopter, every time the helicopter does
something good, you say, "Good helicopter,"
and every time it crashes, you say, "Bad
helicopter," and then over time, it learns to do
the right things more and more often.
The reason one of the reasons that
reinforcement learning is much harder than
supervised learning is because this is not a
one-shot decision making problem. So in
supervised learning, if you have a
classification, prediction if someone
has cancer or not, you make a prediction and
then you're done, right? And your patient either
has cancer or not, you're either right or wrong,
they live or die, whatever. You make a decision
and then you're done.
In reinforcement learning, you have to keep
taking actions over time, so it's called the
sequential decision making. So concretely,
suppose a program loses a game of chess on
move No. 60. Then it has actually made 60
moves before it got this negative reward of
losing a game of chess and the thing that makes
it hard for the algorithm to learn from
this is called the credit assignment problem.
And just to state that informally, what this is
if the program loses a game of chess in move
60, you're actually not quite sure of all the
moves he made which ones were the right
moves and which ones were the bad moves,
and so maybe it's because you've blundered on
move No. 23 and then everything else
you did may have been perfect, but because you
made a mistake on move 23 in your
game of chess, you eventually
end up losing on move 60.
So just to define very loosely for the
assignment problem is whether you get a
positive or negative reward, so figure out what
you actually did right or did wrong to cause the
reward so you can do more of the right things
and less of the wrong things. And this is sort of
one of the things that
makes reinforcement learning hard.
And in the same way, if the helicopter crashes,
you may not know. And in the same way,
if the helicopter crashes, it may be something
you did many minutes ago that causes the
helicopter to crash. In fact, if you ever crash a
car and hopefully none of you ever get in
a car accident but when someone crashes a
car, usually the things they're doing right
before they crash is step on the brakes to slow
the car down before the impact. And
usually stepping on the brakes
does not cause a crash.
Rather it makes the crash sort of hurt less.
But so, reinforcement algorithm, you see this
pattern in that you step on the brakes, you
crash, it's not the reason you crash and it's hard
to figure out that it's not actually your
stepping on the brakes that caused the crash,
but something you did long before that.
So let me go ahead and define the formalize
the reinforcement learning problem more,
and as a preface, let me say algorithms are
applied to a broad range of problems, but
because robotics videos are easy to show in the
lecture I have a lot of them
throughout this lecture I use a bunch of robotics
for examples, but later, we'll talk about
applications of these ideas, so broader ranges of
problems as well. But the basic problem
I'm facing is sequential decision making.
We need to make many decisions and where
your decisions perhaps
have long term consequences.
So let's formalize the reinforcement learning
problem. Reinforcement learning problems
model the worlds using something called the
MDP or the Markov Decision Process
formalism. And let's see, MDP is a five tuple
I don't have enough space
well, comprising five things.
So let me say what these are.
Actually, could you please raise the screen?
I won't need the laptop anymore today.
[Inaudible] more space. Yep, go, great. Thanks.
So an MDP comprises a five tuple. The first of
these elements, s is a set of states and so
for the helicopter example, the set of states
would be the possible positions and
orientations of a helicopter. A is a set of actions.
So again, for the helicopter example,
this would be the set of all possible positions
that we could put our control sticks into. P,
s, a are state transition distributions. So for each
state and each action, this is a high
probability distribution, so sum over s prime,
Psa, s prime equals 1 and Psa s prime is
created over zero.
And state transition distributions are or state
transition probabilities work as follows. P
subscript (s, a) gives me the probability
distribution over what state I will transition to,
what state I wind up in, if I take an action a in a
state s. So this is probability distribution
over states s prime and then I get to when I take
an action a in the state s. Now I'll read
this in a second.
Gamma is the number called the discount
factor. Don't worry about this yet. I'll say what
this is in a second. And there's usually a
number strictly rated, strictly less than 1 and
rated equal to zero. And R is our reward
function, so the reward function maps from the
set of states to the real numbers and can be
positive or negative.
This is the set of real numbers.
So just to make these elements concrete,
let me give a specific example of a MDP.
Rather than talking about something
as complicated as helicopters,
I'm going to use a much smaller MDP
as the running example
for the rest of today's lecture.
We'll look at much more complicated MDPs
in subsequent lectures.
This is an example that I adapted from
a textbook by Stuart Russell and Peter Norvig
called Artificial Intelligence: A Modern
Approach (Second Edition). And this is a small
MDP that models a robot navigation task in
which if you imagine you have a robot that
lives all over the grid world where the
shaded-in cell is an obstacle,
so the robot can't go over this cell.
And so, let's see. I would really like the robot
to get to this upper right north cell, let's
say, so I'm going to associate that cell with a +1
reward, and I'd really like it to avoid
that grid cell, so I'm gonna associate that grid
cell with -1 reward.
So let's actually iterate through the five
elements of the MDP and so see what they are
for this problem. So the robot can be in any of
these eleven positions and so I have an
MDP with 11 states, and it's a set capital S
corresponding to the 11 places it could be in.
And let's say my robot in this set, highly
simplified for a logical example, can try to
move in each of the compass directions, so in
this MDP, I'll have four actions
corresponding to moving in each of the North,
South, East, West compass directions.
And let's see. Let's say that my robot's
dynamics are noisy. If you've worked in
robotics before, you know that if you command
a robot to go North, because of wheel slip or a
core design in how you act or whatever, there's
a small chance that your robot will be off
side here. So you command your robot to move
forward one meter, usually it will move
forward somewhere between like 95
centimeters or to 105 centimeters.
So in this highly simplified grid world,
I'm going to model the stochastic dynamics of
my robot as follows. I'm going to say that if
you command the robot to go north, there's
actually a 10 percent chance that it will
accidentally veer off to the left and a 10 percent
chance it will veer off to the right and only a .8
chance that it will manage to go in the
direction you commanded it. This is sort of a
crude model, wheels slipping on the model
robot. And if the robot bounces off a wall, then
it just stays where it is and nothing happens.
So let's see. Concretely, we would write this
down using the state transition probability.
So for example, let's take the state let me call
it a three comma one state and let's say
you command the robot to go north. To specify
these noisy dynamics of the robot, you
would write down state transition probabilities
for the robot as follows. You say that if
you're in the state three one and you take the
action north, your chance of getting to three
two is 0.8. If you're in the state of three one and
you take the action north, the chance of
getting to four 1 is open 1 and so on.
And so on, okay?
This last line is that if you're in the state three
one and you take the action north, the
chance of you getting to the state three three is
zero. And this is your chance of
transitioning in one-time sets of the state three
three is equal to zero. So these are the state
transition probabilities for my MDP.
Let's see. The last two elements of my five
tuple are gamma and the reward function.
Let's not worry about gamma for now, but my
reward function would be as follows, so I
really want the robot to get to the fourth I'm
using four comma three. It's indexing to the
states by using the numbers I wrote at the sides
of the grid.
So my reward for getting to the fourth three state
is +1 and my reward for getting to the
fourth 2-state is -1, and as is common practice
let's see. As is fairly common practice in
navigation tasks, for all other states, the
terminal states, I'm going to associate sort of a
small negative reward and you can think of this
as a small negative reward that charges
my robot for his battery consumption or his fuel
consumption for one move around. And
so a small negative reward like this that charges
the robot for running around randomly
tends to cause the system to compute solutions
that don't waste time and make its way to
the goal as quickly as possible because it's
charged for fuel consumption.
Okay. So, well, let me just mention, there's
actually one other complication that I'm
gonna sort of not worry about. In this specific
example, unless you're going to assume
that when the robot gets to the +1 or the -1
reward, then the world ends and so you get to
the +1 and then that's it. The world ends. There
are no more rewards positive or negative
after that, right? And so there are various ways
to model that. One way to think about that
is you may imagine there's actually a 12th state,
something that's called the zero cost
absorbing state, so that whenever you get to the
+1 or the -1, you then transition the
probability one to this 12th state and you stay in
this 12th state forever with no more
rewards. I just mention that, that when you get
to the +1 or -1, think of the problems in
finishing. The reason I do that is because it
makes some of the numbers come up nicer
and be easier to understand. It's the sort of state
where you go in where sometimes you
hear the term zero cost absorbing states. It's
another state so that when you enter that
state, there are no more rewards; you always
stay in that state forever.
All right. So let's just see how an MDP works
and it works as follows. At time 0,
your robot starts off at some state as 0 and,
depending on where you are, you get to choose
an action a0 to decide to go North, South, East,
or West. Depending on your choice, you get
to some state s1, which is going to be randomly
drawn from the state transition
distribution index by state 0 and the action you
just chose. So the next state you get to
depends well, it depends in the probabilistic
way on the previous state and the action
you just took. After you get to the state s1, you
get to choose a new action a1, and then as
a result of that, you get to some new state s2
sort of randomly from the state transition
distributions and so on. Okay?
So after your robot does this for a while, it will
have visited some sequence of states s0,
s1, s2, and so on, and to evaluate how well we
did, we'll take the reward function and
we'll apply it to the sequence of states and add
up the sum of rewards that your robot
obtained on the sequence of states it visited.
State s0 is your action, you get to s1, take an
action, you get to s2 and so on. So you keep the
reward function in the pile to every state
in the sequence and this is the sum of rewards
you obtain. Let me show you just one more
bit. You can multiply this by gamma, gamma
squared, and the next term will be
multiplied by gamma cubed and so on. And this
is called I'm going to call this the Total
Payoff for the sequence of states s0, s1, s2, and
so on that your robot visited. And so let
me also say what gamma is. See the quality
gamma is a number that's usually less than
one. It usually you think of gamma as a number
like open 99. So the effect of gamma is
that the reward you obtain at time 1 is given a
slightly smaller weight than the reward you
get at time zero. And then the reward you get at
time 2 is even a little bit smaller than the
reward you get at a previous time set and so on.
Let's see. And so if this is an economic
application, if you're in like stock market
trading with Gaussian algorithm or whatever,
this is an economic application, then your
rewards are dollars earned and lost. Then to
this kind of factor, gamma has a very natural
interpretation as the time value of money
because like a dollar today is worth slightly less
than excuse me, the dollar today is
worth slightly more than the dollar tomorrow
because the dollar in the bank can earn a
little bit of interest. And conversely, having to
pay out a dollar tomorrow is better than
having to pay out a dollar today. So in other
words, the effect of this compacted gamma
tends to weight wins or losses in the future less
than wins or losses in the immediate future
tends to weight wins and losses in the distant
future less than wins and losses in
the immediate. And so the girth of the
reinforcement learning algorithm is to choose
actions over time, to choose actions a0, a1 and
so on to try to maximize the expected
value of this total payoff. And more concretely,
what we will try to do is have our
reinforcement learning algorithms compute a
policy, which I denote by the lower case p,
which and all a policy is, a definition of a
policy is a function mapping from the states
of the actions and so it goes to kind of a policy
that tells us so for every state, what action
it recommends we take in that state. So
concretely, here is an example of a policy. And
this actually turns out to be the optimal policy
for the MDP and I'll tell you later how I
computed this. And so this is an example of a
policy. A policy is just a mapping from the
states to the actions, and so our policy tells me
when you're in this state, you should take
the left action and so on. And this particular
policy I drew out happens to be after a policy
in the sense that when you execute this policy,
this will maximize your expected value of
the total payoff. This will maximize your
expected total sum of the counter rewards.
Student:if the policy be multitle
Yeah, so can policy be over multiple states, can
it be over so can it be a function
of not only current state,
but the state I was in previously as well.
So the answer is yes. Sometimes people call
them strategies instead of policies, but usually
you're going to use policies. It actually turns
out that for an MDP, you're allowing
policies that depend on my previous states, will
not allow you to do any better. At least in
the limited context we're talking about. So in
other words, there exists a policy that only
ever lets the current state ever maximize my
expected total payoff. And this statement
won't be true for some of the richer models we
talk about later, but for now, all we need
to do is this suffices to just look at the current
states and actions.
And sometimes they use the term executable
policy to mean that I'm going to take
actions according to the policies, so I'm going
to execute the policy p. That means I'm
going to whenever some state s, I'm going to
take the action that the policy p outputs
when given the current state.
All right. So it turns out that one of the things
MDPs are very good at is all right, let's
look at our states. Say the optimal policy in this
state is to go left. There's actually this
probably wasn't very obvious. Why is it that
you have actions that go left take a longer
path there? The alternative would be to go north
and try to find a much shorter path to the
+1 state, but when you're in this state over here,
this, I guess, three comma 2 state, when
in that state over there, when you go north,
there's a .1 chance you accidentally veer off
to the right to the -1 state. And so there will be
subtle tradeoffs. Is it better to take the
longer, safer route, but the discount factor tends
to discourage that and the .02 charge per
step will tend to discourage that. Or is it better
to take a shorter, riskier route.
And so it wasn't obvious to me until
I computed it, but just to see also action
and this is one of those things
that MDP machinery is very good at making,
to make subtle tradeoffs to make these optimal.
So what I want to do next is make a few more
definitions and that will lead us to our first
algorithm for computing optimal policies and
MDPs, so finding optimal ways to act on
MDPs. Before I move on, let's check for any
questions about the MDP formalism.
Okay, cool.
So let's now talk about how we actually go
about computing optimal policy like that and
to get there, I need to define a few things. So
just as a preview of the next moves I'm
gonna take, I'm going to define something
called Vp and then I'm going to define V* and
then I'm going to define p*. And it will be a
consequence of my definitions that p* is the
optimal policy.
And so I'm going to say as I define these
things, keep in mind what is a definition and
what is a consequence of a definition.
In particular, I won't be defining p* to be the
optimal policy, but I'll define p* by a different
equation and it will be a consequence of
my definition that p* is the optimal policy.
The first one I want to define is Vp, so for any
given policy p, for any policy p, I'm going
to define the value function Vp and sometimes
I call this the value function for p.
So I want to find the value function for Vp,
the function mapping from the state's known
numbers, such that Vp(s) is the expected payoff
is the expected total payoff if you
started in the state s and execute p. So in other
words, Vp(s) is equal to the expected
value of this here, sum of this counted rewards,
the total payoff, given that you execute
the policy p and the first state in the sequence is
zero, is that state s.
I say this is slightly sloppy probabilistic
notation, so p isn't really in around the variable,
so maybe I shouldn't actually be conditioning
on p. This is sort of moderately standard
notation horror, so we use the steady sloppy
policy notation.
So as a concrete example, here's a policy
and this is not a great policy.
This is just some policy p.
It's actually a pretty bad policy that
for many states, seems to be heading
to the 1 rather than the +1.
And so the value function is
the function mapping from the states of
known numbers, so it associates each state with
a number and in this case, this is Vp. So
that's the value function for this policy.
And so you notice, for instance, that for all the
states in the bottom two rows, I guess, this
is a really bad policy that has a high chance to
take you to the -1 state and so all the
values for those states in the bottom two rows
are negative. So in this expectation, your
total payoff would be negative. And if you
execute this rather bad policy, you start in any
of the states in the bottom row, and if you start
in the top row, the total payoff would be
positive. This is not a terribly bad policy if it
stays in the topmost row.
And so given any policy, you can write down
a value function for that policy. If some of
you are still writing, I'll leave that up for a
second while I clean another couple of boards.
Okay. So the circumstances of the following,
Vp(s) is equal to well, the expected value
of R if s is zero, which is the reward you get
right away for just being in the initial state s,
plus let me write this like this I'm going to
write gamma and then R if s1 plus
gamma, R of s2 plus dot, dot, dot,
what condition of p. Okay?
So just de-parenthesize these.
This first term here, this is sometimes called the
immediate reward. This is the reward
you get right away just for starting in the state
at zero. And then the second term here,
these are sometimes called the future reward,
which is the rewards you get sort of one
time step into the future and what I want you to
note is what this term is. That term there
is really just the value function for the state s1
because this term here in parentheses, this
is really suppose I was to start in the state s1
or this is the sum of the counter rewards I
would get if I were to start in the state s1. So
my immediate reward for starting in s1
would be R (s1), then plus gamma times
additional future rewards in the future.
And so it turns out you can write VRp
recursively in terms of itself. And presume that
VRp is equal to the immediate reward plus
gamma times actually, let me write it
would just be mapped as notation s0 gets
mapped to s and s1 gets mapped to s prime
and it just makes it all right.
So value function for p to stay zero is the
immediate reward plus this current factor
gamma times and now you have Vp of s1.
Right here is Vp of s prime. But s prime is a
random variable because the next state you get
to after one time set is random and so in
particular, taking expectations, this is the sum
of all states s prime of your probability of
getting to that state times that. And just to be
clear on this notation, right, this is P
subscript (s, a) of s prime is the chance of you
getting to the state s prime when you take
the action a in state s.
And in this case, we're executing the policy p
and so this is P(s) p(s) because the action
we're going to take in state s is the action p
reverse. So this is in other words, this Ps
p(s), this distribution overstates s prime that
you would transitioned to, the one time step,
when you take the action p(s) in the state s.
So just to give this a name, this equation is
called Bellman's equations and is one of the
central equations that we'll use over and over
when we solve MDPs. Raise your hand if
this equation makes sense. Some of you didn't
raise your hands. Do you have questions?
So let's try to say this again. Actually, which of
the symbols don't make sense for those
of you that didn't raise your hands? You're
regretting not raising your hand now, aren't
you? Let's try saying this one more time and
maybe it will come clear later. So what is it?
So this equation is sort of like my value at the
current state is equal to R(s) plus gamma
times and depending on what state I get to
next, my expected total payoff from the state
s prime is Vp of s prime, whereas prime is the
state I get to after one time step. So
incurring one state as I'm going to take some
action and I get to some state that's prime
and this equation is sort of my expected total
payoff for executing the policy p
from the state s.
But s prime is random because the next state
I get to is random and well, we'll use the
next board. The chance I get to some specific
state as prime is given by we have a P
subscript (s, a), s prime, where because these
are just [inaudible] and probabilities
where the action a I chose is given by p(s)
because I'm executing the action a in the
current state s. And so when you plug this back
in, you get P subscript s R(s) as prime,
just gives me the distribution over the states in
making the transition to it in one step, and
hence, that just needs Bellman's equations.
So since Bellman's equations gives you a way
to solve for the value function for policy in
closed form. So again, the problem is suppose
I'm given a fixed policy. How do I solve
for Vp? How do I solve for the so given fixed
policy, how do I solve for this equation?
It turns out, Bellman's equation gives you
a way of doing this, so coming back to this
board, it turns out to be sort of coming back
to the previous boards, around could you
move the camera to point to this board? Okay,
cool. So going back to this board, we work
the problem's equation, this equation, right,
let's say I have a fixed policy p and I want to
solve for the value function for the policy p.
Then what this equation is just imposes a set
of linear constraints on the value function. So in
particular, this says that the value for a
given state is equal to some constant, and then
some linear function of other values.
And so you can write down one such equation
for every state in your MDP and this
imposes a set of linear constraints on what the
value function could be. And then it turns
out that by solving the resulting linear system
equations, you can then solve for the value
function Vp(s). There's a high level description.
Let me now make this concrete.
So specifically, let me take the three one state,
that state we're using as an example. So
Bellman's equation tells me that the value for p
for the three one state oh, and let's say I
have a specific policy so that p are three one
let's say it takes a North action, which is
not the ultimate action. For this policy,
Bellman's equation tells me that Vp of three one
is equal to R of the state three one, and then plus
gamma times our trans 0.8 I get to the three
two state, which translates .1 and gets to the
four one state and which times 0.1,
I will get to the two one state.
And so what I've done is I've written down
Bellman's equations for the three one state. I
hope you know what it means. It's in my low
MDP; I'm indexing the states 1, 2, 3, 4, so
this state over there where I drew the circle is
the three one state.
So for every one of my 11 states in the MDP,
I can write down an equation like this. This
stands just for one state. And you notice that if
I'm trying to solve for the values, so these
are the unknowns, then I will have 11 variables
because I'm trying to solve for the value
function for each of my 11 states, and I will
have 11 constraints because I can write down
11 equations of this form, one such equation for
each one of my states.
So if you do this, if you write down this sort of
equation for every one of your states and
then do these, you have your set of linear
equations with 11 unknowns and 11 variables
excuse me, 11 constraints or 11 equations with
11 unknowns, and so you can solve that
linear system of equations to get an explicit
solution for Vp.
So if you have n states, you
end up with n equations and n unknowns and
solve that to get the values for all of your states.
Okay, cool. So actually, could you
just raise your hand if this made sense? Cool.
All right, so that was the value function for
specific policy and how to solve for it. Let me
define one more thing. So the optimal value
function when defined as V*(s) equals max
over all policies p of Vp(s). So in other words,
for any given state s,
the optimal value
function says suppose I take a max over all
possible policies p, what is the best possible
expected some of the counter rewards that
I can expect to get?
Or what is my optimal
expected total payoff for starting at state s,
so taking a max over all
possible control policies p.
So it turns out that there's a version of
Bellman's equations for V* as well and so this
is also called Bellman's equations for V* rather
than for Vp and I'll just write that down.
So this says that the optimal payoff you can
get from the state s is equal to
so I'll first write some multi here, so let's see. Just for
starting off in the state s, you're going to
get your immediate R(s) and then depending on
what action a you take your expected
total payoff will be given by this. So if I take an
action a in some state s, then with
probability given by P subscript (s; a) of s
prime, by this probability our transition of state
s prime, and when we get to the state s prime,
I'll expect my total payoff from there to be
given by V*(s) prime because I'm now starting
to use the s prime.
So the only thing in this equation I need to fill
in is where is the action a, so in order to
actually obtain the optimal expected payoff,
and to actually obtain the maximum or the
optimal expected total payoff, what you should
choose here is the max over our actions a,
choose your action a that maximizes the
expected value of your total payoffs as well.
So it just makes sense. There's a version of
Bellman's equations for V* rather than Vp
and I'll just say it again. It says that my optimal
expected total payoff is my immediate
reward plus, and then the best action it can
choose, the max over all actions a of my
expected future payoff.
And these also lead to my definition of p*,
which is let's say I'm in some state s and I
want to know what action to choose. Well, if
I'm in some state s, I'm gonna get here an
immediate R(s) anyway, so what's the best
action for me to choose is whatever action
will enable me to maximize the second term, as
well as if my robot is in some state s and
it wants to know what action to choose, I want
to choose the action that will maximize
my expected total payoff and so p*(s) is going
to define as R(max) over actions a of this
same thing.
I could also put the gamma there, but gamma
is just a positive. Gamma is almost always
positive, so I just drop that because it's just a
constant scale you go through
and doesn't affect the R(max).
And so, the consequence of this definition is
that p* is actually the optimal policy because
p* will maximize my expected total payoffs.
Cool. Any questions at this point?
Cool. So what I'd like to do now is
talk about how algorithms actually
compute high start, compute the optimal policy.
I should write down a little bit more
before I do that, but notice that
if I can compute V*, if I can compute the
optimal value function, then I can plug it into
this equation and then I'll be done.
So if I can compute V*, then you are using this
definition for p* and can compute
the optimal policy.
So my strategy for computing the optimal
policy will be to compute V* and then plug it
into this equation and that will give me the
optimal policy p*. So my goal, my next goal,
will really be to compute V*.
But the definition of V* here doesn't lead to a
nice algorithm for computing it because
let's see so I know how to compute Vp for
any given policy p by solving that linear
system equation, but there's an exponentially
large number of policies, so you get 11
states and four actions and what the number of
policies is froze to the par of 11. This is of
a huge space of possible policies and so I can't
actually exhaust the union of all policies
and then take a max on V*.
So I should write down some other things first,
just to ground the notations, but what I'll
do is eventually come up with an algorithm for
computing V*, the optimal value function
and then we'll plug them into this and that will
give us the optimal policy p*.
And so I'll write down the algorithm in a
second, but just to ground the notation, well
yeah, let's skip that. Let's just talk about the
algorithm. So this is an algorithm called
value iteration and it makes use of Bellman's
equations for the optimal policy to compute
V*. So here's the algorithm. Okay, and that's
the entirety of the algorithm and oh, you
repeat the step, I guess.
You repeatedly do this step.
So just to be concrete,
let's say in my MDP of
11 states, the first step is initialize V(s)
equals zero, so what that means is
I create an array in computer
implementation, create an array of 11 elements
and say set all of them to zero.
Says I can initialize into anything.
It doesn't really matter.
And now what I'm going to do is I'll take
Bellman's equations and we'll keep on taking
the right hand side of Bellman's equations and
overwriting and start copying down the
left hand side. So we'll essentially iteratively
try to make Bellman's equations hold true
for the numbers V(s) that are stored along the
way. So V(s) here is in the array of 11
elements and I'm going to repeatedly compute
the right hand side and copy that onto V(s).
And it turns out that when you do this, this will
make V(s) converge to V*(s), so it may
be of no surprise because we know V
V*(s) set inside Bellman's equations.
Just to tell you, some of these ideas that they
get more than the problem says, so I won't
prove the conversions of this algorithm. Some
implementation details, it turns out there's
two ways you can do this update. One is when I
say for every state s that has performed
this update, one way you can do this is for
every state s, you can compute the right hand
side and then you can simultaneously overwrite
the left hand side for every state s. And
so if you do that, that's called a sequence
update. Right and sequence [inaudible],
so update all the states s simultaneously.
And if you do that, it's sometimes written as
follows. If you do synchronous update, then
it's as if you have some value function, you're
at the Ith iteration or Tth iteration of the
algorithm and then you're going to compute
some function of your entire value function,
and then you get to set your value function to
your new version, so simultaneously update
all 11 values in your s space value function.
So it's sometimes written like this. My B here
is called the Bellman backup operator, so
the synchronized valuation you sort of take the
value function, you apply the Bellman
backup operator to it and then the Bellman
backup operator just means computing the
right hand side of this for all the states and
you've overwritten your entire value function.
The only way of performing these updates is
asynchronous updates, which is where you
update the states one at a time. So you go
through the states in some fixed order, so
would update V(s) for state No. 1 and then I
would like to update V(s) for state No. 2,
then state No. 3, and so on. And when I'm
updating V(s) for state No. 5, if V(s) prime, if
I end up using the values for states 1, 2, 3, and
4 on the right hand side, then I'd use my
recently updated values on the right hand side.
So as you update sequentially, when
you're updating in the fifth state, you'd be
using values, new values, for states 1, 2, 3, and
4. And that's called an asynchronous update.
Other versions will cause V(s) conversion to be
(s). In synchronized updates, it makes
them just a tiny little bit faster but they'll gonna find and
then it turns out the analysis of value
iterations synchronous updates are also easier
to analyze and that just matters [inaudible].
Asynchronous has been just a little bit faster.
So when you run this algorithm on the MDP
I forgot to say all these values were
computed with gamma equals open 99 and
actually, Roger Gross, who's a, I guess,
master [inaudible] helped me with computing
some of these numbers. So you compute it.
That way you run value relation on this MDP.
The numbers you get for V* are as
follows: .86, .90 again, the numbers sort of
don't matter that much, but just take a look
at it and make sure it intuitively makes sense.
And then when you plug those in to the formula
for computing, that I wrote down earlier,
for computing p* as a function of V*, then
well, I drew this previously, but here's the
optimal policy p*.
And so, just to summarize, the process is run
value iteration to compute V*, so this would
be this table of numbers, and then I use my
form of p* to compute the optimal policy,
which is this policy in this case.
Now, to be just completely concrete, let's look
at that three one state again. Is it better to
go left or is it better to go north? So let me just
illustrate why I'd rather go left than north.
In the form of the p*, if I go west, then sum
over s prime, P(s, a) s prime, P*(sp), this
would be well, let me just write this down.
Right, if I go north, then it would be because
of that. I wrote it down really quickly, so it's
messy writing. The way I got these numbers
is suppose I'm in this state, in this three one
state. If I choose to go west and with chance
.8, I get to .75 to this table 75. With chance .
1, I veer off and get to the .69, then at
chance .1, I go south and I bounce off the wall
and I stay where I am.
So that's why my expected future payoff for
going west is .8 times .75, plus .1 times .69,
plus .1 times .71, the last .71 being if I bounce
off the wall to the south and then seeing
where I am, that gives you .740.
You can then repeat the same process to
estimate your expected total payoff if you go
north, so if you do that, with a .8 chance, you
end up going north, so you get .69. With a
.1 chance, you end up here and .1 chance you
end up there. This map leads mentally to
that expression and compute the expectation,
you get .676. And so your total payoff is
higher if you go west your expected total
payoff is higher if you go west than if you go
north. And that's why the optimal action in this
state is to go west.
So that was value iteration. It turns out there are
two sort of standard algorithms for
computing optimal policies in MDPs. Value
iteration is one. As soon as you finish the
writing. So value iteration is one and the other
sort of standard algorithm for computing
optimal policies in MDPs is called policy
iteration. And let me –
I'm just going to write this down.
In policy iteration, we initialize the policy p
randomly, so it doesn't matter. It can be the
policy that always goes north or the policy that
takes actions random or whatever. And
then we'll repeatedly do the following. Okay,
so that's the algorithm.
So the algorithm has two steps.
In the first step, we solve.
We take the current policy p
and we solve Bellman's equations
to obtain Vp.
So remember, earlier I said if you have a
fixed policy p, then yeah,
Bellman's equation defines this system
of linear equations with 11 unknowns
and 11 linear constraints.
And so you solve that linear system equation
so you get the value function for your current
policy p, and by this notation, I mean just let
V be the value function for policy p.
Then the second step is you update the policy.
In other words, you pretend that your
current guess V from the value function is
indeed the optimal value function and you let
p(s) be equal to that out max formula, so as to
update your policy p.
And so it turns out that if you do this, then V
will converge to V* and p will converge to
p*, and so this is another way to find the
optimal policy for MDP.
In terms of tradeoffs, it turns out that
let's see in policy iteration,
the computationally expensive step is this one.
You need to solve this linear system of
equations. You have n equations and
n unknowns, if you have n states. And so
if you have a problem with a reasonably
few number of states, if you have a problem
with like 11 states, you can solve the linear
system equations fairly efficiently, and so
policy iteration tends to work extremely well
for problems with smallish numbers of states
where you can actually solve those linear
systems of equations efficiently.
So if you have a thousand states, anything less
than that, you can solve a system of a
thousand equations very efficiently, so policy
iteration will often work fine. If you have
an MDP with an enormous number of states, so
we'll actually often see MDPs with tens
of thousands or hundreds of thousands or
millions or tens of millions of states. If you
have a problem with 10 million states and you
try to apply policy iteration, then this step
requires solving the linear system of 10 million
equations and this would be
computationally expensive. And so for these
really, really large MDPs, I tend to use
value iteration.
Let's see. Any questions about this?
Student:So this is a convex function where
that it could be good in local
optimization scheme.
Ah, yes, you're right. That's a good question: Is
this a convex function? It actually turns out
that there is a way to pose a problem
of solving for V* as a convex
optimization problem, as a linear program.
For instance, I can break down the
solution you write down V* as a solution, so
linear would be the only problem you can
solve. Policy iteration converges as gamma T
conversion. We're not just stuck with local
optimal, but the proof of the conversions of
policy iteration sort of uses somewhat
different principles in convex optimization. At
least the versions as far as I can see, yeah.
You could probably relate this back to convex
optimization, but not understand the
principle of why this often converges.
The proof is not that difficult, but it is also sort
of longer than I want to go over in this
class. Yeah, that was a good point. Cool.
Actually, any questions for any of these?
Okay, so we now have two algorithms for
solving MDP. There's a given, the five tuple,
given the set of states, the set of actions, the
state transition properties, the discount
factor, and the reward function, you can now
apply policy iteration or value iteration to
compute the optimal policy for the MDP.
The last thing I want to talk about is what if you
don't know the state transition
probabilities, and sometimes you won't know
the reward function R as well, but let's
leave that aside. And so for example, let's say
you're trying to fly a helicopter and you
don't really know in advance what state your
helicopter will transition to and take an
action in a certain state, because helicopter
dynamics are kind of noisy. You sort of often
don't really know what state you end up in.
So the standard thing to do, or one standard
thing to do, is then to try to estimate the state
transition probabilities from data. Let me just
write this out. It turns out that the MDP has
its 5 tuple, right? S, A; you have the transition
probabilities, gamma, and R. S and A you
almost always know. The state space is sort of
up to you to define. What's the state space
at the very bottom, factor you're trying to
control, whatever. Actions is, again, just one of
your actions. Usually, we almost always know
these. Gamma, the discount factor is
something you choose depending on how much
you want to trade off current versus
future rewards. The reward function you
usually know. There are some exceptional
cases. Usually, you come up with a reward
function and so you usually know what the
reward function is. Sometimes you don't,
but let's just leave that aside for now
and the most common thing for you
to have to learn are the state transition
probabilities. So we'll just talk about
how to learn that. So when you don't
know state transition probabilities,
the most common thing to do is just estimate it
from data. So what I mean is imagine some
robot maybe it's a robot roaming around the
hallway, like in that grid example you
would then have the robot just take actions in
the MDP and you would then estimate your
state transition probabilities P subscript (s, a) s
prime to be pretty much exactly what
you'd expect it to be.
This would be the number of times you took
action a in state s and you got to s prime,
divided by the number of times you took action
a in state s. Okay? So the estimate of this
is just all the times you took the action a in the
state s, what's the fraction of times you
actually got to the state s prime. It's pretty
much exactly what you expect it to be. Or you
can or in case you've never actually tried
action a in state s, so if this turns out to be 0
over 0, you can then have some default estimate
for those vector uniform distribution
over all states, this reasonable default.
And so, putting it all together and by the way,
it turns out in reinforcement learning, in
most of the earlier parts of this class where we
did supervised learning, I sort of talked
about the logistic regression algorithm, so it
does the algorithm and most
implementations of logistic regression like a
fairly standard way to do logistic
regression were SVMs or faster analysis or
whatever. It turns out in reinforcement
learning there's more of a mix and match sense,
I guess, so there are often different
pieces of different algorithms you can choose to
use. So in some of the algorithms I write
down, there's sort of more than one way to do it
and I'm sort of giving specific examples,
but if you're faced with an AI problem, some of
you in control of robots, you want to
plug in value iteration here instead of policy
iteration. You want to do something slightly
different than one of the specific things I wrote
down. That's actually fairly common, so
just in reinforcement learning, there's sort of
other major ways to apply different
algorithms and mix and match different
algorithms. And this will come up again in the
weekly lectures. So just putting the things I said
together, here would be a now this
would be an example of how you might
estimate the state transition probabilities in a
MDP and find the policy for it. So you might
repeatedly do the following. Let's see. Take
actions using some policy p to get experience in
the MDP, meaning that just execute the
policy p observed state transitions. Based on
the data you get, you then update estimates
of your state transition probabilities P subscript
(s, a) based on the experience of the
observations you just got. Then you might solve
Bellman's equations using value
iterations, which I'm abbreviating to VI, and by
Bellman's equations, I mean Bellman's
equations for V*, not for Vp. Solve Bellman's
equations using value iteration to get an
estimate for P* and then you update your policy
by events equals [inaudible].
And now you have a new policy so you can
then go back and execute this policy for a bit
more of the MDPs to get some more
observations of state transitions, get the noisy ones in MDP,
use that update to estimate your
state transition probabilities again; use value
iteration or policy iteration to solve for
[inaudible] the value function, get a new policy
and so on. Okay? And it turns out when you do
this, I actually wrote down value iteration
for a reason. It turns out in the third step of the
algorithm, if you're using value iteration
rather than policy iteration, to initialize value
iteration, if you use your solution from the
previous used algorithm, right, then that's a
very good initialization condition and this
will tend to converge much more quickly
because value iteration tries to solve for V(s)
for every state s. It tries to estimate V*(s) and
the s from the * in V(s) and so if you're
looking through this and you initialize your
value iteration algorithm using the values you
have from the previous round through this, then
that will often make this converge faster.
But again, this is again here, you can also adjust
a small part in policy iteration in here as
well and whatever, and this is a fairly typical
example of how you would solve a policy,
correct digits and then key in and try to find a
good policy for a problem for which you
did not know the state transition probabilities in
advance.
Cool. Questions about this?
Cool. So that sure was exciting.
This is like our first two MDP algorithms
in just one lecture. All right,
Let's close for today, thanks