So what I want to do today in this
lecture is talk a little bit more about learning theory.
In particular, I'll talk about VC dimension
and building on the issues of bias variance
tradeoffs of under fitting and over fitting;
that we've been seeing in the previous lecture,
and then we'll see in this one.
I then want to talk about model selection
algorithms for automatically making
decisions for this bias variance tradeoff,
that we started to talk about in the previous lecture.
And depending on how much time,
I actually may not
get to Bayesian, [inaudible].
But if I don't get to this today,
I'll get to this in next week's lecture.
To recap: the result we proved
at the previous lecture
was that if you have a finite hypothesis class
if h is a set of k hypotheses,
and suppose you have some fixed parameters,
gamma and delta, then in order to guarantee that this holds
we're probability at least one minus delta.
It suffices that n is greater and equal to that; okay?
And using big-O notations,
just learning dropped constants,
I can also write this as that; okay?
So just to quickly remind you of what all
of the notation means,
we talked about empirical risk minimization,
which was the simplified modern
machine learning that has a hypothesis class of script h.
And what the empirical risk minimization-learning
algorithm does is it just chooses the hypothesis
that attains the smallest error on the training set.
And so this symbol, epsilon,
just denoted generalization error; right?
This is the probability of a hypothesis h
[inaudible] misclassifying a new
example drawn from the same
distribution as the training set.
And so this says that in order to guarantee that the
generalization error of the hypothesis h [inaudible] output
by empirical risk minimization that this is less and equal
to the best possible generalization error
use it in your hypothesis class plus two times gamma
two times this error threshold.
We want to guarantee that this holds a
probability at least one minus delta.
We show that it suffices for your training set size m
to be greater than equal to this; okay?
One over two gamma square log two k over delta;
where again, k is the size of your hypothesis class.
And so this is some complexity result
because it gives us a bound in the number of
training examples we need in order to
give a guarantee on something on the error; okay?
So this is a sample complexity result.
So what I want to do now is
take this result, and try to generalize it
to the case of infinite hypothesis classes.
So here, we said that the set script h is
sort of just k specific functions,
when you want to use a model
like logistic regression,
which is actually parameterized by real numbers.
So I'm actually first going to give an argument
that's sort of formally broken
just sort of technically somewhat broken,
but conveys useful intuition.
And then I'll give the more correct argument,
but without proving.
It's as if, full proof is somewhat involved.
So here's a somewhat broken argument.
Let's say I want to apply this
result analyzing logistic regression.
So let's say your hypothesis class is
because of all linear division boundaries; right?
So say script h is parameterized by d real numbers; okay?
So for example, if you're applying logistic
regression with over [inaudible],
then d would be endless
one with logistic regression
to find the linear position boundary,
parameterized by endless one real numbers.
When you think about how your hypothesis class
is really represented in a computer
computers use zero one bits to represent real numbers.
And so if you use like a normal standard computer,
it normally will represent real numbers
by what's called double position floating point numbers.
And what that means is that each real number is
represented by or a 64-bit representation; right?
So really you know what floating point is in a computer.
So a 64-bit floating point is what
almost all of us use routinely.
And so this parameterized by d real numbers,
that's really as if it's parameterized by 64 times d bits.
Computers can't represent real numbers.
They only represent used to speed things.
And so the size of your hypothesis
class in your computer representation
you have 64 times d bits that you can flip.
And so the number of possible values for your 62 to 64
d bits is really just to the power of 64 d; okay?
Because that's the number of ways
you can flip the 64 d bits.
And so this is why it's important that
we that we had log k there; right?
So k is therefore, to the 64 d.
And if I plug it into this equation over here,
what you find is that in order to get this sort of guarantee,
it suffices that m is great and equal to on the order of
one of the gamma square log
it's just a 64 d over delta, which is that; okay?
So just to be clear,
in order to guarantee that there's only one,
instead of the same complexity result as we had before –so
the question is: suppose, you want a guarantee that a
hypotheses returned by empirical risk minimization will
have a generalization error that's within two gamma or the
best hypotheses in your hypotheses class.
Then what this result suggests is that,
you know, in order to give that
sort of error bound guarantee,
it suffices that m is greater and equal to this.
In other words,
that your number of training examples has to be on the
order of d over gamma square; 10, 12, 1 over delta. Okay?
And the intuition that this conveys is actually,
roughly right.
This says,
that the number of training examples
you need is roughly linear in the number of parameters
of your hypothesis class.
That m has [inaudible] on the order of something linear,
That intuition is actually, roughly right.
I'll say more about this later.
This result is clearly, slightly broken,
in the sense that it relies on a 64-bit
representation of 14-point numbers.
So let me actually go ahead and outline the
"right way" to show this more formally; all right?
And it turns out the "right way" to
show this more formally involves a much longer
because the proof is extremely involved,
so I'm just actually going to state the result,
and not prove it.
Farther proof be a source of learning theory balance,
infinite hypothesis classes.
This definition
given a set of d points,
we say, a hypothesis class h shatters the set s,
if h can realize
any labeling on it; okay?
And what I mean by realizing any labeling on it
the informal way of thinking about this is:
if a hypothesis class has shattered the set s,
what that means is that I can take these d points,
and I can associate these d points with
any caught set of labels y; right?
So choose any set of labeling y for each of these d points.
And if your hypothesis class shatters s,
then that means that there will be a hypothesis
that labels those d examples perfectly; okay?
That's what shattering means.
So let me just illustrate those in an example.
So let's say h is the class of
all linear classifiers into e,
and let's say that s is this [inaudible]
comprising two points; okay?
So there are four possible labelings that
computes with these two points.
You can choose to label both positive;
one positive, one negative, one negative, one positive
or you can label both of them negative.
And if the hypothesis class h classed
all linear classifiers into the then,
for each of these training sets,
I can sort of find a linear classifier that
attains zero training error on each of these.
Then on all possible labelings
of this set of two points.
And so I'll say that the hypothesis class script
h shatters this set s of two points; okay?
One more example show you a larger example.
Suppose my set s is now this set of three points; right?
Then, I now have eight possible
labelings for these three points; okay?
And so for these three points,
I now have eight possible labelings.
And once again, I can for each of these labelings,
I can find the hypothesis in the
hypothesis class that labels these examples correctly.
And so once again, I see that by definition, say,
that my hypothesis class also shatters this set s.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):And then that that terminology
h can realize any labeling on s.
That's obviously [inaudible].
Give it any set of labels and
you can find a hypothesis that
perfectly separates the positive
and negative examples; okay?
So how about this set?
Suppose s is now this set of four points, then,
you know, there are lots of labels.
There are now 16 labelings we can choose on this;
right?That's one for instance, and this is another one;
right? And so I can realize some labelings. But there's no
linear division boundary that can realize this labeling, and
so h does not shatter this set of four points; okay?
And I'm not really going to prove it here,
but it turns out that you can show that in two dimensions,
there is no set of four points that
the class of all linear classifiers can shatter; okay?
So here's another definition.
When I say that the well, it's called the VC dimension.
These two people,
Vapnik and Chervonenkis
so given a hypothesis class,
the Vapnik and Chervonenkis dimension of h,
which we usually write as VC of script h, is the size of
the larger set that is shattered by this set by h.
And if a hypothesis class can shatter
arbitrarily large sets,
then the VC dimension is infinite.
So just as a kind of good example:
if h is the class of all linear classifiers into d,
then the VC dimension of the set is equal to three
because we saw just now that there is a size of
there was a set s of size three that it could shatter,
and I don't really prove it.
But it turns out there is no
sets of size four that it can shatter.
And therefore, the VC dimension of this is three. Yeah?
Student:But there are sets of sizethree that
cannot shatter; right? [Inaudible] was your point.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes, absolutely.
So it turns out that if I choose a set like this
it's actually set s,
then there are labelings on this they cannot realize.
And so, h cannot shatter this set.
But that's okay because right
there definitely is there exists some
other set of size three being shattered.
So the VC dimension is three.
And then there is no set of size four
that can shatter. Yeah?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Not according to this definition
No. Right. So again, let's see,
I can choose my set s to be to be a
set of three points that are all over lapping.
Three points in exactly the same place.
And clearly, I can't shatter this set,
but that's okay.
And I can't shatter this set, either,
but that's okay because there are some
other sets of size three that I can shatter.
And it turns out this result holds true into the
more generally, in any dimensions
the VC dimension of the class of linear classifiers
in any dimensions is equal to n plus one. Okay?
So this is in [inaudible],
and if you have linear classifiers over
in any dimensional feature space,
the VC dimension in any dimensions;
whereas, n d is equal to n plus one.
So maybe you wanna write it down:
what is arguably the best-known
result in all of learning theory, I guess; which is that.
Let a hypothesis class be given,
and let the VC dimension of h be equal to d.
Then we're in probability of one minus delta.
We have that
the formula on the right looks a bit complicated,
but don't worry about it.
I'll point out the essential aspects of it later.
But the key to this result is that
if you have a hypothesis class with VC dimension d,
and now this can be an infinite hypothesis class,
what Vapnik and Chervonenkis show is that
we're probability of at least one minus delta.
You enjoy this sort of uniform conversions results; okay?
We have that for all hypotheses h
that for all the hypotheses in your hypothesis class,
you have that the generalization error
of h minus the training error of h.
So the difference between these two things
is bounded above by some
complicated formula like this; okay?
And thus, with probably one minus delta.
We also have that
have the same thing; okay?
And going from this step to this step; right?
Going from this step to this step is actually
something that you saw yourself;
that we actually proved earlier.
Because you remember,
in the previous lecture we proved
that if you have uniform conversions,
then that implies that
it appears actually that we showed that
if generalization error and
training error are close to each other;
within gamma of each other,
then the generalization error of
the hypotheses you pick will be
within two gamma times the best generalization error.
So this is really generalization error of h
[inaudible] best possible generalization
error plus two times gamma.
And just the two constants in front here
that I've absorbed into the big-O notation.
So that formula is slightly more complicated.
Let me just rewrite this as a corollary,
which is that in order to guarantee that this holds,
we're probability of one minus delta.
We're probably at least one minus delta,
I should say. It suffices that I'm gonna write this this
way: I'm gonna write m equals big-O of d, and I'm going
to put gamma and delta in as a subscript error to denote
that. Let's see,
if we treat gamma and delta as constants,
so they allow me to absorb turns
that depend on gamma and
delta into the big-O notation,
then in order to guarantee this holds,
it suffices that m is on the order
of the VC dimension and
hypotheses class; okay?
So let's see.
So what we conclude from this is that
if you have a learning algorithm that tries to
for empirical risk minimization algorithms
in other words, less formally,
for learning algorithms,
they try to minimize training error.
The intuition to take away from this is that
the number of training examples you need
is therefore, roughly, linear in the VC dimension
of the hypotheses class.
And more formally,
this shows that sample complexity is upper
bounded by the VC dimension;
okay? It turns out that
for most reasonable hypothesis classes,
it turns out that the VC dimension is sort of very similar,
I guess, to the number of parameters you model.
So for example,
you have model and logistic regression
linear classification.
In any dimensions logistic regression
in any dimensions is endless one parameters.
And the VC dimension of which is the
of class of linear classifiers is always the endless one.
So it turns out that
for most reasonable hypothesis classes,
the VC dimension is usually
linear in the number of parameters of your model.
Wherein, is most sense of low other polynomial;
in the number of parameters of your model.
And so this the takeaway intuition from this is that the
number of training examples you need to fit in those
models is going to be let's say, roughly, linear in the
number of parameters in your model; okay?
There are some somewhat strange examples
where what I just said is not true.
There are some strange examples
where you have very few parameters,
but the VC dimension is enormous.
But I actually know of
all of the examples I know
of that fall into that regime are
somewhat strange and degenerate.
So somewhat unusual,
and not the source
of not learning algorithms you usually use.
Let's see, just other things.
It turns out that
so this result shows the sample complexity
is upper bounded by VC dimension.
But if you have a number of training examples that
are on the order of the VC dimension,
then you find
it turns out that in the worse case
some complexity is also lower bounded by VC dimension.
And what that means is that if
you have a perfectly nasty learning problem,
say, then if the number of training examples
you have is less than on the order of the VC dimension;
then it is not possible to prove this bound.
So I guess in the worse case,
sample complexity in the
number of training examples you need is upper
bounded and lower bounded by the VC dimension.
Let's see, questions about this?
Student:Does the proof of this assume any
sort of finites of, like, finite [inaudible] like you
have to just [inaudible] real numbers and [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
The proof is not, no.
I've actually stated the entirety of the theorem.
This is true. It turns out in the proof
well, somewhere, regardless of the proof there's
a step reconstruction called an epsilon net,
which is a very clever [inaudible].
It' sort of in regardless of the proof,
it is not an assumption that you need.
In someway that sort of proof that's one-step that uses
a very clever [inaudible] to prove this.
But that's not needed;
it's an assumption.
I'd like to say,
back when I was a Ph.D. student,
when I was working through this proof,
there was sort of a solid week where I would wake up,
and go to the office at 9:00 a.m.
Then I'd start reading the book that led up to this proof.
And then I'd read from 9:00 a.m. to 6:00 p.m.
And then I'd go home, and then the next day,
I'd pick up where I left off.
And it sort of took me a whole week that way,
to understand this proof,
so I thought I would inflict that on you.
Just to tie a couple of loose ends:
what I'm about to do is,
I'm about to just mention a few things that will maybe,
feel a little bit like random facts.
But I'm just gonna tie up just a couple of loose ends.
And so let's see,
it turns out that
just so it will be more strong with you
so this bound was proved for an algorithm
that uses empirical risk minimization,
for an algorithm that minimizes 0-1 training error.
So one question that some of you ask is
how about support vector machines; right?
How come SVM's don't over fit?
And in the sequel of
remember our discussion on support
vector machines said that you use kernels,
and map the features in infinite dimensional feature space.
And so it seems like the VC dimension should be infinite;
n plus one and n is infinite.
So it turns out that the
class of linear separators with large
margin actually has low VC dimension.
I wanna say this very quickly, and informally.
It's actually, not very important for you
to understand the details,
but I'm going to say it very informally.
It turns out that I will give you a set of points.
And if I ask you to consider only
the course of lines that separate these points
of a large margin [inaudible],
so my hypothesis class will comprise
only the linear position boundaries that
separate the points of a large margin.
Say with a margin, at least gamma; okay.
And so I won't allow a point that comes closer.
Like, I won't allow that line because it
comes too close to one of my points.
It turns out that if I consider my data
points all lie within some sphere of radius r,
and if I consider only the course of
linear separators is separate to data with a
margin of at least gamma,
then the VC dimension of this course is less than or equal
to r squared over four gamma squared plus one; okay?
So this funny symbol here, that just means rounding up.
This is a ceiling symbol;
it means rounding up x.
And it turns out you prove
and there are some strange things about this
result that I'm deliberately not gonna to talk about
but turns they can prove that the VC dimension of the class
of linear classifiers with large margins is actually bounded
The surprising thing about this is that
this is the bound on VC dimension that
has no dependents on the dimension of the points x.
So in other words,
your data points x combine an infinite dimensional space,
but so long as you restrict attention to
the class of your separators
with large margin,
the VC dimension is bounded.
And so in trying to find a
large margin separator
in trying to find the line that separates your
positive and your negative
examples with large margin,
it turns out therefore,
that the support vector machine is automatically trying
to find a hypothesis class with small VC dimension.
And therefore, it does not over fit. Alex?
Student:What is the [inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):It is actually defined the same
way as finite dimensional spaces.
So you know, suppose you have infinite
actually, these are constantly infinite dimensional vectors;
not [inaudible] to the infinite dimensional vectors.
Normally, the 2 to 1 squared is equal to some equals
110 xi squared,
so if x is infinite dimensional,
you just appoint it like that. [Inaudible]. [Crosstalk]
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Now, say that again.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes. Although, I assume that
this is bounded by r.
Student:Oh.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):It's a yeah so this
insures that conversions.
So just something people sometimes wonder about.
And last, the actually tie empirical risk minimization
back a little more strongly to the source of
algorithms we've talked about.
It turns out that so the theory was about,
and so far, was really for empirical risk minimization.
So that view's so we focus on just one training example.
Let me draw a function, you know, a zero here
jumps to one, and it looks like that.
And so this for once, this training example,
this may be indicator h where x axis is
z equals theta transpose x; okay?
But one training example
your training example will be positive or negative.
And depending on what the value of this data transpose x
is, you either get it right or wrong.
And so you know,
I guess if your training example
if you have a positive example,
then when z is positive, you get it right.
Suppose you have a negative example,
so y equals 0; right?
Then if z, which is data transpose x
if this is positive, then you will get this example wrong;
whereas, if z is negative then you'd get this example right.
And so this is a part of indicator h
subscript x not equals y; okay?
You know, it's equal to g of data transpose x; okay?
And so it turns out that
so what you really like to do is choose
parameters data so as to minimize this step function; right?
You'd like to choose parameters data,
so that you end up with a correct classification on
setting your training example,
and so you'd like indicator h of x not equal y.
You'd like this indicator function to be 0.
It turns out this
step function is clearly a non-convex function.
And so it turns out that just the linear classifiers
minimizing the training error is an empty heart problem.
It turns out that both logistic regression,
and support vector machines can be viewed as
using a convex approximation for this problem.
And in particular and draw a function like that
it turns out that logistic regression
is trying to maximize likelihood.
And so it's tying to minimize the
minus of the logged likelihood.
And if you plot the minus
of the logged likelihood,
it actually turns out it'll be a function that looks like this.
And this line that I just drew,
you can think of it as a rough
approximation to this step function;
which is maybe what you're really trying to minimize,
so you want to minimize training error.
So you can actually think of logistic regression
as trying to approximate empirical risk minimization.
Where instead of using this step function,
which is non-convex,
and gives you a hard optimization problem,
it uses this line above this curve above.
So approximate it,
so you have a convex optimization problem
you can find the maximum likelihood
it's in the parameters for logistic regression.
And it turns out,
support vector machine also
can be viewed as approximated dysfunction
to only a little bit different
let's see, support vector machine turns out,
can be viewed as trying to approximate this
step function two over different
approximation that's linear,
and then that sort of linear that
our results goes this [inaudible] there,
and then it goes up as a linear function there.
And that's that is called the hinge class.
And so you can think of logistic regression
and the support vector machine
as different approximations to try to minimize
this step function; okay?
And that's why I guess, all the theory we developed
even though SVM's and logistic regression
aren't exactly due to empirical risk minimization,
the theory we develop often gives the completely
appropriate intuitions for SVM's,
and logistic regression; okay.
So that was the last of the loose ends.
And if you didn't get this, don't worry too much about it.
It's a high-level message.
It's just that SVM's and logistic regression
are reasonable to think of as approximations
empirical risk minimization algorithms.
What I want to do next is move
on to talk about model selection.
Before I do that, let me just check
for questions about this. Okay. Cool.
Okay. So in the theory that we
started to develop in the previous lecture,
and that we sort of wrapped up
with a discussion on VC dimension,
we saw that there's
often a trade-off
between bias and variance.
And in particular, so it is important not to choose
a hypothesis that's either too simple or too complex.
So if your data has sort of a quadratic structure to it,
then if you choose a linear function to
try to approximate it, then you would under fit.
So you have a hypothesis with high bias.
And conversely, we choose a
hypothesis that's too complex,
and you have high variance.
And you'll also fail to fit.
Then you would over fit the data,
and you'd also fail to generalize well.
So model selection algorithms provide
a class of methods to automatically trade
make these tradeoffs between bias
and variance; right?
So remember the cartoon I drew
last time of generalization error?
I drew this last time.
Where on the x-axis was model complexity,
meaning the number of
the degree of the polynomial;
the [inaudible] regression function or whatever.
And if you have too simple a model,
you have high generalization error,
those under fitting.
And you if have too complex a model,
like 15 or 14-degree polynomial to five data points,
then you also have high generalization error,
and you're over fitting.
So what I wanna do now is actually just talk about
model selection in the abstract; all right?
well, I'll run the example of
Some examples of model selection problems will include –
let's say you're trying to choose
the degree of a polynomial; right?
What degree polynomial do you want to choose?
Another example of a model selection problem would be i
if you're trying to choose the parameter [inaudible],
which was the bandwidth parameter
in locally awaited linear regression or
in some sort of local way to regression.
Yet, another model selection problem is
if you're trying to choose the parameter c
[inaudible] and as the [inaudible]; right?
And so one known soft margin is the
we had this
optimization objective; right?
And the parameter c controls the tradeoff between
how much you want to set for your example.
So a large margin versus how much
you want to penalize in this class [inaudible] example.
So these are three specific examples
of model selection problems.
And let's come up with a method
for semantically choosing them.
Let's say you have some finite set of models,
and let's write these as m1, m2, m3, and so on.
For example, this may be
the linear classifier
or this may be the quadratic classifier,
and so on; okay?
Or this may also be you may
also take the bandwidth parameter [inaudible]
and discretize it into a range of values,
and you're trying to choose from the most
discrete of the values.
So let's talk about how you would
select an appropriate model; all right?
Well, one thing you could do is
you can pick all of these models,
and train them on you're training set.
And then see which model has the lowest training error.
So that's a terrible idea,
and why's that?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Right. Cool.
Because of the over fit; right.
And those some of you are laughing that I asked that.
So that'd be a terrible idea to choose a
model by looking at your training set because well,
obviously, you end up choosing
the most complex model; right?
And you choose a 10th degree polynomial
because that's what fits the training set.
So we come to model selection in a training set
several standard procedures to do this.
One is hold out cross validation,
and in hold out cross validation,
we teach a training set.
And we randomly split the training set into two subsets.
We call it subset
take all the data you have and
randomly split it into two subsets.
And we'll call it the training set,
and the hold out cross validation subset.
And then, you know, you train each model
on just trading subset of it,
and test it on your hold out cross validation set.
And you pick the model with the lowest error
on the hold out cross validation subset; okay?
So this is sort of a relatively straightforward procedure,
and it's commonly used where you
train on 70 percent of the data.
Then test all of your models.
And 30 percent, you can
take whatever has the smallest hold
out cross validation error.
And after this
you actually have a chose.
You can actually having taken all
of these hypothesis trained on 70 percent of the data,
you can actually just output the hypothesis
that has the lowest error on your hold out cross
validation set. And optionally, you can actually
take the model that you selected and go back,
and retrain it on all 100
percent of the data; okay?
So both versions are actually done and used really often.
You can either, you know, just take the best
hypothesis that was trained on 70 percent of the data,
and just output that as you find the
hypothesis or
you can use this to say,
having chosen the degree of the polynomial
you want to fit,
you can then go back and retrain
the model on the entire 100 percent of your data.
And both of these are commonly done.
How about a cross validation does sort of work straight?
And sometimes we're working with
a company or application or something.
The many machine-learning applications
we have very little data or where,
you know, every training example you have
was painfully acquired at great cost; right?
Sometimes your data is acquired by medical experiments,
and each of these each training example represents a sick
man in amounts of physical human pain or something.
So we talk and say,
"Well, I'm going to hold out 30 percent of your data set,
just to select my model."
If people were who sometimes that causes unhappiness,
and so maybe you wanna use
not have to leave out 30 percent of
your data just to do model selection.
So there are a couple of other variations on
hold out cross validation that makes sometimes,
slightly more efficient use of the data.
And one is called k-fold cross validation.
And here's the idea:
I'm gonna take all of my data s;
so imagine, I'm gonna
draw this box s,
as to note the entirety of all the data I have.
And I'll then divide it into k pieces,
and this is five pieces in what I've drawn.
Then what'll I'll do is I will
repeatedly train on k minus one pieces.
Test on the remaining one test on the
remaining piece, I guess; right?
And then you average over the k result.
So another way, we'll just hold out
I will hold out say, just 1/5 of my data
and I'll train on the remaining 4/5,
and I'll test on the first one.
And then I'll then go and hold out the second 1/5
from my [inaudible] for the remaining pieces
test on this,
you remove the third piece,
train on the 4/5;
I'm gonna do this five times.
And then I'll take the five error measures I have
and I'll average them.
And this then gives me an estimate of
the generalization error of my model; okay?
And then, again, when you do k-fold cross validation,
usually you then go back and
retrain the model you selected on the
entirety of your training set.
So I drew five pieces here because
that was easier for me to draw,
but k equals 10 is very common; okay?
I should say k equals 10 is the fairly common choice
to do 10 fold cross validation.
And the advantage of the over hold out cross option is that
you switch the data into ten pieces.
Then each time you're only holding out 1/10 of your data,
rather than, you know, say, 30 percent of your data.
I must say, in standard hold out
in simple hold out cross validation,
a 30 70 split is fairly common.
Sometimes like 2/3 1/3 or
a 70 30 split is fairly common.
And if you use k-fold cross validation,
k equals 5 or more commonly k equals 10,
and is the most common choice.
The disadvantage of k-fold cross validation is
that it can be much more computationally expensive.
In particular, to validate your model,
you now need to train your model ten times,
instead of just once.
And so you need to:
from logistic regression,
ten times per model,
rather than just once.
And so this is computationally more expensive.
But k equals ten works great.
And then, finally, in there's actually a
version of this that you can take even further,
which is when your set k equals m.
And so that's when you take your training set,
and you split it into as many pieces as
you have training examples.
And this procedure is called
leave one out cross validation.
And what you do is you then
take out the first training example,
train on the rest,
and test on the first example.
Then you take out the second training example,
train on the rest,
and test on the second example.
Then you take out the third example,
train on everything, but your third example.
Test on the third example, and so on.
And so with this many pieces you are now making,
maybe even more effective use of your
data than k-fold cross validation.
But you could leave leave one out
cross validation is computationally very expensive
because now you need to repeatedly
leave one example out,
and then run your learning
algorithm on m minus one training examples.
You need to do this a lot of times,
and so this is computationally very expensive.
And typically,
this is done only when you're extremely data scarce.
So if you have a learning problem where you have,
say, 15 training examples or something,
then if you have very few training examples,
leave one out cross validation is maybe preferred.
Yeah?
Student:You know, that time you proved that
the difference between the generalized by number of
examples in your training set and VC dimension.
So maybe examples into different groups, we can use that
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, I mean
Student:- compute the training error,
and use that for computing for a generalized error.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, that's done, but
yeah, in practice, I personally tend not to do that.
It tends not to be the VC dimension
bounds are somewhat loose bounds.
And so there are people in structure risk
minimization that propose what you do,
but I personally tend not to do that, though.
Questions for cross validation? Yeah.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Right.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):No okay.
So it turns out that when you're
proving learning theory bounds,
very often the bounds will be extremely loose
because you're sort of proving the worse case upper
bound that holds true even for very bad
what is it so the bounds
that I proved just now; right?
That holds true for absolutely any
probability distribution over training examples; right?
So just assume the training
examples we've drawn,
iid from some distribution script d,
and the bounds I proved hold true
for absolutely any probability distribution over script d.
And chances are whatever real life
distribution you get over, you know,
houses and their prices or whatever,
is probably not as bad as the very worse
one you could've gotten; okay?
And so it turns out that if you actually
plug in the constants of learning theory bounds,
you often get extremely large numbers.
Take logistic regression
logistic regression you have ten parameters
and 0.01 error, and with 95
percent probability.
How many training examples do I need?
If you actually plug in actual constants
into the text for learning theory bounds,
you often get extremely pessimistic estimates
with the number of examples you need.
You end up with some ridiculously large numbers.
You would need 10,000 training
examples to fit ten parameters.
So a good way to think of these learning theory
bounds is and this is why, also,
when I write papers on learning theory bounds,
I quite often use big-O notation to just
absolutely just ignore the constant factors
because the bounds seem to be very loose.
There are some attempts to use these
bounds to give guidelines as to what model to choose,
and so on. But I personally tend to use the bounds
again, intuition about
for example, what are the number of training examples you
need gross linearly in the number of parameters or what
are your gross x dimension in number of parameters;
whether it goes quadratic parameters?
So it's quite often the shape of the bounds.
The fact that the number of training examples
the fact that some complexity
is linear in the VC dimension,
that's sort of a useful intuition you
can get from these theories.
But the actual magnitude of the bound
will tend to be much looser than
will hold true for a particular problem you are working on.
So did that answer your question?
Student:Uh-huh.
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah. And it turns out, by the way,
for myself, a rule of thumb that I often use
is if you're trying to fit a logistic
regression model,
if you have n parameters or n plus one parameters;
if the number of training examples is
ten times your number of parameters,
then you're probably in good shape.
And if your number of training examples is
like tiny times the number of parameters,
then you're probably perfectly fine fitting that model.
So those are the sorts of intuitions that
you can get from these bounds.
Student:In cross validation do
we assume these examples randomly?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yes. So by convention
we usually split the train testers randomly.
One more thing I want to talk about for model selection
is there's actually a special case of model selections,
called the feature selection problem.
And so here's the intuition:
for many machine-learning problems
you may have a very high dimensional feature space
So for example, for text classification
and I wanna talk about this text classification
with very high dimensional you have x's –feature x's.
example that spam versus non-spam.
You may easily have on the order
of 30,000 or 50,000 features.
I think I used 50,000 in my early examples.
So if you have so many features
you have 50,000 features,
depending on what learning algorithm you use,
there may be a real risk of over fitting.
And so if you can reduce the number of features,
maybe you can reduce the
variance of your learning algorithm,
and reduce the
risk of over fitting.
And for the specific case of text classification,
if you imagine that maybe
there's a small number of "relevant features,"
so there are all these English words.
And many of these English words probably
don't tell you anything at all about
whether the email is spam or non-spam.
If it were, you know, English function words like,
the, of, a, and; these are probably words
that don't tell you anything about whether
the email is spam or non-spam.
So words in contrast will be a much smaller number of
features that are truly "relevant" to the learning problem.
So for example, you see the
word buy or Viagra,
those are words that are very useful.
So you words, some you spam and non-spam.
You see the word Stanford or
machine-learning or your own personal name.
These are other words that are useful
for telling you whether something is spam or non-spam.
So in feature selection,
we would like to select a subset of the
features that may be or hopefully the most
relevant ones for a specific
learning problem,
so as to give ourselves a simpler learning
a simpler hypothesis class to choose from.
And then therefore, reduce the risk of over fitting.
Even when we may have had 50,000 features originally.
So how do you do this?
Well, if you have n features,
then there are two to the n possible subsets; right?
Because, you know, each of your n features
can either be included or excluded.
So there are two to the n possibilities.
And this is a huge space.
So in feature selection,
what we most commonly do is use various
searcheristics sort of simple search algorithms
to try to search through this space of
two to the n possible subsets of features;
to try to find a good subset of features.
This is too large a number to enumerate
all possible feature subsets.
And as a complete example,
this is the forward search algorithm;
it's also called the forward selection algorithm.
It's actually pretty simple,
but I'll just write it out.
My writing it out will make it look more
complicated than it really is,
but it starts with
initialize the sets script f to be the empty set,
and then repeat for i equals one to n;
try adding feature i to the set scripts f,
and evaluate the model using cross validation.
And by cross validation, I mean any of the three flavors,
be it simple hold out cross validation
or k-fold cross validation
or leave one out cross validation.
And then, you know, set f to be equal to f union, I guess.
And then the best feature found is f 1, I guess; okay?
And finally, you would okay?
So forward selections, procedure is:
follow through the empty set of features.
And then on each generation,
take each of your features that isn't already in your set
script f and you try adding that feature to your set.
Then you train them all, though,
and evaluate them all, though, using cross validation.
And basically, figure out what is the best single
feature to add to your set script f.
In step two here,
you go ahead and add that feature to your set script f,
and you get it right. And when I say
best feature or best model here by best,
I really mean the best model
according to hold out cross validation.
By best, I really mean the single feature addition
that results in the lowest hold out cross validation error
or the lowest cross validation error.
So you do this adding one feature at a time.
When you terminate this a little bit,
as if you've added all the features to f,
so f is now the entire set of features;
you can terminate this.
Or if by some rule of thumb,
you know that you probably don't ever
want more than k features,
you can also terminate this
if f is already exceeded some
threshold number of features.
So maybe if you have 100 training examples,
and you're fitting logistic regression,
you probably know you won't
want more than 100 features.
And so you stop after
you have 100 features
added to set f; okay?
And then finally, having done this,
output of best hypothesis found; again,
by best, I mean,
when learning this algorithm,
you'd be seeing lots of hypothesis.
You'd be training lots of hypothesis,
and testing them using cross validation.
So when I say output best hypothesis found,
I mean of all of the
hypothesis you've seen
during this entire procedure,
pick the one with the
lowest cross validation error
that you saw; okay?
So that's forward selection.
So let's see, just to give this a name,
this is an incidence of what's
called wrapper feature selection.
And the term wrapper comes from the fact that
this feature selection algorithm that I just described
is a forward selection or forward search.
It's a piece of software that you write that wraps
around your learning algorithm.
In the sense that to perform forward selection,
you need to repeatedly make cause
to your learning algorithm to train your model,
using different subsets of features;
okay? So this is called wrapper model feature selection.
And it tends to be somewhat computationally expensive
because as you're performing the search process,
you're repeatedly training your learning
algorithm over and over and over on all of these
different subsets of features.
Let's just mention also,
there is a variation of this called
backward search or backward selection,
which is where you start with f
equals the entire set of features,
and you delete features one at a time; okay?
So that's backward search or backward selection.
And this is another feature
selection algorithm that you might use.
Part of whether this makes sense is really
there will be problems where it
really doesn't even make sense to
initialize f to be the set of all features.
So if you have 100 training examples and 10,000 features,
which may well happen
100 emails and 10,000 training 10,000 features in email,
then 100 training examples
then depending on the
learning algorithm you're using,
it may or may not make sense to
initialize the set f to be all features,
and train them all by using all features.
And if it doesn't make sense,
then you can train them all by using all features;
then forward selection would be more common.
So let's see.
Wrapper model feature selection algorithms
tend to work well.
And in particular, they actually often work better
than a different class of algorithms
I'm gonna talk about now.
But their main disadvantage is that
they're computationally very expensive.
Do you have any questions about this before
I talk about the other? Yeah?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah yes, you're actually right.
So forward search and backward search,
both of these are searcheristics,
and you cannot but for either of these you cannot
guarantee they'll find the best subset of features.
It actually turns out that under many formulizations
of the feature selection problems
it actually turns out to be an empty heart problem,
to find the best subset of features.
But in practice,
forward selection backward
selection work fine,
and you can also envision other search
algorithms where you sort of have other
methods to search through the space up
to the end possible feature subsets.
So let's see.
Wrapper feature selection tends to work well
when you can afford to do it computationally.
But for problems such as text classification
it turns out for text classification specifically
because you have so many features,
and easily have 50,000 features.
Forward selection would be very, very expensive.
So there's a different class of algorithms
that will give you that tends not to do
as well in the sense of generalization error.
So you tend to learn the hypothesis that works less well,
but is computationally much less expensive.
And these are called the filter
feature selection methods.
And the basic idea is that
for each feature i will compute
some measure of how informative xi is about y; okay?
And to do this,
we'll use some simple heuristics;
for every feature
we'll just try to compute some rough estimate or compute
some measure of how informative xi is about y.
So there are many ways you can do this.
One way you can choose is to just compute
the correlation between xi and y.
And just for each of your features just see how
correlated this is with your class label y.
And then you just pick the top k most correlated features.
Another way to do this
for the case of text classification,
there's one other method,
which especially for this k features I guess
there's one other informative measure that's used
very commonly, which is called major information.
I'm going to tell you some of these ideas in problem sets,
but I'll just say this very briefly.
So the major information between feature xi and y
I'll just write out the definition, I guess.
Let's say this is text classification,
so x can take on two values, 0, 1;
the major information between xi and y is
to find out some overall possible values of x;
some overall possible values of y
times the distribution times that.
Where all of these distributions
where so the joint distribution over xi and y,
you would estimate from your training data
all of these things you would use, as well.
You would estimate from the training data what is
the probability that x is 0,
what's the probability that x is one,
what's the probability that x is 0, y is 0,
x is one; y is 0, and so on.
So it turns out there's a standard information theoretic
measure of how different probability distributions are.
And I'm not gonna prove this here.
But it turns out that this major information is actually
so the standard measure of how different distributions are;
called the K-L divergence.
When you take a class in information theory,
you have seen concepts of mutual information
in the K-L divergence,
but if you haven't, don't worry about it.
Just the intuition is there's something
called K-L divergence that's a formal measure of
how different two
probability distributions are.
And mutual information is a measure
for how different the joint distribution is of x and y;
from the distribution you would get
if you were to assume they
were independent; okay?
So if x and y were independent,
then p of x, y would be equal to p of x times p of y.
And so you know, this distribution
and this distribution would be identical,
and the K-L divergence would be 0.
In contrast, if x and y were very non-independent
in other words, if x and y are
very informative about each other,
then this K-L divergence will be large.
And so mutual information is a formal measure
of how non-independent x and y are.
And if x and y are
highly non-independent
then that means that x will presumably
tell you something about y,
and so they'll have large mutual information.
And this measure of information will tell you
x might be a good feature.
And you get to play with some of these
ideas more in the problem sets.
So I won't say much more about it.
And what you do then is
having chosen some measure like
correlation or major information or something else,
you then pick the top k features;
meaning that you compute correlation between xi and y
for all the features of mutual information
xi and y for all the features.
And then you include in your learning algorithm
the k features of the largest correlation with the label
or the largest mutual information label, whatever.
And to choose k, you can actually
use cross validation, as well; okay?
So you would take all your features,
and sort them in decreasing order of mutual information.
And then you'd try using just the top one feature,
the top two features, the top three features, and so on.
And you decide how many features includes
using cross validation; okay?
Or you can sometimes you can
just choose this by hand, as well.
Okay. Questions about this? Okay. Cool. Great.
So next lecture I'll continue
I'll wrap up the Bayesian model selection,
but less close to the end