MachineLearning-Lecture17
Okay, good morning. Welcome back.
So I hope all of you had a good
Thanksgiving break.
After the problem sets,
I suspect many of us needed one.
Just one quick announcement so as I announced
by email a few days ago, this afternoon we'll
be doing another tape ahead of lecture,
so I won't physically be here
on Wednesday, and so we'll be taping this
Wednesday's lecture ahead of time.
If you're free this afternoon,
please come to that; it'll be at 3:45 p.m.
in the Skilling Auditorium in Skilling 193 at
3:45. But of course, you can also
just show up in class as usual at the usual time
or just watch it online as usual also.
Okay, welcome back.
What I want to do today is
continue our discussion on
Reinforcement Learning in MDPs.
Quite a long topic for me to go over today,
so most of today's lecture will be on continuous
state MDPs, and in particular, algorithms for
solving continuous state MDPs, so I'll talk just
very briefly about discretization.
I'll spend a lot of time talking about models,
assimilators of MDPs, and then talk about one
algorithm called fitted value iteration
and two functions which builds on that,
and then hopefully, I'll have time to get
to a second algorithm called,
approximate policy iteration
Just to recap, right, in the previous lecture,
I defined the Reinforcement Learning problem
and I defined MDPs, so let me just recap
the notation. I said that an MDP or a Markov
Decision Process, was a 5 tuple,
comprising those
things and the running example of
those using last time was this one right, adapted
from the Russell and Norvig AI
textbook. So in this example MDP that I was
using, it had 11 states, so that's where S
was. The actions were compass directions:
north, south, east and west.
The state transition probability is to capture
chance of your transitioning to every state
when you take any action in any other given
state and so in our example that captured the
stochastic dynamics of our robot wondering
around the spread, and we said if you take
the action north and the south, you have
a .8 chance of actually going north
and .1 chance of veering off, so that .
1 chance of veering off to the right
so said model of the robot's
noisy dynamic with a [inaudible]
and the reward function was that +/-1
at the absorbing states and -0.02 elsewhere.
This is an example of an MDP, and that's what
these five things were. Oh, and I used a
discount factor G of usually a number slightly
less than one, so that's the 0.99. And so our
goal was to find the policy, the control policy
and that's at ?, which is a function mapping
from the states of the actions that tells us what
action to take in every state, and our goal was
to find a policy that maximizes the expected
value of our total payoff. So we want to find a
policy. Well, let's see. We define value
functions Vp (s) to be equal to this. We said that
the value of a policy π from State S was given
by the expected value of the sum of discounted
rewards, conditioned on your executing the
policy ? and you're stating off your robot
to say in the State S, and so our strategy
for finding the policy was sort of comprised of
two steps. So the goal is to find a good
policy that maximizes the suspected value of
the sum of discounted rewards, and so I said
last time that one strategy for finding the
[inaudible] of a policy is to first compute the
optimal value function which I denoted V*(s)
and is defined like that. It's the maximum
value that any policy can obtain, and for
example, the optimal value function for that
MDP looks like this. So in other words,
starting from any of these states, what's the
expected value of the sum of discounted
rewards you get, so this is V*. We also said that
once you've found V*, you can compute the
optimal policy using this.
And so once you've found V*, we can use
the last piece of this algorithm was Bellman's
this equation to find the optimal policy π* and
equations where we know that V*, the
optimal sum of discounted rewards you can get
for State S, is equal to the immediate
reward you get just for
starting off in that state +G
(for the max over all the actions you
could take)(your future sum of discounted
rewards)(your future payoff starting from the
State S(p) which is where you might transition
to after 1(s). And so this gave us a value
iteration algorithm, which was essentially V.I.
I'm abbreviating value iteration as V.I.,
so in the value iteration algorithm, in V.I.,
you just take Bellman's equations
and you repeatedly do this.
So initialize some guess of the value functions.
Initialize a zero as the sum rounding guess and
then repeatedly perform this update for all
states, and I said last time that if you do this
repeatedly, then V(s) will converge to
the optimal value function, V*(s)
and then having found V*(s), you can
compute the optimal policy ?*.
Just one final thing I want to recap was
the policy iteration algorithm in which
we repeat the following two steps.
So let's see, given a random initial policy,
we'll solve for Vp. We'll solve for the value
function for that specific policy.
So this means for every state, compute
the expected sum of discounted rewards
for if you execute the policy ?
from that state, and then the other step
of policy iteration is having
found the value function for your policy,
you then update the policy pretending
that you've already found the optimal
value function, V*, and then you repeatedly
perform these two steps where you solve for
the value function for your current policy
and then pretend that that's actually the optimal
value function and solve for the policy given
the value function, and you repeatedly
update the value function or update the policy
using that value function. And last time I said
that this will also cause the estimated value
function V to converge to V* and this will
cause p to converge to ?*, the optimal policy.
So those are based on our last lecture
starts over MDPs and introduced a lot of new
notation symbols and just summarize all that
again. What I'm about to do now,
what I'm about to do for the rest of today's
lecture is actually build on these two algorithms
so I guess if you have any questions about this
piece, ask now since I've got to go on please.
Yeah.
Student:I don't see how those
two algorithms are very different?
I see, right, so yeah,
do you see that they're different? Okay,
how it's different. Let's see.
So well here's one difference.
I didn't say this 'cause no longer use it today.
So value iteration and policy iteration
are different algorithms. In policy iteration in this
step, you're given a fixed policy,
and you're going to solve for the value function
for that policy and so you're given some fixed
policy ?, meaning some function mapping from
the state's actions. So give you some policy and
whatever. That's just some policy; it's not
a great policy. And in that step that I circled,
we have to find the ? of S which means that
for every state you need to compute
your expected sum of discounted rewards
or if you execute this specific policy
and starting off the MDP in that state S.
So I showed this last time. I won't go into
details today, so I said last time that you can
actually solve for Vp by solving a linear system
of equations. There was a form of
Bellman's equations for Vp, and it turned out to
be, if you write this out, you end up with
a linear system of 11 equations of 11 unknowns
and so you can actually solve for the
value function for a fixed policy by solving like
a system of linear equations with 11
variables and 11 constraints, and so that's
policy iteration; whereas, in value iteration,
going back on board, in value iteration
you sort of repeatedly perform this update where
you update the value of a state as the
[inaudible]. So I hope that makes sense that the
algorithm of these is different.
Student: In this occasion, on the atomic kits
so is the assumption
that we can never get out of those states?
Yes. There's always things that you where you
solve for this [inaudible], for example,
and make the numbers come up nicely,
but I don't wanna spend too much time
on them, but yeah, so the assumption is
that once you enter the absorbing state,
then the world ends or there're no more
rewards after that and you can think of
another way to think of the absorbing states
which is sort of mathematically equivalent.
You can think of the absorbing states as
transitioning with probability 1 to sum 12 state,
and then once you're in that 12th state, you
always remain in that 12th state, and there're
no further rewards from there. If you want, you
can think of this as actually an MDP with
12 states rather than 11 states, and the 12th state
is this zero cost absorbing state that you
get stuck in forever.
Other questions?
Yeah, please go.
Student:Where did the Bellman's equations
[inaudible] to optimal value [inaudible]?
Boy, yeah. Okay, this Bellman's equations,
this equation that I'm pointing to, I sort of tried
to give it justification for this last time. I'll say
it in one sentence so that's that the expected
total payoff I get, I expect to get something
from the state as is equal to my immediate
reward which is the reward I get for starting a
state. Let's see. If I sum the state, I'm gonna get
some first reward and then I can transition to
some other state, and then from that other state,
I'll get some additional rewards from then.
So Bellman's equations breaks that sum
into two pieces. It says the value of a state
is equal to the reward you get right away is
really, well. V*(s) is really equal to +G,
so this is V*(s) is, and so Bellman's equations
sort of breaks V* into two terms and says that
there's this first term which is the immediate
reward, that, and then +G(the rewards you
get in the future) which it turns out
to be equal to that second row.
I spent more time justifying this in the previous
lecture, although yeah, hopefully,
for the purposes of this lecture,
if you're not sure where this is came,
if you don't remember the justification of that,
why don't you just maybe take my word for
that this equation holds true since I use it
a little bit later as well, and then the lecture notes
sort of explain a little further the justification
for why this equation might hold true.
But for now, yeah, just for
now take my word for it
that this holds true
cause we'll use it a little bit later today as well.
Student:[Inaudible] and would it be in sort of
turn back into [inaudible].
Actually, [inaudible] right question
is if in policy iteration if
we represent ? implicitly, using V(s),
would it become equivalent to valuation,
and the answer is sort of no.
Let's see. It's true that policy iteration
and value iteration are closely
related algorithms, and there's actually
a continuum between them, but yeah, it actually
turns out that, oh, no, the algorithms are not
equivalent. It's just in policy iteration,
there is a step where you're solving
for the value function for the policy vehicle
is V, solve for Vp. Usually, you can do this,
for instance, by solving a linear system of
equations. In value iteration, it is a different
algorithm, yes. I hope it makes sense that at
least cosmetically it's different.
Student:[Inaudible] you have [inaudible]
representing ? implicitly, then you won't have
to solve that to [inaudible] equations.
Yeah, the problem is - let's see. To solve for Vp,
this works only if you have a fixed policy, so
once you change a value function, if ? changes
as well, then it's sort of hard to solve this.
Yeah, so later on we'll actually talk about some
examples of when ? is implicitly represented
but at least for now it's I think there's
yeah. Maybe there's a way to redefine
something, see a mapping onto value iteration
but that's not usually done.
These are viewed as different algorithms.
Okay, cool, so all good questions. Let me move
on and talk about how to generalize these
ideas to continuous states. Everything we've
done so far has been for discrete states or
finite-state MDPs. Where, for example, here we
had an MDP with a finite set of 11 states
and so the value function or V(s) or our
estimate for the value function, V(s), could then
be represented using an array of 11 numbers
'cause if you have 11 states, the value
function needs to assign a real number to each
of the 11 states and so to represent V(s)
using an array of 11 numbers. What I want to
do for [inaudible] today is talk about
continuous states, so for example, if you want
to control any of the number of real
[inaudible], so for example, if you want to
control a car, a car is positioned given by
XYT, as position and orientation and if you
want to Markov the velocity as well, then
Xdot, Ydot, Tdot, so these are so depending on
whether you want to model the
kinematics and so just position, or whether you
want to model the dynamics, meaning the
velocity as well.
Earlier I showed you video of a helicopter that
was flying, using a rain forest we're
learning algorithms, so the helicopter which can
fly in three-dimensional space rather
than just drive on the 2-D plane, the state will
be given by XYZ position, FT?, which is
?[inaudible]. The FT? is sometimes used to note
the P[inaudible] of the helicopter, just
orientation, and if you want to control a
helicopter, you pretty much have to model
velocity as well which means both linear
velocity as well as angular velocity, and so this
would be a 12-dimensional state.
If you want an example that is kind of fun but
unusual is, and I'm just gonna use this as
an example and actually use this little bit
example in today's lecture is the inverted
pendulum problem which is sort of a
long-running classic in reinforcement learning
in which imagine that you have a little cart
that's on a rail. The rail ends at some point and
if you imagine that you have a pole attached to
the cart, and this is a free hinge and so the
pole here can rotate freely, and your goal is to
control the cart and to move it back and
forth on this rail so as to keep the pole
balanced. there's no long pole in this class
but you know what I mean, so you can imagine.
Oh, is there a long pole here?
Student:Back in the corner.
Oh, thanks. Cool. So I did not practice this but
you can take a long pole
and sort of hold it up,
balance, so imagine that you can do it better
than I can. Imagine these are [inaudible] just
moving back and forth to try to keep the pole
balanced, so you can actually us the
reinforcement learning algorithm to do that.
problems that people [inaudible] implement and
play off using reinforcement learning
algorithms, and so for this, the states would be
X and T, so X would be the position of the cart,
and T would be the orientation of the pole and
also the linear velocity and the angular velocity
of the pole, so I'll actually use this example a
couple times.
So to read continuous state space, how can you
apply an algorithm like value iteration
and policy iteration to solve the MDP to control
like the car or a helicopter or something
like the inverted pendulum? So one thing you
can do and this is maybe the most
straightforward thing is, if you have say a
two-dimensional continuous state space, a S-1
and S-2 are my state variables, and in all the
examples there are I guess between
4dimensional to 12-dimensional
I'll just draw 2-D here.
The most straightforward thing to
do would be to take the continuous state space
and discretize it into a number of discrete cells.
And I use S-bar to denote
they're discretized or
they're discrete states, and so you can
[inaudible] with this continuous state problem
with a finite or discrete set of states and
then you can use policy iteration or value
iteration to solve for V*(s)-bar and ?*(s)-bar.
And if you're robot is then in some state given
by that dot, you would then figure out
what discretized state it is in. In this case it's in,
this discretized dygrid cell that's called
S-bar, and then you execute. You choose the
policy. You choose the action given by
applied to that discrete state, so discretization is
maybe the most straightforward way to
turn a continuous state problem
into a discrete state problem.
Sometimes you can sorta make
this work but a couple of reasons why this does
not work very well. One reason is the
following, and for this picture, let's even
temporarily put aside reinforcement learning.
Let's just think about doing regression for now
and so suppose you have some invariable X and
suppose I have some data, and I want to fill a
function. Y is the function of X,
so discretization is saying that I'm going to take
my horizontal Xs and chop it up into a number
of intervals. Sometimes I call these intervals
buckets as well. We chop my horizontal Xs up
into a number of buckets and then
we're approximate this function using
something that's piecewise constant in each of
these buckets. And just look at this.
This is clearly not a very good representation,
right, and when we talk about regression,
you just choose some features of X and run
linear regression or something. You get a
much better fit to the function. And so the sense
that discretization just isn't a very good
source of piecewise constant functions. This
just isn't a very good function for
representing many things, and there's also the
sense that there's no smoothing or there's
no generalization across the different buckets.
And in fact, back in regression, I would
never have chosen to do regression using this
sort of visualization. It's just really doesn't
make sense.
And so in the same way, instead of X, V(s),
instead of X and some hypothesis function of
X, if you have the state here and you're trying
to approximate the value function, then
you can get discretization to work for many
problems but maybe this isn't the best
representation to represent a value function.
The other problem with discretization and
maybe the more serious problem is what's often
somewhat fancifully called the curse of
dimensionality. And just the observation that if
the state space is in RN, and if you
discretize each variable into K buckets, so if
discretize each variable into K discrete
values, then you get on the order of K to the
power of N discrete states. In other words,
the number of discrete states you end up with
grows exponentially in the dimension of
the problem, and so for a helicopter with
12-dimensional state space, this would be
maybe like 100 to the power of 12, just huge,
and it's not feasible. And so discretization
doesn't scale well at all with two problems in
high-dimensional state spaces, and this
observation actually applies more generally
than to just robotics and continuous state
problems. For example, another fairly
well-known applications of reinforcement
learning has been to factory automations.
If you imagine that you have 20 machines
sitting in the factory and the machines
lie in a assembly line
and they all do something to
a part on the assembly line, then they route
the part onto a different machine.
You want to use
reinforcement learning algorithms,
[inaudible] the order in which the
different machines operate
on your different things that are flowing
through your assembly line and maybe
different machines can do different things.
So if you have N machines and
each machine can be in K states,
then if you do this sort of discretization,
the total number of
states would be K to N as well.
If you have N machines
and if each machine can be in K states,
then again, you can get this huge number
of states. Other well-known examples would be
if you have a board game is another example.
You'd want to use reinforcement learning
to play chess. Then if you have N pieces on
your board game, you have N pieces on the
chessboard and if each piece can be in K
positions, then this is a game sort of
the curse of dimensionality thing where the number of
discrete states you end up with goes
exponentially with the number of pieces in your
board game. So the curse of
dimensionality means that discretization scales
poorly to high-dimensional state spaces or
at least discrete representations scale poorly to
high-dimensional state spaces. In practice,
discretization will usually, if you have a
2-dimensional problem, discretization will
usually work great. If you have a 3-dimensional
problem, you can often get discretization
to work not too badly without too much trouble.
With a 4-dimensional problem, you can
still often get to where that they could be
challenging and as you go to higher and higher
dimensional state spaces, the odds and
[inaudible] that you need to figure around to
discretization and do things like non-uniform
grids, so for example, what I've drawn for
you is an example of a non-uniform
discretization where I'm discretizing S-2
much more finally than S-1.
If I think the value function is
much more sensitive to the value of state
variable S-2 than to S-1, and so as you get into
higher dimensional state spaces, you may
need to manually fiddle with choices like these
with no uniform discretizations and so on.
But the folk wisdom seems to be that if you
have 2- or 3-dimensional problems, it work
fine. With 4-dimensional problems, you can
probably get it to work but it'd be just
slightly challenging and you can sometimes by
fooling around and being clever, you can
often push discretization up to let's say about
6-dimensional problems but with some
difficulty and problems higher than
6-dimensional would be extremely difficult
to solve with discretization. So that's just rough
folk wisdom order of managing problems you
think about using for discretization.
But what I want to spend most of today talking
about is [inaudible] methods that
often work much better than discretization and which we
will approximate V* directly without resulting
to these sort of discretizations. Before I jump
to the specific representation let me just spend
a few minutes talking about the problem
setup then. For today's lecture, I'm going to
focus on the problem of continuous states
and just to keep things sort of very simple in
this lecture, I want view of continuous
actions, so I'm gonna see discrete actions A.
So it turns out actually that is a critical fact
also for many problems, it turns out that
the state space is much larger than the states of
actions. That just seems to have worked out that
way for many problems, so for example,
for driving a car the state space is
6-dimensional, so if XY T, Xdot, Ydot, Tdot.
Whereas, your action has, you still have two
actions. You have forward backward motion
and steering the car, so you have 6-D states and
2-D actions, and so you can discretize the
action much more easily than discretize the
states. The only examples down for a
helicopter you've 12-D states in a
4-dimensional action it turns out,
and it's also often much easier
to just discretize a continuous
actions into a discrete sum of actions. And for
the inverted pendulum, you have a 4-D state
and a 1-D action. Whether you accelerate
your cart to the left or the right is one D action
and so for the rest of today, I'm gonna
assume a continuous state but I'll assume that
maybe you've already discretized your
actions, just because in practice it turns out that
not for all problems, with many problems
large actions is just less of a difficulty than
large state spaces. So I'm going to assume
that we have a model or simulator of the MDP,
and so this is really an assumption on
how the state transition probabilities are
represented. I'm gonna assume and I'm going
to use the terms "model" and "simulator"
pretty much synonymously,
so specifically, what I'm going to assume
is that we have a black
box and a piece of code, so that I can input
any state, input an action and it will output S
prime, sample from the state transition
distribution. Says that this is really my
assumption on the representation I have for the
state transition probabilities, so I'll assume I
have a box that read take us in for the stated
action and output in mixed state. And so since
they're fairly common ways to get models
of different MDPs you may work with, one is
you might get a model from a physics
simulator. So for example, if you're interested
in controlling that inverted pendulum, so
your action is A which is the magnitude of the
force you exert on the cart to left or right,
and your state is Xdot, T, Tdot. I'm just gonna
write that in that order. And so I'm gonna
write down a bunch of equations just for
completeness but everything I'm gonna write
below here is most of what I wanna write is a
bit gratuitous, but so since I'll maybe flip
open a textbook on physics, a textbook on
mechanics, you can work out the equations of
motion of a physical device like this, so you
find that Sdot. The dot denotes derivative, so
the derivative of the state with respect to time is
given by Xdot, ?-L(B) cost B over M
Tdot, B. And so on where A is the force is the
action that you exert on the cart. L is the
length of the pole. M is the total mass of the
system and so on. So all these equations are
good uses, just writing them down for
completeness, but by flipping over, open like a
physics textbook, you can work out these
equations and notions yourself and this then
gives you a model which can say that S-2+1.
You're still one time step later will be equal
to your previous state plus [inaudible], so in
your simulator or in my model what happens
to the cart every 10th of a second, so delta T would
be within one second and then so plus delta T
times that. And so that'd be one way to come
up with a model of your MDP. And in this
specific example, I've actually written down
deterministic model because and by
deterministic I mean that given an action in a
state, the next state is not random, so would
be an example of a deterministic model where I
can compute the next state exactly as a
function of the previous state and the previous
action or it's a deterministic model
because all the probability mass is on a single
state given the previous stated action. You
can also make this a stochastic model. A second
way that is often used to attain a model
is to learn one. And so again, just concretely
what you do is you would imagine that you
have a physical inverted pendulum system as
you physically own an inverted pendulum
robot. What you would do is you would then
initialize your inverted pendulum robot to
some state and then execute some policy, could
be some random policy or some policy
that you think is pretty good, or you could even
try controlling yourself with a joystick or
something. But so you set the system off in
some state as zero. Then you take some
action. Here's zero and the game could be
chosen by some policy or chosen by you using
a joystick tryina control your inverted
pendulum or whatever. System would transition
to some new state, S-1, and then you take some
new action, A-1 and so on. Let's say you do
this for two time steps and sometimes I call this
one trajectory and you repeat this M
times, so this is the first trial of the first
trajectory, and then you do this again. Initialize
it in some and so on. So you do this a bunch of
times and then you would run the learning
algorithm to estimate ST+1 as a function of ST
and AT. And for sake of completeness,
you should just think of this as inverted
pendulum problem, so ST+1 is a 4-dimensional
vector. ST, AT will be a 4-dimensional vector
and that'll be a real number, and so you
might run linear regression 4 times to predict
each of these state variables as a function of
each of these 5 real numbers and so on.
Just for example, if you say that if you want to
estimate your next state ST+1 as a linear
function of your previous state in your action
and so A here will be a 4 by 4 matrix, and
B would be a 4-dimensional vector, then you
would choose the values of A and B that
minimize this. So if you want your model to be
that ST+1 is some linear function of the
previous stated action, then you might pose this
optimization objective and choose A and
B to minimize the sum of squares error in your
predictive value for ST+1 as the linear
function of ST and AT. I should say that this is
one specific example where you're using
a linear function of the previous stated action to
predict the next state.Of course, you can also
use other algorithms like low [inaudible]
weight to linear regression or linear regression
with nonlinear features or kernel linear
regression or whatever to predict the next state
as a nonlinear function of the current state as
well, so this is just [inaudible] linear problems.
And it turns out that low [inaudible] weight to
linear regression is for many robots turns out to
be an effective method for this learning
problem as well. And so having learned to
model, having learned the parameters A and B,
you then have a model where you say that
ST+1 is AST plus BAT, and so that would be an
example of a deterministic model or having
learned the parameters A and B, you might say
that ST+1 is equal to AST + BAT + ?T. And so
these would be very reasonable ways to come
up with either a deterministic or a stochastic
model for your inverted pendulum MDP. And
so just to summarize, what we have now is a
model, meaning a piece of code, where you
can input a state and an action and get an ST+1.
And so if you have a stochastic model,
then to influence this model, you would
actually sample ?T from this [inaudible]
distribution in order to generate ST+1.
So it actually turns out that in a preview,
I guess, in the next lecture it actually turns out
that in the specific case of linear dynamical
systems, in the specific case where the next
state is a linear function of the current stated
action, it actually turns out that there're very
powerful algorithms you can use. So I'm
actually not gonna talk about that today. I'll talk
about that in the next lecture rather than right
now but turns out that for many problems
of inverted pendulum go if you use low
[inaudible] weights and linear regressionals and
long linear algorithm 'cause many systems
aren't really linear.
You can build a nonlinear model.
So what I wanna do now is talk about given
a model, given a simulator for your MDP,
how to come up with an algorithm to
approximate the alpha value function piece.
Before I move on, let me check if there're
questions on this. Okay, cool.
So here's the idea. Back when we talked about
linear regression, we said that given some
inputs X in supervised learning, given the input
feature is X, we may choose some features of X
and then approximate the type of variable
as a linear function of various features of X,
and so just do exactly the same thing to
approximate the optimal value function, and in
particular, we'll choose some features
5-S of a state S.
And so you could actually choose 5-S equals S.
That would be one reasonable choice, if
you want to approximate the value function as
a linear function of the states, but you can
also choose other things, so for example, for the
inverted pendulum example, you may
choose 5-S to be equal to a vector of features
that may be [inaudible]1 or you may have
Xdot2, Xdot maybe some cross terms, maybe
times X, maybe dot2 and so on. So you
choose some vector or features and then
approximate the value function as the value of
the state as is equal to data transfers times the
features. And I should apologize in
advance; I'm overloading notation here.
It's unfortunate. I use data both to denote the
angle of the cart of the pole inverted pendulum.
So this is known as the angle T but also
using T to denote the vector of parameters in
my [inaudible] algorithm.
So sorry about the overloading notation.
Just like we did in linear regression,
my goal is to come up with
a linear combination of
the features that gives me a good approximation
to the value function and this is
completely analogous to when we said that in
linear regression our estimate, my response
there but Y as a linear function a feature is at
the input. That's what we have in linear
regression. Let me just write down value
iteration again and then I'll written down an
approximation to value iteration, so for discrete
states, this is the idea behind value
iteration and we said that V(s) will be updated
as R(s) + G [inaudible].
That was value iteration and in the case of
continuous states, this would be the replaced
by an [inaudible], an [inaudible] over states
rather via sum over states. Let me just write
this as R(s) + G([inaudible]) and then that sum
over T's prime. That's really an
expectation with respect to random state as
prime drawn from the state transition
probabilities piece SA of V(s) prime. So this is
a sum of all states S prime with the
probability of going to S prime (value), so
that's really an expectation over the random
state S prime flowing from PSA of that. And so
what I'll do now is write down an
algorithm called fitted value iteration that's in
approximation to this but specifically for
continuous states. I just wrote down the first
two steps, and then I'll continue on the next
board, so the first step of the algorithm is we'll
sample. Choose some set of states at
random. So sample S-1, S-2 through S-M
randomly so choose a set of states randomly
and initialize my parameter vector to be equal
to zero. This is analogous to in value
iteration where I might initialize the value
function to be the function of all zeros. Then
here's the end view for the algorithm. Got quite
a lot to write actually. Let's see. And so
that's the algorithm. Let me just adjust the
writing. Give me a second. Give me a minute
to finish and then I'll step through this.
Actually, if some of my handwriting is eligible,
let me know. So let me step through this and so
briefly explain the rationale. So the hear
of the algorithm is - let's see. In the original
value iteration algorithm, we would take the
value for each state, V(s)I, and we will
overwrite it with this expression here. In the
original, this discrete value iteration algorithm
was to V(s)I and we will set V(s)I to be
equal to that, I think. Now we have in the
continuous state case, we have an infinite
continuous set of states and so you can't
discretely set the value of each of these to that.
So what we'll do instead is choose the
parameters T so that V(s)I is as close as possible
to this thing on the right hand side
instead. And this is what YI turns out to be. So
completely, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to construct estimates of this term, and
then I'm going to choose the parameters of my
function approximator. I'm gonna choose
my parameter as T, so that V(s)I is as close as
possible to these. That's what YI is, and
specifically, what I'm going to do is I'll choose
parameters data to minimize the sum of
square differences between T [inaudible] plus
5SI. This thing here is just V(s)I because
I'm approximating V(s)I is a linear function of
5SI and so choose the parameters data to
minimize the sum of square differences. So this
is last step is basically the approximation
version of value iteration. What everything else
above was doing was just coming up
with an approximation to this term, to this thing
here and which I was calling YI. And so
confluently, for every state SI we want to
estimate what the thing on the right hand side is
and but there's an expectation here. There's an
expectation over a continuous set of
states, may be a very high dimensional state so
I can't compute this expectation exactly.
What I'll do instead is I'll use my simulator to
sample a set of states from this distribution
from this P substrip, SIA, from the state
transition distribution of where I get to if I take
the action A in the state as I, and then I'll
average over that sample of states to compute
this expectation. And so stepping through the
algorithm just says that for each state and
for each action, I'm going to sample a set of
states. This S prime 1 through S prime K
from that state transition distribution, still using
the model, and then I'll set Q(a) to be
equal to that average and so this is my estimate
for R(s)I + G(this expected value for that
specific action A). Then I'll take the maximum
of actions A and this gives me YI, and so
YI is for S for that. And finally, I'll run really
run linear regression which is that last of
the set [inaudible] to get V(s)I to be close to the
YIs. And so this algorithm is called fitted
value iteration and it actually often works quite
well for continuous, for problems with
anywhere from 6- to 10- to 20-dimensional
state spaces if you can choose appropriate
features. Can you raise a hand please if this
algorithm makes sense? Some of you didn't
have your hands up. Are there questions for
those, yeah?
Student: Is there a recess [inaudible]
function in this setup?
Oh, yes. An MDP comprises SA,
the state transition probabilities G and R
and so for continuous state spaces,
S would be like R4 for the inverted pendulum
or something. Actions with discretized state
transitions probabilities with specifying with
the model or the simulator, G is just a real
number like .99 and the real function is usually
a function that's given to you. And so the
reward function is some function of your
4-dimensional state, and for example,
you might choose a reward function to be
minus I don't know. Just for an example
of simple reward function, if we want a -1
if the pole has fallen and there it depends
on you choose your reward function to be -1
if the inverted pendulum falls over
and to find that its angle is greater than 30° or
something and zero otherwise. So that
would be an example of a reward function that
you can choose for the inverted pendulum,
but yes, assuming a reward function is given to
you so that you can compute R(s)I for any
state. Are there other questions?
Actually, let me try asking a question,
so everything I did here assume that we have a
stochastic simulator. So it turns out I can simply
this algorithm if I have a deterministic
simulator, but deterministic simulator is given a
stated action, my next state is always
exactly determined. So let me ask you, if I have
a deterministic simulator, how would I
change this algorithm? How would I simplify
this algorithm?
Student:Lower your samples
that you're drawing [inaudible].
Right, so Justin's going right.
If I have a deterministic simulator,
all my samples from those would
be exactly the same, and so if I have a
deterministic simulator, I can set K
to be equal to 1, so I don't need to draw
K different samples. I really only need
one sample if I have a deterministic simulator,
so you can simplify this by setting K=1
if you have a deterministic simulator. Yeah?
Student:I guess I'm really confused about the,
yeah, we sorta turned this [inaudible] into
something that looks like linear state regression
or some' you know the data transpose
times something that we're used to but I guess
I'm a little. I don't know really know what
question to ask but like when we did this before
we had like discrete states and
everything. We were determined with finding
this optimal policy and I guess it doesn't
look like we haven't said the word policy in a
while so kinda difficult.
Okay, yeah, so [inaudible] matters back
to policy but maybe I should just say
a couple words so let me actually try
to get at some of what maybe
what you're saying.
Our strategy for finding optimal policy has
been to find some way to find
V*, find some way to find the optimal value
function and then use that to compute ?
and some of approximations of ?*.
So far everything I've been doing
has been focused on how to find V*.
I just want to say one more word.
It actually turns out that for linear regression
it's often very easy.
It's often not terribly difficult
to choose some resource of the features.
Choosing features for approximating the value
function is often somewhat harder,
so because the value of a state is how good is
starting off in this state. What is my expected
sum of discounted rewards? What if I start in a
certain state? And so what the feature of
the state have to measure is really how good is
it to start in a certain state? And so for
inverted pendulum you actually have that states
where the poles are vertical and when a
cart that's centered on your track or something,
maybe better and so you can come up
with features that measure the orientation of the
pole and how close you are to the center
of the track and so on and those will be
reasonable features to use to approximate V*.
Although in general it is true that choosing
features, the value function approximation, is
often slightly trickier than choosing good
features for linear regression.
Okay and then Justin's questions of
so given V*, how do you go back to actually
find a policy? In the discrete case, so we have
that ?*(s) is equal to all [inaudible] over A of
that. So that's again, I used to write this as a
sum over states [inaudible]. I'll just write
this as an expectation and so then once you find
the optimal value function V*, you can
then find the optimal policy ?* by computing
the [inaudible]. So if you're in a continuous
state MDP, then you can't actually do this in
advance for every single state because
there's an infinite number of states and so you
can't actually perform this computation in
advance to every single state.
What you do instead is whenever your robot is
in some specific state S is only when your
system is in some specific state S like your car
is at some position orientation or your
inverted pendulum is in some specific position,
posed in some specific angle T. It's only
when your system, be it a factor or a board
game or a robot, is in some specific state S
that you would then go ahead and compute this
augmax, so it's only when you're in some
state S that you then compute this augmax, and
then you execute that action A and then
as a result of your action, your robot would
transition to some new state and then so it'll
be given that specific new state that you
compute as augmax using that specific state S
that you're in.
There're a few ways to do it. One way to do
this is actually the same as in the inner loop
of the fitted value iteration algorithm so
because of an expectation of a large number of
states, you'd need to sample some set of states
from the simulator and then approximate
this expectation using an average over your
samples, so it's actually as inner loop of the
value iteration algorithm. So you could do that.
That's sometimes done. Sometimes it can
also be a pain to have to sample a set of states
to approximate those expectations every
time you want to take an action in your MDP.
Couple of special cases where this can be done,
one special case is
if you have a deterministic simulator.
If it's a deterministic simulator, so in
other words, if your similar is just
some function, could be a linear or a nonlinear
function. If it's a deterministic simulator
then the next state, ST+1, is just some function
of your previous stated action.
If that's the case then this expectation, well,
then this simplifies to
augmax of A of V* of F of I guess S,
A because this is really saying S
prime=F(s),A. I switched back and forth
between notation; I hope that's okay. S to
denote the current state,
and S prime to deterministic state
versus ST and ST+1 through
the current state. Both of these are sorta
standing notation and don't mind my switching
back and forth between them. But if it's a
deterministic simulator you can then just
compute what the next state S prime would be
for each action you might take from the current
state, and then take the augmax of actions
A, basically choose the action that gets you to
the highest value state.
And so that's one case where you can compute
the augmax and we can compute that
expectation without needing to sample an
average over some sample. Another very
common case actually it turns out is if you have
a stochastic simulator, but if your similar
happens to take on a very specific form of
ST+1=F(s)T,AT+?T
where this is galsie noise.
The [inaudible] is a very common way to build
simulators where you model the next state
as a function of the current state and action plus
some noise and so once specific example
would be that sort of mini dynamical system
that we talked about with linear function of
the current state and action plus galsie noise.
In this case, you can approximate augment
over A, well.
In that case you take that expectation that
you're trying to approximate. The expected
value of V* of S prime, we can approximate
that with V* of the expected value of S
prime, and this is approximation. Expected
value of a function is usually not equal to the
value of an expectation but it is often a
reasonable approximation and so that would be
another way to approximate that expectation
and so you choose the actions according to
watch we do the same formula as I wrote just
now. And so this would be a way of
approximating this augmax, ignoring the noise
in the simulator essentially. And this often
works pretty well as well just because many
simulators turn out to be the form of some
linear or some nonlinear function plus zero
mean galsie noise, so and just that ignore the
zero mean galsie noise, so that you can
compute this quickly.
And just to complete about this, what that is,
right, that V* F of SA, this you down rate as
data transfers Fi of S prime where S prime=F of
SA. Great, so this V* you would
compute using the parameters data that you just
learned using the fitted value iteration
algorithm. Questions about this?
Student:[Inaudible] case, for real-time
application is it possible to use that [inaudible],
for example for [inaudible].
Yes, in real-time applications is it possible to
sample case phases use [inaudible] expectation.
Computers today actually amazingly fast.
I'm actually often surprised by how much
you can do in real time so the helicopter
we actually flying a helicopter using
an algorithm different than this? I can't say.
But my intuition is that you could actually
do this with a helicopter. A helicopter would
control at somewhere between 10hz and 50hz.
You need to do this 10 times a second to 50
times a second, and that's actually plenty
of time to sample 1,000 states
and compute this expectation.
They're real difficult, helicopters because
helicopters are mission critical, and you do
something it's like fast. You can do serious
damage and so maybe not for good reasons.
We've actually tended to avoid tossing coins
when we're in the air, so the ideal of letting
our actions be some up with some random
process is slightly scary and just tend not to do
that. I should say that's probably not a great
reason because you average a large number of
things here very well fine but just as a maybe
overly conservative design choice, we
actually don't, tend not to find anything
randomized on which is prob'ly being over
conservative. It's the choice we made 'cause
other things are slightly safer. I think you
can actually often do this.
So long as I see a model can be evaluated fast
enough where you can sample 100 state
transitions or 1,000 state transitions, and then
do that at 10hz. They haven't said that.
This is often attained which is why we often
use the other approximations that don't
require your drawing a large sample. Anything
else? No, okay, cool. So now you know
one algorithm [inaudible] reinforcement
learning on continuous state spaces. Then we'll
pick up with some more ideas on some even
more powerful algorithms, the solving
MDPs of continuous state spaces.
Thanks. Let's close for today.