Okay. So good morning and welcome back.
What I want to do today is
actually begin a new chapter in 229
in which I'm gonna start to talk about
So today is I'm gonna just very briefly
talk about clustering's, algorithm. [Inaudible]
and a special case of the EM, Expectation
Maximization, algorithm with a mixture of
[inaudible] model to describe something called
Jensen and Equality
and then we'll use that derive a general form
of something called the EM
or the Expectation Maximization algorithm,
which is a very useful algorithm.
We sort of use it
all over the place and different
unsupervised machine or any application.
So the cartoons that I used to draw for
supervised learning was you'd be given the
data set like this, right, and you'd use
[inaudible] between the positive
and negativecrosses
and we'd call it the supervised learning
because you're sort of told what the
right cross label is for every training example,
and that was the supervision.
In unsupervised learning,
we'll study a different problem.
You're given a data set
that maybe just comprises a set of points.
You're just given a data set with no labels
and no indication of what the "right answers"
or where the supervision is and it's the job of
the algorithm to discover structure in the data.
So in this lecture and the next couple of weeks
we'll talk about a variety of
unsupervised learning algorithms
that can look at data sets like these and discover
there's different types of structure in it.
In this particular cartoonthat I've drawn
one has the structure that you and I can
probably see as is that this data lives in two
different crosses and so the first unsupervised
learning algorithm that I'm just gonna talk
about will be a clustering algorithm.
It'll be an algorithm that looks for a data set like
this and automatically breaks the data set
into different smaller clusters.
So let's see.
When my laptop comes back up,
I'll show you an example.
So clustering algorithms like these
have a variety of applications.
Just to rattle off a few of the better-known ones
I guess in biology application
you often cross the different things here.
You have [inaudible] genes
and they cluster the different genes together
in order to examine them
and understand the biological function better.
Another common application of clustering
is market research.
So imagine you have a customer database of
how your different customers behave.
It's a very common practice to apply clustering
algorithms to break your database of
customers into different market segments so
that you can target your products towards
different market segments
and target your sales pitches
specifically to different market segments.
Something we'll do later today
I don't want to do this now,
but you actually go to a website,
like, use.google.com
and that's an example of a website that uses
a clustering algorithm to everyday group
related news articles together to display to you
so that you can see one of the thousand news
articles today on whatever the top story of
today is and all the 500 news articles on all the
different websites on different story of the day.
And a very solid [inaudible] actually
talks about image segmentation,
which the application of when you might take a
picture and group together different subsets of
the picture into coherent pieces of pixels to try
to understand what's contained in the picture.
So that's yet another application of clustering.
The next idea is given a data set like this,
given a set of points,
can you automatically group the data sets
into coherent clusters.
Let's see.
I'm still waiting for the laptop to come back
so I can show you an example.
You know what, why don't I just start to
write out the specific clustering algorithm
and then I'll show you the animation later.
So this is the called the k-means clustering
algorithm for finding clustering's near the inset.
The input to the algorithm will be
an unlabeled data set
which I write as X1, X2, [inaudible]
and because we're now
talking about unsupervised learning,
you see a lot of this as [inaudible] with
just the Xs
and no cross labels Y.
So what a k-means algorithm
does is the following.
This will all make a bit more sense
when I show you the animation on my laptop.
To initialize a set of points,
called the cluster centroids,
[inaudible] randomly
and so if you're [inaudible] of training data are
[inaudible] then your cluster centroids, these
muse, will also be vectors and [inaudible]
and then you repeat
until convergence the following two steps.
So the cluster centroids will be your guesses for
where the centers of each of the clusters are
and so in one of those steps you look at each
point, XI and you look at which cluster centroid J
is closest to it and then this step is called
assigning your point XI to cluster J.
So looking at each point
and picking the cluster centroid
that's closest to it
and the other step is you update the cluster
centroids to be the median of all the points
that have been assigned to it.
Okay. Let's see. Could you please
bring down the display for the laptop?
Okay. Okay. There we go.
Okay. So here's an example of
the k-means algorithm
and hope the animation will make more sense.
This is an inch chopped off.
This is basically an example
I got from Michael Jordan in Berkley.
So these points in green are my data points
and so I'm going to randomly initialize
a pair of cluster centroids.
So the [inaudible] blue crosses to
note the positions of New1 and New2
say if I'm going to guess
that there's two clusters in this data.
Sets of k-means algorithms as follow.
I'm going to repeatedly go to all of the points in
my data set and I'm going to associate each of
the green dots with the closer of the two cluster
centroids, so visually, I'm gonna denote that by
painting each of the dots either blue or red
depending on which is the closer cluster centroid.
Okay. So all the points closer to the
blue cross points are
painted blue and so on.
The other step is updating the cluster centroids
and so I'm going to repeatedly look at all
the points that I've painted blue
and compute the average of all of the blue dots,
and I'll look at all the red dots
and compute the average of all the red dots
and then I move the cluster centroids as follows
to the average of the respective locations.
So this is now [inaudible] of k-means on here,
and now I'll repeat the same process.
I look at all the points and assign all the points
closer to the blue cross to the color blue
and similarly red.
And so now I have that assignments of points to
the cluster centroids and finally, I'll again compute
the average of all the blue points and compute
the average of all the red points and update the
cluster centroids again as follows
and now k-means is actually [inaudible].
If you keep running these two sets of k-means
over and over, the cluster centroids and the
assignment of the points closest to the cluster
centroids will actually remain the same.
Yeah.
[Inaudible]
Yeah, I'll assign that in a second.
Yeah. Okay.
So [inaudible]. Take a second to look at this again
and make sure you understand how the algorithm
I wrote out maps onto the animation
that we just saw.
Do you have a question?
[Inaudible]
I see. Okay. Let me answer on that in a second.
Okay. So these are the two steps.
This step 2.1 was assigning
the points to the closest centroid
and 2.2 was shifting the cluster centroid to be the
mean of all the points assigned
to that cluster centroid.
Okay. Okay. [Inaudible] questions that we just had,
one is, does the algorithm converge?
The answer is yes,
k-means is guaranteed to
converge in a certain sense.
In particular, if you define the distortion function
to be J of C [inaudible] squared.
You can define the distortion function
to be a function of the cluster assignments,
and the cluster centroids and [inaudible] square
distances, which mean the points and the cluster
centroids that they're assigned to,
then you can show I won't really prove this here
but you can show that k-means is called
[inaudible] on the function J. In particular,
who remembers, it's called in a sense as
an authorization algorithm, I don't know,
maybe about two weeks ago,
so called in a sense is the algorithm
that we'll repeatedly [inaudible] with respect to C.
Okay. So that's called [inaudible].
And so what you can prove is
that k-means the two steps of k-means,
are exactly optimizing this function with respect
to C and will respect a new alternately.
And therefore, this function, J of C, new,
must be decreasing monotonically
on every other variation
and so the sense in which k-means converges is
that this function, J of C, new, can only go down
and therefore, this function
will actually eventually converge in the sense
that it will stop going down.
Okay. It's actually possible that there may be
several clustering's they give the same value of J
of C, new and so k-means may actually switch back and
forth between different clustering's that they [inaudible]
in the extremely unlikely case, if there's multiple
clustering's, they give exactly
the same value for this objective function.
K-means may also be [inaudible]
it'll just never happen.
That even if that happens,
this function J of C, new will converge.
Another question was
how do you choose the number of clusters?
So it turns out that in the vast majority of time
when people apply k-means,
you still just randomly pick a number of clusters
or you randomly try a few
different numbers of clusters
and pick the one
that seems to work best.
The number of clusters in this algorithm
instead of just one parameters,
so usually I think
it's not very hard to choose automatically.
There are some automatic ways of
choosing the number of clusters,
but I'm not gonna talk about them.
When I do this,
I usually just pick of
the number of clusters randomly.
And the reason is
I think for many clustering problems the "true"
number of clusters is actually ambiguous
so for example
if you have a data set that looks like this,
some of you may see four clusters, right,
and some of you may see two clusters,
and so the right answer for the
actual number of clusters is sort of ambiguous.
Yeah.
[Inaudible]. [Inaudible] clusters [inaudible] far
away from the data point [inaudible] points
and the same cluster?
I see.
Right. So yes. K-means is susceptible
to [inaudible] so this function,
J of C, new is not a convex function
and so k-means, sort of called in a sense
on the non-convex function is not guaranteed to
converge the [inaudible].
So k-means is susceptible to
local optimal and [inaudible].
One thing you can do is
try multiple random initializations
and then run clustering a bunch of times
and pick the solution
that ended up with
the lowest value for the distortion function.
Yeah.
[Inaudible]
Yeah, let's see.
Right. So what if one cluster centroid
has no points assigned to it,
again, one thing you could do
is just eliminate it exactly the same.
Another thing you can is you can just reinitialize
randomly if you really [inaudible].
More questions.
[Inaudible]
I see.
Right. Is it usually two norms?
Let's see. For the vast majority of applications
I've seen for k-means, you do take two norms
when you have data [inaudible].
I'm sure there are others who
have taken infinity norm and one norm as well.
I personally haven't seen that very often,
but there are other variations
on this algorithm that use different norms,
but the one I described is probably
the most commonly used there is.
Okay. So that was k-means clustering.
What I want to do next and this will take longer to
describe is actually talk about
a closely related problem.
In particular, what I wanted to do
was talk about density estimation.
As another k-means example, this is a problem
that I know some guys that worked on.
Let's say you have aircraft engine
building off an assembly.
Let's say you work for an aircraft company,
you're building aircraft engines off
the assembly line and as the aircraft engines
roll off the assembly line, you test these aircraft
engines and measure various different
properties of it and to use [inaudible] example
I'm gonna write these properties
as heat and vibrations.
Right. In reality, you'd measure different
vibrations, different frequencies and so on.
We'll just write the amount of
heat produced and vibrations produced.
Let's say that maybe it looks like
that and what you would like to do is
estimate the density of
these [inaudible] of the joint distribution,
the amount of heat produced
and the amount of vibrations
because you would like to detect [inaudible]
so that as a new aircraft engine rolls off
the assembly line, you can then measure
the same heat and vibration properties.
If you get a point there,
you can then ask,
"How likely is it that there was
an undetected flaw in this aircraft engine
that it needs to go undergo further inspections?"
And so if we look at
the typical distribution of features we get,
and we build a model for P of X
and then if P of X is very small
for some new aircraft engine
then that would raise a red flag
and we'll say there's an anomaly aircraft engine
and we should subject it to further inspections
before we let someone fly with the engine.
So this problem I just described is
an instance of what is called anomaly detection
and so a common way of
doing anomaly detection is
to take your training set
and from this data set, build a model, P of X of the
density of the typical data you're saying
and if you ever then see an example
with very low probability under P of X,
then you may flag that as an anomaly example.
Okay? So anomaly detection is also
used in security applications.
If many, very unusual transactions
to start to appear on my credit card,
that's a sign to me that someone
has stolen my credit card.
And what I want to do now is talk about specific
algorithm for density estimation,
and inparticular,
one that works with data sets likethese,
that, you know,
this distribution like this doesn't really fall into
any of the standard text book distributions.
This is not really, like, a Gaussian
or a [inaudible] explanation or anything.
So can we come up with a model to
estimate densities that may look like
these somewhat unusual shapes?
Okay. So to describe the algorithm a bit a more
I'm also going to use a one dimensional example
rather than a two D example,
and in the example that I'm going to describe I'm
going to say that let's imagine maybe a data set
that looks like this
where the horizontal access here is the X axis
and these dots represent
the positions of the data set that I have.
Okay.
So this data set looks like
it's maybe coming from a density
that looks like that as if this was
the sum of two Gaussian distributions
and so the specific model I'm gonna describe will
be what's called a mixture of Gaussian's model.
And just be clear that the picture I have is that
when visioning that maybe there were two
separate Gaussian's that generated this data set,
and if only I knew what the two Gaussian's were,
then I could put a Gaussian to my crosses,
put a Gaussian to the Os
and then sum those up to get
the overall density for the two,
but the problem is
I don't actually have access to these labels.
I don't actually know which of the
two Gaussian's each of my data points came from
and so what I'd like to do is come up with an
algorithm to fit this mixture of Gaussian's model
even when I don't know which of the
two Gaussian's each of my data points came from.
Okay. So here's the idea.
In this model,
I'm going to imagine
there's a latent random variable,
latent is just synonymous with
hidden or unobserved,
okay. So we're gonna imagine
there's a latent random variable Z
and XI, ZI have a joint distribution
that is given as follows.
We have that P of X, ZI by the chamber of
probability, this is always like that.
This is always true.
And moreover, our [inaudible] is given by
the following ZI is distributed
multinomial with parameters I.
And in the special case where I have just to
make sure that two Gaussian's and ZI will be
and so these parameter [inaudible] are
the parameters of a multinomial distribution.
And the distribution of XI conditioned on ZI being
equal to J so it's P of XI given ZI is equal to J.
That's going to be a Gaussian distribution
with [inaudible] and covariant sigler.
Okay. So this should actually
look extremely familiar to you.
What I've written down are pretty much the same
equations that I wrote down for
the Gaussian Discriminant Analysis algorithm
that we saw way back, right,
except that the differences instead of,
I guess supervised learning
where we were given the cross labels Y,
I've now replaced Y in Gaussian Discriminant
Analysis with these latent random variables
or these unobserved random variables Z,
and we don't actually know
what the values of Z are.
Okay. So just to make the link to the Gaussian
Discriminant Analysis even a little more explicit
if we knew what the Zs were,
which was actually don't,
but suppose for the sake of argument
that we actually knew which of,
say the two Gaussian's,
each of our data points came from,
then you can use [inaudible] estimation –
you can write down the likelihood
the parameters which would be that
and you can then use [inaudible] estimation
and you get exactly the same formula as
in Gaussian Discriminant Analysis.
Okay. So if you knew the value of the Z,
you can write down the law of likelihood
and do maximum likeliness this way,
and you can then estimate
all the parameters of your model.
Does this make sense?
Raise your hand if this makes sense.
Cool. Some of you have questions?
Some of you didn't raise your hands.
Yeah.
So this ZI is just a label, like, an X or an O?
Yes. Basically.
Any other questions?
Okay. So if you knew the values of Z,
the Z playing a similar role to the cross labels
in Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis,
then you could use maximum
likeliness estimation parameters.
But in reality,
we don't actually know the values of the Zs.
All we're given is
this unlabeled data set
and so let me write down
the specific bootstrap procedure
in which the idea is
that we're going to use our model to
try and guess what the values of Z is.
We don't know our Z,
but we'll just take a guess at the values of Z
and we'll then use some of the values of Z that we
guessed to fit the parameters of the rest of the
model and then we'll actually iterate. And now
that we have a better estimate for the parameters
for the rest of the model, we'll then take another
guess for what the values of Z are.
And then we'll sort of use something like
the maximum likeliness estimation
to set even parameters of the model.
So the algorithm I'm gonna write down is
called the EM Algorithm
and it proceeds as follows.
Repeat until convergence
and the E set,
we're going to guess the values of the unknown ZIs
and in particular, I'm going to set WIJ. Okay.
So I'm going to compute the probability
that ZI is equal to J.
So I'm going to use the
rest of the parameters in my model
and then I'm gonna compute the probability
that point XI came from Gaussian number J.
And just to be sort of concrete about
what I mean by this, this means that I'm going to
compute P of XI. This step is sort of [inaudible], I
guess. And again, just to be completely concrete
about what I mean about this, the [inaudible] rate
of P of XI given ZI equals J, you know,
well that's the Gaussian density. Right?
from O equals 1 to K ofof essentially the same
That's one over E to the –and then divided by sum
thing, but with J replaced by L. Okay. for
the Gaussian and the numerator and the sum of
the similar terms of the denominator.
Excuse me. This is the sum from O equals 1
through K in the denominator.
Okay. Let's see. The maximization step
where you would then update
your estimates of the parameters.
So I'll just lay down the formulas here.
When you see these, you should compare them
to the formulas we had for
maximum likelihood estimation.
And so these two formulas on top are very similar
to what you saw for Gaussian Discriminant Analysis
except that now, we have these [inaudible]
so WIJ is you remember was the probability that
we computed that point I came from Gaussian's.
I don't want to call it cluster J,
but that's what point I came from Gaussian J,
rather than an indicator for
where the point I came from Gaussian J.
Okay. And the one slight difference
between this and the formulas who
have a Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis is
that in the mixture of Gaussian's,
we more commonly use different covariant
[inaudible] for the different Gaussian's.
So in Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis,
sort of by convention,
you usually model all of the crosses
to the same covariant matrix sigma.
when you dealing with Gaussian model
this sort of, not always, but some time
you are allowed the coherence matrix
with different Gaussian areas
for this formulation we have different coherence matrix sigma J
and that is responding to the Gaussian analysis
Why don't you just take a second
to look at this and make sure it all makes sense?
Do you have questions about this?
Raise your hand if this makes sense to you?
[Inaudible]. Okay. Only some of you.
Let's see.
So let me try to explain that a little bit more.
Some of you recall
that in Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis,
right, if we knew the values for the ZIs so let's see.
Suppose I was to give you labeled data sets,
suppose I was to tell you
the values of the ZIs for each example,
then I'd be giving you a data set that looks like this.
Okay. So here's my 1 D data set.
That's sort of a typical 1 D
Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis.
So for Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis
we figured out the maximum likeliness estimation
and the maximum likeliness estimate
for the parameters of GDA,
and one of the estimates for
the parameters for GDA was [inaudible]
which is the probability that ZI equals J.
You would estimate
that as sum of I equals sum of I from 1 to M indicator
ZI equals J and divide by N. Okay.
When we're deriving GDA, [inaudible].
If you knew the cross labels
for every example you cross,
then this was your maximum likeliness estimate for
the chance that the labels came from the positive
[inaudible] versus the negative [inaudible].
It's just a fraction of examples.
Your maximum likeliness estimate for probability of
getting examples from cross J is just the fraction of
examples in your training set
that actually came from cross J.
So this is the maximum likeliness estimation for
Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis.
Now, in the mixture of Gaussian's model
and the EM problem
we don't actually have these cross labels, right,
we just have an unlabeled
data set like this.
We just have a set of dots.
I'm trying to draw the same data set
that I had above,
but just with the cross labels.
So now, it's as if you only get to observe the XIs,
but the ZIs are unknown.
Okay. So the cross label is unknown.
So in the EM algorithm
we're going to try to take a guess for
the values of the ZIs,
and specifically, in the E step we computed WIJ
was our current best guess for the probability
that ZI equals J given that data point.
Okay. So this just means given my current hypothesis,
the way the Gaussian's are, and given everything
what was the [inaudible] probability that the point XI
else, can I compute the [inaudible] probability –
actually came from cross J? What is the probability
that this point was a cross versus O?
What's the probability that this point was [inaudible]?
And now in the M step,
my formula of estimating for the parameters
[inaudible] will be given by 1 over M sum from I
equals 1 through M, sum of WIJ. So WIJ is right. The
probability is my best guess for the probability that
point I belongs to Gaussian or belongs to cross J,
and [inaudible] using this formula instead of this one.
Okay. And similarly,
this is my formula for the estimate for new J
and it replaces the WIJs with
these new indicator functions,
you get back to the formula
that you had in Gaussian's Discriminant Analysis.
I'm trying to convey an intuitive sense of
why these algorithm's make sense.
Can you raise your hand if this makes sense now?
Cool.
So that's introduction of the EM algorithm,
it turns out that the way I came out from this formular.
this is actually same generation of EM algorithm,
which we'll talk about next.
So I hope this is efficient which can do the sense.
but it exactly where it came from.
It a question of answer of data.
Okay. So what I want to do now is actually
present a broader view of the EM algorithm.
What you just saw was a special case of
the EM algorithm for specially to
make sure of Gaussian's model,
and in the remaining half hour I have today
I'm going to describe a general description of the EM
algorithm and everything you just saw will be
devised, sort of there's a special case of this more
general view that I'll present now.
And as a pre-cursor to actually deriving
this more general view of the EM algorithm,
I'm gonna have to describe
something called Jensen's and Equality
that we use in the derivation.
So here's Jensen's and Equality.
Just let F be a convex function.
So a function is a convex of the second derivative,
which I've written F prime prime to [inaudible].
The functions don't have to
be differentiatable to be convex,
but if it has a second derivative,
then F prime prime should be creating a 0.
And let X be a random variable
then the F applied to the expectation of X is less than
the equal of 2D expectation of F of F.
Okay. And hopefully you remember
I often drop the square back,
so E of X is the [inaudible],
I'll often drop the square brackets.
So let me draw a picture that would explain this
and I think Many of my friends and I often don't
remember is less than or great than or whatever,
and the way that many of us remember the sign of
that in equality is by drawing the following picture.
For this example,
let's say, X is equal to 1 with a probability of one-half
and X is equal to 6 worth probability 1 whole.
So I'll illustrate this inequality with an example.
So let's see. So X is 1 with probability one-half
and X is 6 with probably with half
and so the expected value of X is 3.5.
It would be in the middle here.
So that's the expected value of X.
The horizontal axis here is the X axis.
And so F of the expected value of X,
you can read of as this point here.
So this is F of the expected value of X.
Where as in contrast, let's see.
If X is equal to 1 then here's F of 1
and if X equaled a 6 then here's F of 6
and the expected value of F of X,
it turns out, is now averaging on the vertical axis.
We're 50 percent chance you get F of 1
with 50 percent chance you get F of 6
and so these expected value of F of X
is the average of F of 1 and F of 6,
which is going to be the value in the middle here.
And so in this example you see that the expected value
of F of X is greater than
or equal to F of the expected value of X.
Okay.
So the illustration why this cause in this case.
And it turns out further
that if F double prime of X makes [inaudible]
than Z row,
if this happens,
we say F is strictly convex
then the inequality holds
an equality or in other words,
E of F of X equals F of EX,
if and only if, X is a constant with probability 1.
Well, another way of writing this is X equals EX.
Okay. So in other words,
if F is a strictly convex function,
then the only way for this inequality to hold its
equality is if the random variable X
always takes on the same value.
if X=E[x],probably one of the this one estating.
Em,further,so thus state for concave fuctions.
then everything holds the direction of the any quality of verse.
It turns out that if f''《=0.the effort of concave.
So f''(Ex)>=E[f(x)],etc.
So you just if you hava concave of function.
then all the qualities hold the same way,
because the direction in quality of verse.
and it turn out later on we will derive the EM algorithm
why use that concave version,would this quality verse.
Okay. Any questions about this? Yeah.
[Inaudible]
Say that again?
[inaudible]?
What is the strictly convex [inaudible]?
I still couldn't hear that. What is –
Oh, I see.
If double prime of X is strictly greater than 0
that's my definition for strictly convex.
If the second derivative of X is strictly greater than 0
then that's what it means for F to be strictly convex.
[Inaudible]
I see. Sure.
So for example,
this is an example of a convex function
that's not strictly convexed
because there's part of this function is a straight line
and so F double prime would be zero in this portion.
Let's see. Yeah.
It's just a less formal way of saying strictly convexed
just means that you can't
have a convex function within a straight line portion
and then [inaudible]. Speaking very informally, think
of this as meaning that there aren't
any straight line portions. Okay.
So here's the derivation
for the general version of EM.
The problem was face is as follows.
We have some model for
the joint distribution of X of Z,
but we observe only X,
and our goal is to maximize
the law of likelihood of the parameters of model.
Right. So we have some models
for the joint distribution for X and Z
and our goal is to find the
maximum likeliness estimate of the parameters data
where the likelihood is defined as something equals 1
to M [inaudible] probably of our data as usual.
And here X is parameterized by data is now given
by a sum over all the values
of ZI parameterized by data. Okay.
So just by taking our model of
the joint distribution of X and Z
and marginalizing out ZI
that we get P of XI parameterized by data.
And so the EM algorithm will be a way of performing
this maximum likeliness estimation problem,
which is complicated by the fact that we have
these ZIs in our model that are unobserved.
Before I actually do the math,
here's a useful picture to keep in mind.
So the horizontal axis in this cartoon
is the [inaudible] axis and there's some function,
the law of likelihood of theta zero
that we're trying to maximize,
and usually maximizing our [inaudible] derivatives
instead of the zero
that would be very hard to do.
What the EM algorithm will do is the following.
Let's say it initializes some value of theta zero,
what the EM algorithm will end up doing is
it will construct a lower bound
for this law of likelihood function
and this lower bound will be tight [inaudible] of
equality after current guessing the parameters
and they maximize this lower boundary
with respect to theta
so we'll end up with say that value.
So that will be data 1.
Okay. And then EM algorithm look at theta 1
and they'll construct a new lower bound of theta
and then we'll maximize that.
So you jump here.
So that's the next theta 2
and you do that again
and you get the same 3, 4,
and so on until you converge to
local optimum on [inaudible] theta function.
Okay. So this is a cartoon that displays
what the EM algorithm will do.
So let's actually make that formal now.
So you want to maximize with respect to theta sum
of [inaudible] there's my theta, so this is sum over
1 [inaudible] sum over all values of Z.
Okay. So what I'm going to do is multiply
and divide by the same thing
and I'm gonna write this as Q okay.
So I'm going to construct the
probability distribution QI, that would be over
the latent random variables ZI
and so these QI would get distribution
so each of the QI would bring in a 0
and sum over all the values of ZI of QI would be 1,
so these Qs will be a probability distribution
that I get to construct.
Okay. And then I'll later go describe
the specific choice of this distribution QI.
So this QI is a probability distribution
over the random variables of ZI
so this is [inaudible].
some of the probable Z(i) times some functional Z(i)
So this innersermation is really an expectation
is really the expected value of that. of this one.
While the expectation is the
distribution of the random variable z^((i) )
draw the distribution Q_i
It wasn't mean that we task the expected value of this formula
just some [inaudible] of the probable z^((i) ) times that functional z^((i) )
Right. I see some frowns.
Do you have questions about this?
No. Okay.
So the log function looks like that
and there's a concave function
so that tells us that the log of E of X is greater than
and equal to the expected value of log X by the
other concave function form of Jensen's and Equality.
And so continuing from the previous expression,
this is a summary of a log and an expectation,
that must therefore be greater than or equal to
the expected value of the log of that.
Okay.
Using Jensen's and Equality.
And lastly just to expand out this formula again.
This is equal to that.
Okay. Yeah.
[Inaudible]
Yeah. Okay.
So this has the [inaudible] so let's say Random
variable Z, right, and Z has some distribution.
Let's denote it P.
And let's say I have some function G of Z.
Okay. Then by definition,
the expected value of G of Z, by definition, that's
equal to sum over all the values of Z, the probability
of that value of Z times Z of G. Right.
That's sort of the definition of a random variable.
And so the way I got from
this step to this step is by using that.
So in particular,
now, I've been using distribution QI
to denote the distribution of Z,
so this is, like, sum over Z of P of Z times [inaudible].
And so this is just the expected value with respect to
a random variable Z joined from
the distribution Q of G of Z.
Are there questions?
So in general when you're
doing maximum likelihood estimations,
the likelihood of the data,
but in this case you only say probability of X
because you only have observed X whereas
previously we said probability of X given the labels?
Yes. Exactly. Right. Right.
[Inaudible] we want to choose
the parameters that maximizes
the probability of the data,
and in this case, our data comprises only the Xs
because we don't reserve the Zs,
and therefore, the likelihood of parameters
is given by the probability of the data, which is [inaudible].
So this is all we've done, right,
we wanted to maximize the law of likelihood of theta
and what we've done, through these manipulations,
we've know constructed a lower bound
on the law of likelihood of data.
Okay. And in particular, this formula that we came up,
we should think of this as a function of theta then,
theta are the parameters of your model, right,
if you think about this
as a function of your parameters theta,
what we've just shown is
that the law of likelihood of your parameters theta
is lower bounded by this thing.
Okay. Remember that cartoon of repeatedly
constructing a lower bound
and optimizing the lower bound.
So what we've just done is construct a lower bound
for the law of likelihood for theta.
Now, the last piece we want for this lower bound is
actually we want this inequality to hold with equality for
the current value for theta.
So just refrain back to the previous cartoon.
If this was the law of likelihood for theta,
we'd then construct some lower bound of it,
some function of theta
and if this is my current value for theta,
then I want my lower bound to be tight.
I want my lower bound to be equal to
the law of likelihood of theta
because that's what I need to guarantee
that when I optimize my lower bound,
then I'll actually do even better on
the true objective function.
and so to do that,to ensure that any equality
actually hold the equal of equality.
what I need is going back the [inaudible].
What I need is in the steps that I use the [inaudible] of quality,
I need these any quatity to hold of equality.
and particular I am going to choose my distribute-
so these hold ture for any probility
distribution cute that am I choose.
and so what I am going to do is I choose
my probility ditribution Q to ensure
that this any qulity holds ture if equality
for my current value for data.
Yeah.
[inaudible]
Excuse me. Yeah. Great question.
How do I know that function is concave?
Yeah. I don't think I've shown it.
It actually turns out to be true for
all the models we work with.
Do I know that the law of bound
is a concave function of theta?
I think you're right.
In general, this may not be a concave function of theta.
For many of the models we work with,
this will turn out to be a concave function,
but that's not always true.
Okay. So let me go ahead and choose a value for Q.
And I'll refer back to Jensen's and Equality.
We said that this inequality will become an equality
if the random variable inside is a constant.
Right. If you're taking an expectation
with respect to
constant valued variables.
So what we want is to choose
this distribution QI of ZIs
So that is equal to constant.
and by constant I mean these take on
the same value for all values of Zi.
no matter what Zi you plug in
you end up the same value for this special.
and so you'll set QI of Zi to be proportional to that,
right, to make sure this constant.
But also you know that this Zi must be-oh,excuse me,
that Qi must be for this distribution,
and so that sum of Zi is equal to 1.
and as all know this except must escape here.
that the choice is actually equal to-
So the QI of ZIs must sum to 1
and so to compute it you should just
take P of XI, ZI, parameterized by theta
and just normalize the sum to one.
There is a step that I'm skipping here
to show that this is really the right thing to do.
Hopefully, you'll just be convinced it's true.
For the actual steps that I skipped,
it's actually written out in the lecture notes.
So you then have the denominator, by definition, is that
and so by the definition of conditional probability QI of ZI
is just equal to P of ZI given XI and parameterized by theta.
Okay. And so to summarize the algorithm,
the EM algorithm has two steps.
And the E step,
we set, we choose the distributions QI,
so QI of ZI will set to be equal to
a P of ZI given [inaudible] by data.
That's the formula we just worked out.
And so by this step we've now created a lower bound
on the law of likelihood function that is now tight
at a current value of theta.
And in the M step,
we then optimize that lower bound with respect to
our parameters theta and specifically to
the [inaudible] of theta.
Okay. And so that's the EM algorithm.
I won't have time to do it today,
but I'll probably show this in the next lecture,
but the EM algorithm's that I wrote down for
the mixtures of Gaussian's algorithm
is actually a special case of this more general template
where the E step and the M step responded.
So pretty much exactly to this E step and this M step
that I wrote down.
The E step constructs this lower bound
and makes sure that it is tight to
the current value of theta.
That's in my choice of Q,
and then the M step optimizes
the lower bound with respect to [inaudible] data.
Okay. So lots more to say about this in the next lecture.
Let's check if there's any questions before we close.
No. Okay. Cool.
So let's wrap up for today
and we'll continue talking about this in the next session.