Instructor (Andrew Ng):Okay.
Good morning. Welcome back.
What I want to do today is actually
wrap up our discussion
on learning theory and sort of on
and I'm gonna start by talking about
Bayesian statistics
and regularization,
and then take a very brief digression
to tell you about online learning.
And most of today's lecture will
actually be on various pieces of that,
by applying machine learning
algorithms to problems like,
you know, like the project
or other problems you may go work on
after you graduate from this class.
But let's start the talk about
Bayesian statistics
and regularization.
So you remember from last week,
we started to talk about
learning theory and
we learned about bias and variance.
And I guess in the previous lecture,
we spent most of the previous lecture
talking about algorithms for model
selection and for feature selection.
We talked about cross-validation.Right?
So most of the methods we talked about
in the previous lecture were ways
for you to try to simplify the model.
So for example,
the feature selection algorithms
we talked about
gives you a way
to eliminate a number of features,
so as to reduce the number of
parameters you need to fit
and thereby reduce overfitting.
Right? You remember that?
So feature selection algorithms
choose a subset of the features
so that you have less parameters and
you may be less likely to overfit.
Right?
What I want to do today is to talk about
a different way to prevent overfitting.
And there's a method
called regularization and there's a way
that lets you keep all the parameters.
So here's the idea,
and I'm gonna illustrate this example
with, say, linear regression.
So you take the linear regression
model, the very first model
we learned about, right,
we said that we would choose the
parameters via maximum likelihood.
Right?
And that meant that, you know,
you would choose the parameters theta
that maximized the probability of the
data, which is parameters theta that
maximized the probability of
the data we observe. Right?
And so to give this
sort of procedure a name,
this is one example of
most common frequencies procedure,
and frequency,
you can think of sort of
as maybe one school of statistics.
And the philosophical view behind
writing this down was we envisioned
that there was some true parameter
theta out there that generated,
you know, the Xs and the Ys.
There's some true parameter theta
that govern housing prices,
Y is a function of X,
and we don't know
what the value of theta is,
and we'd like to
come up with some procedure
for estimating the value of theta.
Okay?
And so, maximum likelihood is just
one possible procedure for estimating
the unknown value for theta.
And the way you formulated this, you know
theta was not a random variable.Right?
That's what why said,
so theta is just some true value out
there. It's not random or anything,
we just don't know what it is,
and we have a procedure
called maximum likelihood
for estimating the value for theta.
So this is one example of what's called
a frequencies procedure.
The alternative to the, I guess,
the frequency school of statistics
is the Bayesian school,
in which we're gonna say that
we don't know what theta is,
and so we will put a prior
on theta. Okay?
So in the Bayesian school
students would say,
"Well don't know
What's the value of theta is
so let's represent our uncertainty
over theta with a prior."
So for example, our prior on theta
may be a Gaussian distribution with
mean zero and curvalence matrix
given by tau squared I. Okay?
And so actually, if I use S to denote
my training set, well right,
so theta represents my beliefs about
what the parameters are
in the absence of any data.
So not having seen any data,
theta represents, you know, what I
think theta it probably represents
what I think theta is most likely to be.
And so given the training set, S,
in the sort of Bayesian procedure,
we would, well, calculate the
probability, the posterior probability
by parameters given my training sets,
and let's write this on the next board.
So my posterior on my parameters
given my training set,
by Bayes' rule,
this will be proportional to, you know,
this. Right?
So by Bayes' rule.
Let's call it posterior.
And this distribution now represents
my beliefs about what theta is
after I've seen the training set.
And when you now want to
make a new prediction
on the price of a new house,
on the input X, I would say that, well,
the distribution over the possible
housing prices for this new house
I'm trying to estimate the price of,
say, given the size of the house,
the features of the house at X,
and the training set I had previously,
it is going to be given by an integral
over my parameters theta of probably of
Y given X comma theta and times the
posterior distribution of theta given
the training set. Okay?
And in particular,
if you want your prediction to be
the expected value of Y given the
input X in training set,
you would say
integrate over Y times the posterior.
Okay?
You would take an expectation of Y
with respect to your
posterior distribution. Okay?
And you notice that when I was
writing this down,
so with the Bayesian formulation,
and now started to write up here
Y given X comma theta
because this formula now is the
property of Y conditioned on the values
of the random variables X and theta.
So I'm no longer writing
semicolon theta, I'm writing comma
theta because I'm now
treating theta as a random variable.
So all of this is somewhat abstract
but this is and it turns out
actually let's check.
Are there questions about this?
No? Okay.
Let's try to make this more concrete.
It turns out that
for many problems,
both of these steps in the computation
are difficult
because if, you know, theta is an
N plus one-dimensional vector,
is an N plus one-dimensional
parameter vector,
then this is one an integral
over an N plus one-dimensional,
you know, over RN plus one.
And because numerically it's very
difficult to compute integrals over
very high dimensional spaces,
all right?
So usually this integral
actually usually it's hard to
compute the posterior in theta and
it's also hard to compute this integral
if theta is very high dimensional.
There are few exceptions
for which this can be done
in closed form,
but for many learning algorithms,
say, Bayesian logistic regression,
this is hard to do.
And so what's commonly done is to
take the posterior distribution
and instead of actually computing
a full posterior distribution, chi of
theta given S, we'll instead take this
quantity on the right-hand side
and just maximize this quantity
on the right-hand side.
So let me write this down.
So commonly,
instead of computing
the full posterior distribution,
we will choose the following. Okay?
We will choose
what's called the MAP estimate,
or the maximum a posteriori
estimate of theta,
which is the most likely value of theta,
most probable value of theta
onto your posterior distribution.
And that's just ont max chi of theta.
And then when you need to
make a prediction, you know,
you would just predict, say, well,
using your usual hypothesis
and using this MAP value of theta
in place of as the parameter vector
you'd choose.
Okay?
And notice,
the only difference between this and
standard maximum likelihood estimation
is that when you're choosing, you know,
the instead of choosing
the maximum likelihood value for theta,
you're instead maximizing this,
which is what you have
for maximum likelihood estimation,
and then times this other quantity
which is the prior. Right?
And let's see,
when intuition is that
if your prior is theta
being Gaussian and with mean zero
and some covariance,
then for a distribution like this,
most of the [inaudible] mass is
close to zero. Right?
So there's a Gaussian
centered around the point zero,
and so [inaudible] mass
is close to zero.
And so the prior distribution,
instead of saying that you think mostof
the parameters should be close to zero,
and if you remember our discussion
on feature selection,
if you eliminate a feature
from consideration
that's the same as
setting the source and value of theta
to be equal to zero.
All right?
So if you set
theta five to be equal to zero,
that's the same as, you know,
eliminating feature five
from the your hypothesis.
so, this is the prior that drives
most of the parameter values to zero –
to values close to zero.
And you'll think of this as
doing something analogous, if
doing something reminiscent
of feature selection.
Okay?
And it turns out that
with this formulation, the parameters
won't actually be exactly zero
but many of the values
will be close to zero.
And I guess in pictures,
if you remember,
I said that if you have, say,
five data points and you fit a
fourth-order polynomial
well I think that had too many bumps
in it, but never mind.
If you fit it a
if you fit very high polynomial
to a very small dataset,
you can get
these very large oscillations
if you use maximum likelihood
estimation. All right?
In contrast,
if you apply this
sort of Bayesian regularization,
you can actually fit a
higher-order polynomial
that still get sort of a smoother and
smoother fit to the data as you decrease
tau. So as you decrease tau,
you're driving the parameters
to be closer and closer to zero.
And that in practice
it's sort of hard to see,
but you can take my word for it.
As tau becomes smaller and smaller,
the curves you tend to fit your data
also become smoother and smoother,
and so you tend less and less overfit,
even when you're fitting
a large number of parameters.
Okay?
Let's see, and one last piece of
intuition that I would just toss out
there. And you get to play more with
this particular set of ideas more
in Problem Set 3,
which I'll post online
later this week I guess.
Is that whereas maximum likelihood
tries to minimize, say, this, right?
Whereas maximum likelihood for,
say, linear regression
turns out to be minimizing this,
it turns out that if you
add this prior term there,
it turns out that
the authorization objective you end up
optimizing turns out to be that.
Where you add an extra term that,
you know, penalizes your parameter
theta as being large.
And so this ends up being an algorithm
that's very similar to maximum
likelihood, expect that you
tend to keep your parameters small.
And this has the effect.
Again, it's kind of hard to see
but just take my word for it.
That strengthening the parameters
has the effect of keeping the functions
you fit to be smoother
and less likely to overfit. Okay?
Okay, hopefully this will make more
sense when you play with these ideas
a bit more in the next problem set.
But let's check questions
about all this.
Student:The smoothing behavior is it
because [inaudible] actually get
different
[inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Let's see.
Yeah. It depends on
well most priors with
most of the mass close to zero
will get this effect, I guess.
And just by convention,
the Gaussian prior is what's most
used the most common for models like
logistic regression and linear
regression, generalized in yourmodels.
There are a few other priors
that I sometimes use,
like the Laplace prior,
but all of them will tend to
have these sorts of smoothing effects.
All right. Cool.
And so it turns out that
for problems like text classification,
text classification is like 30,000
features or 50,000 features,
where it seems like an algorithm
like logistic regression would be
very much prone to overfitting. Right?
So imagine trying to
build a spam classifier,
maybe you have 100 training examples
but you have 30,000 features
or 50,000 features, that seems clearly
to be prone to overfitting. Right?
But it turns out that with
this sort of Bayesian regularization,
with [inaudible] Gaussian,
logistic regression becomes
a very effective text
classification algorithm
Alex?
Student:[Inaudible]?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah, right,
and so pick and to pick
either tau squared or lambda.
I think the relation is
lambda equals one over tau squared.
But right, so pick either
tau squared or lambda,
you could use cross-validation, yeah.
All right? Okay, cool.
So all right, that was all
I want to say about
methods for preventing overfitting.
What I want to do next is just
spend, you know, five minutes
talking about online learning.
And this is sort of a digression.
And so, you know,
when you're designing the syllabus of a
class, I guess, sometimes there are
just some ideas you want to talk about
but can't find a very good place
to fit in anywhere.
So this is one of those ideas
that may seem a bit disjointed
from the rest of the class
but I just want to
tell you a little bit about it.
Okay. So here's the idea.
So far, all the learning algorithms
we've talked about are what's
called batch learning algorithms,
where you're given a training set
and then you get to run your
learning algorithm on the training set
and then maybe you test it
on some other test set.
And there's another learning setting
called online learning,
in which you have to
make predictions even while you are
in the process of learning.
So here's how the problem sees.
All right?
I'm first gonna give you X one.
Let's say there's a classification
problem, so I'm first gonna give you X one
and then gonna ask you, you know,
"Can you make a prediction on X one?
Is the label one or zero?"
And you've not seen any data yet.
And so, you make a guess. Right?
You guess we'll call
your guess Y hat one.
And after you've made your prediction,
I will then reveal to you
the true label Y one. Okay?
And not having seen any data before,
your odds of getting the first one right
are only 50 percent, right,
if you guess randomly.
And then I show you X two.
And then I ask you,
"Can you make a prediction on X two?"
And so you now maybe are gonna
make a slightly
more educated guess
and call that Y hat two.
And after you've made your guess,
I reveal the true label to you.
And so, then I show you X three,
and then you make your guess,
and learning proceeds as follows.
So this is just a lot of machine
learning and batch learning,
and the model settings where you
have to keep learning even as
you're making predictions, okay?
So I don't know,
setting your website and
you have users coming in.
And as the first user comes in,
you need to start making predictions
already about what the user
likes or dislikes.
And there's only, you know, as you're
making predictions you get to show
more and more training examples.
So in online learning
what you care about is
the total online error,
which is sum from I equals one to MC if
you get the sequence of M examples
all together, indicator Y hat I not
equal to Y hi. Okay?
So the total online error is the total
number of mistakes you make on a
sequence of examples like this.
And it turns out that, you know,
many of the learning algorithms you
have when you finish all the
learning algorithms, you've learned
about and can apply to this setting.
One thing you could do is
when you're asked to make prediction
on Y hat three, right,
one simple thing to do is well you've
seen some other training examples up to
this point so you can just take your
learning algorithm and run it
on the examples, you know,
leading up to Y hat three.
So just run the learning algorithm on
all the examples you've seen previous
to being asked to make a prediction
on certain example, and then use your
learning algorithm to make a prediction
on the next example.
And it turns out that there are also
algorithms, especially the algorithms
that we saw that you could use the
stochastic gradient descent, that,
you know, can be adapted
very nicely to this.
So as a concrete example,
if you remember the perceptron
algorithms, say, right,
you would say initialize the parameter
theta to be equal to zero.
And then after seeing the Ith training
example, you'd update the parameters,
you know, using
you've see this reel a lot of times now,
right, using the
standard perceptron learning rule.
And the same thing,
if you were using logistic regression
you can then, again, after seeing each
training example, just run, you know,
essentially run one-step stochastic
gradient descent on just the example
you saw. Okay?
And so the reason I've put this
into the sort of "learning theory"
section of this class was because
it turns that sometimes you can prove
fairly amazing results
on your total online error
using algorithms like these.
I will actually I don't actually want
to spend the time in the main lecture
to prove this, but, for example,
you can prove that
when you use the perceptron algorithm,
then even when the features XI, maybe
infinite dimensional feature vectors,
like we saw for simple vector machines.
And sometimes,
infinite feature dimensional vectors
may use kernel representations. Okay?
But so it turns out that you can prove
that when you a perceptron algorithm,
even when the data is
maybe extremely high dimensional
and it seems like you'd be prone to
overfitting, right, you can prove that
so as the long as the positive and
negative examples are separated
by a margin, right. So in this infinite
dimensional space,so long as, you know,
there is some margin down there
separating the positive and negative
examples,you can prove that perceptron
algorithm will converge to a hypothesis
that perfectly separates the positive
and negative examples. Okay? And then
so after seeing only a finite number of
examples, it'll converge to digital
boundary that perfectly separates
the positive and negative examples,
even though you may in an
infinite dimensional space. Okay?
So let's see.
The proof itself would take me sort of
almost an entire lecture to do,
and there are sort of other things
that I want to do more than that.
So you want to see
the proof of this yourself,
it's actually written up in the
lecture notes that I posted online.
For the purposes of this class'
syllabus, the proof of this result,
you can treat this as optional reading.
And by that, I mean, you know,
it won't appear
on the midterm and you won't be
asked about this specifically in the
problem sets, but I thought it'd be –
I know some of you
are curious after the previous lecture
so why you can prove that, you know,
SVMs can have bounded VC dimension,
even in these infinite dimensional
spaces, and how do you prove things in
these how do you prove learning theory
results in these infinite dimensional
feature spaces. And so the perceptron
bound that I just talked about was
the simplest instance I know of
that you can sort of read
in like half an hour and understand it.
So if you're interested,
there are lecture notes online
for how this perceptron bound
is actually proved.
It's a very [inaudible],
you can prove it in like a page or so,
so go ahead and take a look at that
if you're interested. Okay?
But regardless of
the theoretical results, you know,
the online learning setting
is something that you
that comes reasonably often.
And so, these algorithms
based on stochastic gradient descent
often go very well.
Okay, any questions about this
before I move on?
All right. Cool.
So the last thing I want to do today,
and was the majority of today's lecture,
actually can I switch to PowerPoint
slides, please, is I actually want to
spend most of today's lecture sort of
talking about advice for applying
different machine learning algorithms.
And so, you know, right now, already you
have a, I think, a good understanding
of really the most powerful tools known
to humankind in machine learning.
Right?
And what I want to do today is to
give you some advice
on how to apply them really powerfully
because, you know, the same tool
it turns out that you can
take the same machine learning tool,
say logistic regression,
and you can ask two different people
to apply it to the same problem.
And sometimes one person
will do an amazing job
and it'll work amazingly well,
and the second person will sort of
not really get it to work,
even though it was exactly
the same algorithm. Right?
And so what I want to do today,
in the rest of the time I have today,
is try to convey to you, you know,
some of the methods for how to make sure
you're one of you really know how to
get these learning algorithms
to work well in problems.
So just some caveats on what I'm gonna,
I guess, talk about
in the rest of today's lecture.
Something I want to talk about is
actually not very mathematical
but is also some of the hardest,
most conceptually most difficult
material in this class to understand.
All right?
So this is not mathematical
but this is not easy.
And I want to say this caveat some of
what I'll say today is debatable.
I think most good machine learning
people will agree with
most of what I say
but maybe not everything I say.
And some of what I'll say
is also not good advice
for doing machine learning either,
so I'll say more about this later.
What I'm focusing on today is advice
for how to just get stuff to work.
If you work in the company
and you want to deliver a product
or you're, you know, building a system
and you just want your
machine learning system to work. Okay?
Some of what I'm about to say today
isn't great advice if you goal is to
invent a new machine learning algorithm,
but this is advice
for how to make machine learning
algorithm work and, you know,
and deploy a working system.
So three key areas I'm gonna talk about.
One: diagnostics for debugging
learning algorithms.
Second: sort of talk briefly about
error analyses and ablative analysis.
And third, I want to talk about just
advice for how to get started on a
machine-learning problem.
And one theme that'll come up later is
it turns out you've heard about
premature optimization, right,
in writing software.
This is when
someone over-designs from the start,
when someone, you know,
is writing piece of code
and they choose a subroutine
to optimize heavily.
And maybe you write the subroutine
as assembly or something.
And that's often and many of us have
been guilty of premature optimization,
where we're trying to
get a piece of code to run faster.
And we choose probably a piece of code
and we implement it an assembly,
and really tune and
get to run really quickly.
And it turns out that wasn't the
bottleneck in the code at all. Right?
And we call that premature
optimization.
And in undergraduate programming
classes, we warn people all the time
not to do premature optimization and
people still do it all the time. Right?
And turns out,
a very similar thing happens in
building machine-learning systems.
That many people are often guilty of,
what I call, premature statistical
optimization, where they heavily
optimize part of a machine learning
system and that turns out
not to be the important piece. Okay?
So I'll talk about that later, as well.
So let's first talk about
debugging learning algorithms.
As a motivating example,
let's say you want to build an
anti-spam system.
And let's say you've carefully chosen,
you know, a small set of 100 words
to use as features. All right?
So instead of using 50,000 words,
you've chosen
a small set of 100 features
to use for your anti-spam system.
And let's say you implement
Bayesian logistic regression,
implement gradient descent,
and you get 20 percent test error,
which is unacceptably high. Right?
So this is Bayesian logistic
regression, and so it's just like
maximum likelihood but, you know,
with that additional lambda squared
term. And we're maximizing
rather than minimizing as well,
so there's a minus lambda theta square
instead of plus lambda theta squared.
So the question is,
you implemented your Bayesian
logistic regression algorithm,
and you tested it on your test set
and you got unacceptably high error,
so what do you do next? Right?
So, you know, one thing you could do is
think about the ways
you could improve this algorithm.
And this is probably
what most people will do instead of,
"Well let's sit down and think
what could've gone wrong, and then
we'll try to improve the algorithm."
Well obviously having more training
data could only help,
so one thing you can do is
try to get more training examples.
Maybe you suspect,
that even 100 features was too many,
so you might try to get
a smaller set of features.
What's more common is you might suspect
your features aren't good enough,
so you might spend some time,
look at the email headers,
see if you can figure out
better features for, you know,
finding spam emails or whatever. Right.
And right, so and just sit around
and come up with better features,
such as for email headers.
You may also suspect that gradient
descent hasn't quite converged yet,
and so let's try running gradient
descent a bit longer to see
if that works.
And clearly, that can't hurt, right,
just run gradient descent longer.
Or maybe you remember, you know,
you remember hearing from class that
maybe Newton's method converges better,
so let's try that instead.
You may want to tune the
value for lambda,
because not sure
if that was the right thing,
or maybe you even want to use an SVM
because maybe you think an SVM might
work better than logistic regression.
So I only listed eight things here,
but you can imagine
if you were actually sitting down,
building machine-learning system,
the options to you are endless.
You can think of, you know, hundreds of
ways to improve a learning system.
And some of these things like,
well getting more training examples,
surely that's gonna help, so that seems
like it's a good use of your time. Right?
And it turns out that this approach
of picking ways to improve the learning
algorithm and picking one and going for it,
it might work in the sense that
it may eventually get you to
a working system,
but often it's very time-consuming.
And I think it's often a largely
largely a matter of luck,
whether you end up fixing
what the problem is.
In particular, these eight improvements
all fix very different problems.
And some of them will be fixing problems
that you don't have.
And if you can rule out
six of eight of these,
say, you could
if by somehow
looking at the problem more deeply,
you can figure out
which one of these eight things
is actually the right thing to do,
you can save yourself a lot of time.
So let's see
how we can go about doing that.
The people in industry and in research
that I see that are really good,
would not go and try to
change a learning algorithm randomly.
There are lots of things that obviously
improve your learning algorithm,
but the problem is
there are so many of them
it's hard to know what to do.
So you find all the really good ones
that run various diagnostics
to figure out the problem is
and they think where a problem is. Okay?
So for our motivating story, right, we
said let's say Bayesian logistic
regression test error was 20 percent,
which let's say is unacceptably high.
And let's suppose you suspected
the problem is either overfitting,
so it's high bias,
or you suspect that, you know,
maybe you have two few features
that classify as spam, so there's
Oh excuse me;
I think I wrote that wrong.
Let's firstly so let's forget
forget the tables.
Suppose you suspect the problem is
either high bias or high variance,
and some of the text here
doesn't make sense.
And you want to know
if you're overfitting,
which would be high variance,
or you have too few features
classified as spam,
it'd be high bias.
I had those two reversed, sorry. Okay?
So how can you figure out
whether the problem is one of high bias
or high variance? Right?
So it turns out there's a simple
diagnostic you can look at that will
tell you whether the problem is high
bias or high variance.
If you remember the cartoon we'd seen
previously for high variance problems,
when you have high variance
the training error will be
much lower than the test error.
All right?
When you have a high variance problem,
that's when you're
fitting your training set very well.
That's when you're fitting, you know,
a tenth order polynomial
to 11 data points. All right?
And that's when you're just
fitting the data set very well,
and so your training error will be
much lower than your test error.
And in contrast, if you have high bias,
that's when your training error
will also be high. Right?
That's when your data is quadratic, say,
but you're fitting a linear function to
it and so you aren't even
fitting your training set well.
So just in cartoons, I guess,
this is a this is what a typical
learning curve for high variance looks
like. On your horizontal axis,
I'm plotting the training set size M,
and on vertical axis,
I'm plotting the error.
And so, let's see, you know,
as you increase
if you have a high variance problem,
you'll notice
as the training set size, M, increases,
your test set error will
keep on decreasing.
And so this sort of suggests that, well,
if you can increase
the training set size even further,
maybe if you extrapolate
the green curve out,
maybe that test set error will
decrease even further.
All right?
Another thing that's useful to plot here
is let's say the red horizontal line
is the desired performance
you're trying to reach,
another useful thing to plot
is actually the training error. Right?
And it turns out that
your training error will actually grow
as a function of the training set size
because the larger your training set,
the harder it is to fit, you know,
your training set perfectly. Right?
So this is just a cartoon,
don't take it too seriously,
but in general,
your training error will actually grow
as a function of your training set size.
Because smart training sets,
if you have one data point,
it's really easy to fit that perfectly,
but if you have 10,000 data points,
it's much harder to fit that perfectly.
All right?
And so another diagnostic
for high variance,
and the one that I tend to use more,
is to just look at
training versus test error.
And if there's a large gap between them,
then this suggests that, you know,
getting more training data
may allow you to help close that gap.
Okay？
So this is what the cartoon would look
like when in the case of high variance.
This is what the cartoon looks like
for high bias. Right?
If you look at the learning curve,
you see that the curve for test error
has flattened out already.
And so this is a sign that, you know,
if you get more training examples,
if you extrapolate this curve
further to the right,
it's maybe not likely to
go down much further.
And this is a property of high bias:
that getting more training data
won't necessarily help.
But again, to me
the more useful diagnostic is
if you plot training errors well,
if you look at your training error
as well as your, you know,
hold out test set error.
If you find that
even your training error is high,
then that's a sign that getting more
training data is not going to help.
Right?
In fact, you know, think about it,
training error grows as
a function of your training set size.
And so if your training error
is already above your
level of desired performance,
then getting even more training data
is not going to reduce your
training error down to the
desired level of performance. Right?
Because, you know, your training error
sort of only gets worse as you get
more and more training examples.
So if you extrapolate further to
the right, it's not like this blue line
will come back down to the level of
desired performance. Right?
This will stay up there. Okay?
So for me personally, I actually,
when looking at a curve like the green
curve on test error,
I actually personally tend to find it
very difficult to tell if the curve is
still going down or if it's [inaudible].
Sometimes you can tell,
but very often,
it's somewhat ambiguous.
So for me personally,
the diagnostic I tend to use the most
often to tell if I have a bias problem
or a variance problem is to look at
training and test error and see
if they're very close together
or if they're relatively far apart.
Okay?
And so, going back to the list of fixes,
look at the first fix,
getting more training examples
is a way to fix high variance. Right?
If you have a high variance problem,
getting more training examples
will help.
Trying a smaller set of features:
that also fixes high variance.
All right?
Trying a larger set of features
or adding email features,
these are solutions that fix high bias.
Right?
So high bias being if
your hypothesis was too simple,
you didn't have enough features. Okay?
And so quite often you see
people working on
machine learning problems and
they'll remember that
getting more training examples helps.
And so, they'll build a learning
system, build an anti-spam system
and it doesn't work.
And then they go off and
spend lots of time and money and effort
collecting more training data
because they'll say,
"Oh well, getting more data's
obviously got to help."
But if they had a high bias problem
in the first place,
and not a high variance problem,
it's entirely possible to
spend three months or six months
collecting more and more training data,
not realizing that
it couldn't possibly help. Right?
And so, this actually happens a lot in,
you know, in Silicon Valley and
companies, this happens a lot.
There will often people building
various machine learning systems,
and they'll often you often see people
spending six months
working on fixing a learning algorithm
and you could've told them
six months ago that, you know,
that couldn't possibly have helped.
But because they didn't know
what the problem was,
and they'd easily spend six months
trying to invent new features
or something.
And this is you see this surprisingly
often and this is somewhat depressing.
You could've gone to them and told them,
"I could've told you six months ago that
this was not going to help."
And the six months is not a joke,
you actually see this.
And in contrast,
if you actually figure out the problem's
one of high bias or high variance,
then you can rule out
two of these solutions
and save yourself
many months of fruitless effort. Okay?
I actually want to talk about
these four at the bottom as well.
But before I move on,
let me just check
if there were questions about
what I've talked about so far.
No? Okay, great.
So bias versus variance is
one thing that comes up often.
This bias versus variance
is one common diagnostic.
And so, for other machine learning
problems, it's often up to your
own ingenuity to
figure out your own diagnostics
to figure out what's wrong. All right?
So if a machine-learning algorithm
isn't working,
very often it's up to you to figure out,
you know, to construct your own tests.
Like do you look at the
difference training and test errors
or do you look at something else?
It's often up to your own ingenuity
to construct your own diagnostics
to figure out what's going on.
What I want to do is go through another
example. All right?
And this one is slightly more contrived
but it'll illustrate another common
question that comes up, another
one of the most common issues that comes
up in applying learning algorithms.
So in this example,
it's slightly more contrived,
let's say you implement Bayesian
logistic regression
and you get 2 percent error
on spam mail
and 2 percent error non-spam mail.
Right? So it's rejecting, you know,
2 percent of it's rejecting 98 percent
of your spam mail,
which is fine, so 2 percent of all spam
gets through which is fine, but is also
rejecting 2 percent of your good email,
2 percent of the email
from your friends and
that's unacceptably high, let's say.
And let's say that a simple vector
machine using a linear kernel
gets 10 percent error on spam
and 0.01 percent error on non-spam,
which is more of
the acceptable performance you want.
And let's say for the sake of this
example, let's say you're trying to
build an anti-spam system. Right?
Let's say that you really want to deploy
logistic regression to your customers
because of computational efficiency
or because you need
retrain overnight every day,
and because logistic regression just
runs more easily and more
quickly or something. Okay?
So let's say you
want to deploy logistic regression,
but it's just not working out well.
So question is: What do you do next?
So it turns out that this
the issue that comes up here,
the one other common question that
comes up is a question of
is the algorithm converging.
So you might suspect that maybe the
problem with logistic regression
is that it's just not converging.
Maybe you need to run iterations.
And it turns out that, again if you
look at the optimization objective,
say, logistic regression is,
let's say, optimizing J of theta,
it actually turns out that if you
look at optimizing your objective as a
function of the number of iterations,
when you look at this curve, you know,
it sort of looks like
it's going up but it sort of looks like
there's absentiles.
And when you look at these curves,
it's often very hard to tell
if the curve has already flattened out.
All right?
And you look at these curves a lot
so you can ask:
Well has the algorithm converged?
When you look at the J of theta
like this, it's often hard to tell.
You can run this ten times as long
and see if it's flattened out.
And you can run this ten times as long
and it'll often still look like maybe
it's going up very slowly, or something.
Right? So a better diagnostic for
what logistic regression is converged
than looking at this curve.
The other question you might wonder –
the other thing you might suspect is
a problem is
are you optimizing the right function.
So what you care about,
right, in spam,say, is a
weighted accuracy function like that.
So A of theta is, you know,
sum over your examples of some
weights times whether you got it right.
And so the weight may be
higher for non-spam than for spam mail
because you care about getting your
predictions correct for spam email
much more than non-spam mail, say.
So let's say A of theta is
the optimization objective
that you really care about,
but Bayesian logistic regression is
that it optimizes a quantity like that. Right?
It's this sort of maximum likelihood
thing and then with this two-nom,
you know, penalty thing
that we saw previously.
And you might be wondering:
Is this the right optimization function
to be optimizing. Okay?
And: Or do I maybe need to
change the value for lambda
to change this parameter?
Or: Should I maybe really
be switching to support vector machine
optimization objective?
Okay? Does that make sense?
So the second diagnostic I'm gonna talk
about is let's say you want to figure out
is the algorithm converging, is
the optimization algorithm converging,
or is the problem with
the optimization objective
I chose in the first place? Okay?
So here's the diagnostic you can use.
Let me let right.
So to just reiterate the story, right,
let's say an SVM outperforms Bayesian
logistic regression
but you really want to deploy Bayesian
logistic regression to your problem.
Let me let theta subscript SVM,
be the parameters learned by an SVM,
and I'll let theta subscript BLR
be the parameters learned
by Bayesian logistic regression.
So the optimization objective you care
about is this, you know,
weighted accuracy criteria
that I talked about just now.
And the support vector machine
outperforms Bayesian logistic
regression. And so, you know,
the weighted accuracy on the
support vector-machine parameters is
better than the weighted accuracy for
Bayesian logistic regression.
So further, Bayesian logistic
regression tries to optimize an
optimization objective like that,
which I denoted J theta.
And so, the diagnostic I choose to use
is to see if J of SVM is bigger-than
or less-than J of BLR. Okay?
So I explain this on the next slide.
So we know two facts.
We know that well we know one fact.
We know that a weighted accuracy
of support vector machine, right,
is bigger than this weighted accuracy
of Bayesian logistic regression.
So in order for me to figure out
whether Bayesian logistic regression
is converging,
or whether I'm just optimizing
the wrong objective function,
the diagnostic I'm gonna use
and I'm gonna check
if this equality hold through.
Okay?
So let me explain this,
so in Case 1, right,it's
just those two equations copied over.
In Case 1, let's say that J of SVM is,
indeed, is greater than J of BLR or
J of theta SVM is greater than J of theta BLR
But we know that Bayesian logistic
regression was trying to maximize
J of theta; that's the definition
of Bayesian logistic regression.
So this means that theta
the value of theta output
that Bayesian logistic regression
actually fails to maximize J
because the support back to machine
actually returned the value of theta
that, you know does a better job
out-maximizing J.
And so, this tells me that
Bayesian logistic regression didn't
actually maximize J correctly,
and so the problem is with
the optimization algorithm.
The optimization algorithm hasn't
converged.The other case is as follows,
where J of theta SVM is less-than/equal
to J of theta BLR.
Okay? In this case, what does that mean?
This means that
Bayesian logistic regression
actually attains the higher value for
the optimization objective J then
doesn't support back to machine.
The support back to machine,
which does worse on your optimization
problem, actually does better
on the weighted accuracy measure.
So what this means is that
something that does worse on your
optimization objective, on J,
can actually do better
on the weighted accuracy objective.
And this really means that
maximizing J of theta, you know,
doesn't really correspond that well
to maximizing your weighted accuracy
criteria. And therefore, this tells you
that J of theta is maybe the wrong
optimization objective to be
maximizing. Right?
That just maximizing J of theta
just wasn't a good objective
to be choosing if you care about
the weighted accuracy.
Okay?
Can you raise your hand
if this made sense? Cool, good.
So that tells us whether the problem
is with the optimization objective
or whether it's with
the objective function.
And so going back to this slide,
the eight fixes we had, you notice that
if you run gradient descent for more
iterations that fixes the optimization
algorithm. You try and use this method
fixes the optimization algorithm,
whereas using a different value for
lambda, in that lambda times norm of
data squared, you know, in your
objective, fixes the optimization
objective. And changing to an SVM
is also another way of trying to
fix the optimization objective. Okay?
And so once again, you actually
see this quite often that
actually, you see it very often,
people will have a problem with
the optimization objective
and be working harder and harder
to fix the optimization algorithm.
That's another very common pattern that
the problem is in the
formula from your J of theta,
that often you see people, you know,
just running more and more
iterations of gradient descent.
Like trying Newton's method and trying
conjugate and then trying more and more
crazy optimization algorithms,
whereas the problem was, you know,
optimizing J of theta wasn't going to
fix the problem at all.
Okay?
So there's another example of
when these sorts of diagnostics
will help you figure out
whether you should be fixing your
optimization algorithm or
fixing the optimization objective.
Okay?
Let me think how much time I have.
Hmm, let's see. Well okay, we have time.
Let's do this. Show you
one last example of a diagnostic.
This is one that came up in, you know,
my students' and my work
on flying helicopters.
This one actually, this example is
the most complex of the three examples
I'm gonna do today.
I'm going to somewhat quickly,
and this actually
draws on reinforcement learning which
is something that I'm not gonna
talk about until towards
close to the end of the course here,
but this just a more complicated example
of a diagnostic we're gonna go over.
What I'll do is probably
go over this fairly quickly,
and then after we've talked about
reinforcement learning in the class,
I'll probably actually come back
and redo this exact same example
because you'll understand it
more deeply. Okay?
So some of you know that
my students and I
fly autonomous helicopters,
so how do you get a machine-learning
algorithm to design the controller for
helicopter? This is what we do.
All right? This first step was
you build a simulator for a helicopter,
so, you know,
there's a screenshot of our simulator.
This is just like a
it's like a joystick simulator;
you can fly a helicopter in simulation.
And then you choose a cost function,
it's actually called a
[inaudible] function,
but for this actually
I'll call it cost function.
Say J of theta is, you know,
the expected squared error
in your helicopter's position. Okay?
So this is J of theta is maybe
it's expected square error
or just the square error.
And then we run a
reinforcement-learning algorithm,
you'll learn about RL algorithms
in a few weeks.
You run reinforcement learning
algorithm in your simulator to
try to minimize this cost function;
try to minimize the squared error
of how well you're controlling
your helicopter's position. Okay?
The reinforcement learning algorithm
will output some parameters,
which I'm denoting theta subscript RL,
and then you'll use that
to fly your helicopter.
So suppose you run this learning
algorithm and you get out
a set of controller parameters,
theta subscript RL,
that gives much worse performance
than a human pilot.
Then what do you do next?
And in particular, you know,
corresponding to the three steps above,
there are three natural things
you can try. Right?
You can try to
oh, the bottom of the slide
got chopped off.
You can try to improve the simulator.
And maybe you think
your simulator's isn't that accurate,
you need to capture the
aerodynamic effects more accurately.
You need to capture
the airflow and the turbulence affects
around the helicopter more accurately.
Maybe you need to
modify the cost function.
Maybe your square error isn't cutting
it. Maybe what a human pilot does
isn't just optimizing square area
but it's something more subtle.
Or maybe the reinforcement-learning
algorithm isn't working;
maybe it's not quite converging or
something. Okay?
So these are the diagnostics
that I actually used,
and my students and I actually use
to figure out what's going on.
Actually, why don't you just
think about this for a second
and think what you'd do, and then
I'll go on and tell you what we do.
All right, so let me tell you what –
how we do this and see
whether it's the same as yours or not.
And if you have a better idea than I do,
let me know and
I'll let you try it on my helicopter.
So here's a reasoning
that I wanted to experiment, right.
So, yeah, let's say the controller
output by our reinforcement-learning
algorithm does poorly.
Well suppose the following
three things hold true.
Suppose the contrary, I guess.
Suppose that the helicopter simulator
is accurate, so let's assume we have an
accurate model of our helicopter.
And let's suppose that
the reinforcement learning algorithm,
you know, correctly controls the
helicopter in simulation,
so we tend to run a learning algorithm
in simulation so that, you know,
the learning algorithm can crash a
helicopter and it's fine. Right?
So let's assume our
reinforcement-learning algorithm
correctly controls the helicopter
so as to minimize
the cost function J of theta.
And let's suppose that
minimizing J of theta
does indeed correspond to accurate
or the correct autonomous flight.
If all of these things held true,
then that means that the parameters,
theta RL, should actually fly well
on my real helicopter. Right?
And so the fact that the
learning control parameters, theta RL,
does not fly well on my helicopter,
that sort of means that
ones of these three assumptions
must be wrong and
I'd like to figure out which of these
three assumptions is wrong. Okay?
So these are the diagnostics we use.
First one is we look at the controller
and see if it
even flies well in simulation.
Right?
So the simulator of the helicopter
that we did the learning on,
and so if the learning algorithm
flies well in the simulator
but it doesn't fly well on my real
helicopter, then that tells me the
problem is probably in the simulator.
Right?
My simulator predicts the helicopter's
controller will fly well
but it doesn't actually fly well in real
life，so could be the problem's
in the simulator and
we should spend out efforts
improving the accuracy of our simulator.
Otherwise,
let me write theta subscript human,
be the human control policy. All right?
So let's go ahead and ask a human
to fly the helicopter,
it could be in the simulator,
it could be in real life,
and let's measure, you know,
the means squared error
of the human pilot's flight.
And let's see if the human pilot
does better or worse
than the learned controller,
in terms of optimizing this
objective function J of theta. Okay?
So if the human does worse,
if even a very good human pilot attains
a worse value on my optimization
objective, on my cost function,
than my learning algorithm,
then the problem is in the
reinforcement-learning algorithm.
Because my reinforcement-learning
algorithm was trying to minimize J of
theta, but a human actually
attains a lower value for
J of theta than does my algorithm.
And so that tells me that clearly
my algorithm's not managing to
minimize J of theta and that tells me
the problem's in the
reinforcement learning algorithm.
And finally, if J of theta –
if the human actually
attains a larger value for theta
excuse me,
if the human actually attains
a larger value for J of theta,
the human actually has, you know,
larger mean squared error for the
helicopter position than does my
reinforcement learning algorithms,
that's I like but I like the way
the human flies much better than
my reinforcement learning algorithm.
So if that holds true,
then clearly the problem's
in the cost function, right,
because the human does worse
on my cost function
but flies much better
than my learning algorithm.
And so that means the problem's
in the cost function.
It means
oh excuse me, I meant minimizing it,
not maximizing it,
there's a typo on the slide,
because that means that
minimizing the cost function
my learning algorithm does a better job
but doesn't fly as well as a human pilot.
So that tells you that
minimizing the cost function doesn't
correspond to good autonomous flight.
And what you should do is go back and
see if you can change J of theta.
Okay?
And so for those
reinforcement learning problems,
you know, if something doesn't work
often reinforcement learning
algorithms just work
but when they don't work,
these are the sorts of diagnostics
you use to figure out
should we be focusing on the simulator,
or changing the cost function,
or on changing the
reinforcement learning algorithm.
And again,
if you don't know
which of your three problems it is,
it's entirely possible, you know,
to spend two years, whatever, changing,
building a better simulator
for your helicopter.
But it turns out that
modeling helicopter aerodynamics
is an active area of research.
There are people, you know, writing
entire PhD theses on this still.
So it's entirely possible to go out
and spend six years
and write a PhD thesis
and build a much better helicopter
simulator, but if you're
fixing the wrong problem
it's not gonna help.
So quite often,
you need to come up with
your own diagnostics to figure out
what's happening in an algorithm
when something is going wrong.
And unfortunately I don't know of
what I've described are sort of maybe
some of the most common diagnostics
that I've used, that I've seen, you know,
to be useful for many problems.
But very often,
you need to come up with your own
for your own specific learning problem.
And I just want to point out that
even when the learning algorithm is
working well, it's often a good idea
to run diagnostics,
like the ones I talked about,
to make sure you really
understand what's going on. All right?
And this is useful for a couple of
reasons. One is that
diagnostics like these
will often help you to understand
your application problem better.
So some of you will, you know,
graduate from Stanford
and go on to get some
amazingly high-paying job to
apply machine-learning algorithms to
some application problem of, you know,
significant economic interest. Right?
And you're gonna be working on one
specific important machine learning
application for many months,
or even for years.
One of the most valuable things for you
personally will be for you to get in –
for you personally to get in an
intuitive understanding of what works
and what doesn't work your problem.
Sort of right now in the industry,
in Silicon Valley or around the world,
there are many companies with important
machine learning problems and there are
often people working on
the same machine learning problem,
you know, for many months
or for years on end.
And when you're doing that, I mean
solving a really important problem
using learning algorithms,
one of the most valuable things is
just your own personal intuitive
understanding of the problem. Okay?
And diagnostics, like the sort I talked
about, will be one way for you
to get a better and better
understanding of these problems.
It turns out, by the way,
there are some of Silicon Valley
companies that outsource
their machine learning.
So there's sometimes, you know,
whatever. They're a company in Silicon
Valley and they'll, you know,
hire a firm in New York to run
all their learning algorithms for them.
And I'm not a businessman,
but I personally think
that's often a terrible idea because
if your expertise,if your understanding
of your data is given, you know,
to an outsource agency, then if you
don't maintain that expertise,
if there's a problem you really care
about then it'll be your own, you know,
understanding of the problem that you
build up over months that'll be really
valuable. And if that knowledge is
outsourced, you don't get to
keep that knowledge yourself.
I personally think
that's a terrible idea.
But I'm not a businessman,
but I just see people do that a lot,
and just. Let's see.
Another reason for running diagnostics
like these is actually in
writing research papers, right?
So diagnostics and error analyses,
which I'll talk about in a minute,
often help to convey insight
about the problem and
help justify your research claims.
So for example,
rather than writing a research paper,
say, that's says, you know,
"Oh well here's an algorithm that works.
I built this helicopter and it flies,"
or whatever, it's often
much more interesting to say,
"Here's an algorithm that works,
and it works because of a specific
component X. And moreover, here's the
diagnostic that gives you justification
that shows X was the thing that
fixed this problem,"
and that's where you made it work.
Okay?
So that leads me into a discussion
on error analysis,
which is often good machine learning
practice, is a way for understanding
what your sources of errors are.
So what I call error analyses –
and let's check questions about this.
Yeah?
Student:What ended up
being wrong with the helicopter?
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Oh, don't know.
Let's see.
We've flown so many times.
The thing that is most difficult a
helicopter is actually building a very
I don't know. It changes all the time.
Quite often, it's actually the
simulator. Building an accurate
simulator of a helicopter is very hard.
Yeah. Okay. So for error analyses,
this is a way for figuring out
what is working in your algorithm
and what isn't working.
And we're gonna talk about two specific
examples. So there are many learning –
there are many sort of AI systems,
many machine learning systems,
that combine many different components
into a pipeline.
So here's sort of a contrived example
for this, not dissimilar in many ways
from the actual machine learning
systems you see.
So let's say you want to
recognize people from images.
This is a picture of one of my friends.
So you take this input in camera image,
say, and you often run it through a long
pipeline. So for example,
the first thing you may do
may be preprocess the image
and remove the background,
so you remove the background.
And then you run a face
detection algorithm,
so a machine learning algorithm
to detect people's faces. Right?
And then, you know, let's say you want
to recognize the identity of the
person, right,
this is your application.
You then segment of the eyes,
segment of the nose, and have
different learning algorithms
to detect the mouth and so on. I know;
she might not want to be friend
after she sees this.
And then having found all these
features, based on, you know, what the
nose looks like, what the eyes looks
like, whatever, then you feed
all the features into
a logistic regression algorithm.
And your logistic regression
or soft match regression, or whatever,
will tell you the identity of this
person. Okay?
So this is what error analysis is.
You have a long complicated pipeline
combining many machine learning
components. Many of these would be used
in learning algorithms.
And so, it's often very useful to figure
out how much of your error can be
attributed to each of these components.
So what we'll do in a typical error
analysis procedure is we'll repeatedly
plug in the ground-truth for each
component and see how the accuracy
changes.So what I mean by that
is the figure on the bottom left
bottom right, let's say the overall
accuracy of the system is 85 percent.
Right? Then I want to know where
my 15 percent of error comes from.
And so what I'll do is
I'll go to my test set and
I'll actually code it and
oh, instead of actually implement
my correct background removal.
So actually, go in and give it,
give my algorithm what is the
correct background versus foreground.
And if I do that,
let's color that blue to denote that
I'm giving that ground-truth data
in the test set,
let's assume our accuracy
increases to 85.1 percent. Okay?
And now I'll go in and, you know,
give my algorithm the ground-truth,
face detection output.
So I'll go in and actually on my test set
I'll just tell the algorithm
where the face is.
And if I do that,
let's say my algorithm's accuracy
increases to 91 percent, and so on.
And then I'll go for each of these
components and just give it the
ground-truth label for each of the
components, because say, like,
the nose segmentation algorithm's
trying to figure out where the nose is.
I just in and tell it where the nose is
so that it doesn't have to figure that
out. And as I do this, one component
through the other, you know, I end up
giving it the correct output label
and end up with 100 percent accuracy.
And now you can look at this table
I'm sorry this is cut off on the bottom,
it says logistic regression
100 percent.
Now you can look at this table and see,
you know, how much giving the
round-truth labels for each of
these components could help
boost your final performance.
In particular,
if you look at this table,
you notice that when I added
the face detection ground-truth,
my performance jumped
from 85.1 percent accuracy
to 91 percent accuracy. Right?
So this tells me that
if only I can get better face detection,
maybe I can boost my accuracy
by 6 percent. Whereas in contrast,
when I, you know, say plugged in better,
I don't know, background removal,
my accuracy improved from 85 to 85.1
percent. And so, this sort of
diagnostic also tells you that
if your goal is to
improve the system,
it's probably a waste of your time
to try to improve your background
subtraction. Because if even if you got
the ground-truth, this is gives you,
at most, 0.1 percent accuracy,
whereas if you do better face
detection, maybe there's a much larger
potential for gains there. Okay?
So this sort of diagnostic, again,
is very useful because if
your goal is to improve the system,
there are so many different pieces
you can easily choose
to spend the next three months on.
Right? And choosing the right piece
is critical, and
this sort of diagnostic tells you
what's the piece that may actually
be worth your time to work on.
There's sort of another type of analyses
that's sort of the opposite of
what I just talked about.
The error analysis I just talked about
tries to explain the difference between
the current performance and perfect
performance, whereas this sort of
ablative analysis tries to explain
the difference between some baselines,
some really bad performance
and your current performance.
So for this example,
let's suppose you've built
a very good anti-spam classifier for
adding lots of clever features to your
logistic regression algorithm. Right?
So you added features for
spam correction, for, you know,
sender host features,
for email header features,
email text parser features,
JavaScript parser features,
features for embedded images,
and so on.
So now let's say
you preview the system
and you want to figure out, you know,
how well did each of these how much
did each of these components actually
contribute? Maybe you want to
write a research paper and
claim this was the piece
that made the big difference.
Can you actually document that claim
and justify it?
So in ablative analysis,
here's what we do.
So in this example, let's say that
simple logistic regression
without any of your clever improvements
get 94 percent performance.
And you want to figure out what
accounts for your improvement
from 94 to 99.9 percent performance.
So in ablative analysis and so instead
of adding components one at a time,
we'll instead remove components one
at a time to see how it rates.
So start with your overall system,
which is 99 percent accuracy.
And then we remove spelling correction
and see how much performance drops.
Then we'll remove
the sender host features and see
how much performance drops, and so on.
All right? And so,
in this contrived example,
you see that, I guess,
the biggest drop occurred when you
remove the text parser features.
And so you can then make a credible case
that, you know, the text parser
features where what really made the
biggest difference here. Okay?
And you can also tell,
for instance, that, I don't know,
removing the sender host features
on this line, right,
performance dropped from 99.9 to 98.9.
And so this also means that
in case you want to
get rid of the sender host features
to speed up computational something
that would be a good candidate
for elimination. Okay?
Student:Are there any guarantees
that if you shuffle around the order
in which you drop those features that
you'll get the same
Instructor (Andrew Ng):Yeah. Let's
address the question:
What if you shuffle
in which you remove things?
The answer is no.
There's no guarantee
you'd get the similar result.
So in practice,
sometimes there's a fairly natural of
ordering for both types of analyses,
the error analyses and ablative
analysis, sometimes there's a fairly
natural ordering in which you add
things or remove things,
sometimes there's isn't.
And quite often, you either choose
one ordering and just go for it or
And don't think of these analyses as
sort of formulas that are constants,
though; I mean
feel free to invent your own, as well.
You know one of the things that's done
quite often is take the overall system
and just remove one
and then put it back,
then remove a different one
then put it back
until all of these things are done.
Okay.
So the very last thing I want to talk
about is sort of this general advice
for how to get started
on a learning problem.
So here's a cartoon description on
two broad to get started on learning
problem. The first one is
carefully design your system,
so you spend a long time
designing exactly the right features,
collecting the right data set,
and designing the right algorithmic
structure, then you implement it
and hope it works. All right?
The benefit of this sort of approach is
you get maybe nicer,
maybe more scalable algorithms,
and maybe you come up with
new elegant learning algorithms.
And if your goal is to, you know,
contribute to basic research
in machine learning,
if your goal is to invent
new machine learning algorithms,
this process of slowing down
and thinking deeply about the problem,
you know, that is sort of the right way
to go about is think deeply about
a problem and invent new solutions.
Second sort of approach is
what I call build-and-fix,
which is we input something
quick and dirty
and then you run error analyses
and diagnostics
to figure out what's wrong
and you fix those errors.
The benefit of this second type of
approach is that it'll often get your
application working much more quickly.
And especially with those of you,
if you end up working in a company,
and sometimes if you end up working
in a company, you know, very often
it's not the best product that wins;
it's the first product to market that
wins. And so there's
especially in the industry.
There's really something to be said for,
you know, building a system quickly
and getting it deployed quickly.
And the second approach of
building a quick-and-dirty,
I'm gonna say hack and then fixing
the problems will actually get you
to a system that works well
much more quickly.
And the reason is very often it's really
not clear what parts of a system
are easier to think of to build
and therefore what you need
to spends lot of time focusing on.
So there's that example
I talked about just now. Right?
For identifying people, say.
And with a big complicated
learning system like this,
a big complicated pipeline like this,
it's really not obvious at the outset
which of these components you should
spend lots of time working on. Right?
And if you didn't know that
preprocessing wasn't
the right component,
you could easily have spent
three months working on
better background subtraction,
not knowing that it's just
not gonna ultimately matter.
And so the only way to find out
what really works was
inputting something quickly
and you find out what parts
and find out what parts are really
the hard parts to implement,
or what parts are hard parts that
could make a difference in performance.
In fact, say that
if your goal is to
build a people recognition system,
a system like this
is actually far too complicated
as your initial system.
Maybe after you're prototyped
a few systems, and you
converged a system like this.
But if this is your first system
you're designing,
this is much too complicated.
Also, this is a very
concrete piece of advice, and
this applies to your projects as well.
If your goal is to
build a working application,
Step 1 is actually probably not
to design a system like this.
Step 1 is where you would
plot your data.
And very often,
and if you just take the data
you're trying to predict and
just plot your data, plot X, plot Y,
plot your data
everywhere you can think of, you know,
half the time you look at it and go,
"Gee, how come all those numbers
are negative?
I thought they should be positive.
Something's wrong with this dataset."
And it's about half the time
you find something
obviously wrong with your data
or something very surprising.
And this is something you find out
just by plotting your data,
and that you won't find out be
implementing these big
complicated learning algorithms on it.
Plotting the data sounds so simple,
it was one of the pieces of advice that
lots of us give
but hardly anyone follows,
so you can take that for what it's worth.
Let me just reiterate,
what I just said here may be bad advice
if your goal is to come up with
new machine learning algorithms.
All right? So for me personally,
the learning algorithm I use the most
often is probably logistic regression
because I have code lying around.
So give me a learning problem,
I probably won't try anything
more complicated than
logistic regression on it first.
And it's only after trying
something really simple and
figure our what's easy,
what's hard, then you
know where to focus your efforts.
But again, if your goal is to invent
new machine learning algorithms,
then you sort of
don't want to hack up something
and then add another hack to fix it,
and hack it even more to fix it. Right?
So if your goal is to
do novel machine learning research,
then it pays to
think more deeply about the problem
and not gonna follow this specifically.
Shoot, you know what? All right,
sorry if I'm
late but I just have two more slides
so I'm gonna go through these quickly.
And so, this is what I think of as
premature statistical optimization,
where quite often, just like
premature optimization of code,
quite often people will prematurely
optimize one component of a big
complicated machine learning system.
Okay? Just two more slides.
This was –this is a sort of cartoon that
highly influenced my own thinking.
It was based on a paper
written by Christos Papadimitriou.
This is how progress this is how
developmental progress of research
often happens. Right?
Let's say you want to
build a mail delivery robot,
so I've drawn a circle there
that says mail delivery robot.
And it seems like a useful thing to
have. Right?
You know free up people,
don't have to deliver mail.
So what to deliver mail,
obviously you need a robot
to wander around indoor environments
and you need a robot to manipulate
objects and pickup envelopes.
And so, you need to
build those two components
in order to get a mail delivery robot.
And so I've drawing those two components
and little arrows to denote that,
you know, obstacle avoidance is needed
or would help build your mail delivery
robot.Well for obstacle for avoidance,
clearly, you need a robot
that can navigate and
you need to detect objects
so you can avoid the obstacles.
Now we're gonna use computer vision
to detect the objects.
And so, we know that, you know,
lighting sometimes changes, right,
depending on whether it's the morning
or noontime or evening.
This is lighting causes
the color of things to change,
and so you need an object detection
system that's invariant to the
specific colors of an object. Right?
Because lighting changes, say.
Well color, or RGB values,
is represented by three-dimensional
vectors. And so you need to learn
when two colors might be the same thing,
when two, you know, visual appearance
of two colors may be the same thing as
just the lighting change or something.
And to understand that properly,
we can go out and study
differential geometry of 3d manifolds
because that helps us
build a sound theory
on which to develop our
3d similarity learning algorithms.
And to really understand the
fundamental aspects of this problem,
we have to study the
complexity of non-Riemannian
geometries. And on and on it goes until
eventually you're proving
convergence bounds for sampled of
non-monotonic logic.
I don't even know what this is
because I just made it up.
Whereas in reality, you know,
chances are that link isn't real.
Color variance just barely helped
object recognition maybe.
I'm making this up.
Maybe differential geometry was hardly
gonna help 3d similarity learning
and that link's also gonna fail.
Okay?
So, each of these circles
can represent a person,
or a research community,
or a thought in your head.
And there's a very real chance that
maybe there are all these papers
written on differential geometry of 3d
manifolds, and they are written because
some guy once told someone else that
it'll help 3d similarity learning.
And, you know, it's like
"A friend of mine told me that
color invariance would help
in object recognition,
so I'm working on color invariance.
And now I'm gonna tell a friend of mine
that his thing will help my problem.
And he'll tell a friend of his that
his thing will help with his problem."
And pretty soon, you're working on
convergence bound for sampled
non-monotonic logic, when in reality
none of these will see the light of day
of your mail delivery robot. Okay?
I'm not criticizing the role of theory.
There are very powerful theories,
like the theory of VC dimension, which
is far, far, far to the right of this.
So VC dimension is about
as theoretical as it can get.
And it's clearly had a huge impact
on many applications.
And there's, you know, dramatically
advanced data machine learning.
And another example is theory of
NP-hardness as again, you know,
is about theoretical as it can get.
It's like a huge application
on all of computer science,
the theory of NP-hardness.
But when you are off working on
highly theoretical things, I guess,
to me personally
it's important to keep in mind
are you working on something like
VC dimension, which is high impact,
or are you working on something like
convergence bound for sampled
non-monotonic logic,
which you're only hoping
has some peripheral relevance
to some application. Okay?
For me personally, I tend to
work on an application only if I
excuse me. For me personally,
and this is a personal choice,
I tend to trust something only if
I personally can see a link
from the theory I'm working on
all the way back to an application.
And if I don't personally see
a direct link from
what I'm doing to an application then,
you know, then that's fine.
Then I can choose to work on theory,
but I wouldn't necessarily trust that
what the theory I'm working on
will relate to an application,
if I don't personally
see a link all the way back.
Just to summarize.
One lesson to take away from today is
I think time spent coming up with
diagnostics for learning algorithms
is often time well spent.
It's often up to your own ingenuity
to come up with great diagnostics.
And just when I personally, when I
work on machine learning algorithm,
it's not uncommon for me to be spending
like between a third and often half of
my time just writing diagnostics
and trying to figure out
what's going right and what's going wrong.
Sometimes it's tempting not to, right,
because you want to be implementing
learning algorithms and making
progress. You don't want to be spending
all this time, you know, implementing
tests on your learning algorithms;
it doesn't feel like when you're doing
anything. But when I implement
learning algorithms,
at least a third, and quite often
half of my time, is actually spent
implementing those tests and you can
figure out what to work on.
And I think it's actually one of
the best uses of your time.
Talked about error analyses
and ablative analyses,
and lastly talked about, you know,
different approaches and the risks of
premature statistical optimization.
Okay.
Sorry I ran you over.
I'll be here for a few more minutes
for your questions.
That's [inaudible] today.